[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
好的。
This is CS50, Harvard University's introduction to the intellectual enterprises of computer science and the arts of programming.
这里是 CS50，哈佛大学计算机科学和编程艺术的入门课程。
My name is David Malan, and I actually took this course myself, back in 1996.
我叫大卫-马兰（David Malan），其实在 1996 年，我自己就上过这门课了。
I was a sophomore at the time.
当时我上大二。
I was actually concentrating in government, because a year prior, as a first year, I'd come into Harvard thinking that I liked history and constitutional law and similar classes in high school.
我的专业是政府学，刚入学哈佛时我认为自己喜欢历史和宪法，就像高中时类似课程一样。
And so when I got here, I rather gravitated toward that which was familiar.
当我来到这里时，我更倾向于熟悉的事物。
I figured, if I liked and if I were good at that particular subject in high school, then that's presumably who I'm supposed to be here.
我觉得，如果我在高中时喜欢并擅长某门学科，很自然地在这里也会一样。
But it wasn't until sophomore year that I got up the nerve to step foot in the CS50 classroom, and even then, it was only out of curiosity.
直到大二，我才鼓起勇气踏进 CS50 教室，即便如此，也只是出于好奇。
Like I had no intention of studying computer science of even taking CS50 when I got to campus.
刚进校园时，我根本没打算学习计算机科学，没有想着选 CS50 这门课程。
But people were talking about it, and there was a lot of beware.
但不少人都提到这门课，说这课对初学者不友好。
And it was perhaps for the initiated only, and I didn't really ultimately what computer science was.
而且，这也许只是为初学者准备的。可能上到最后，我还是不知道计算机科学是个啥。
But for me, the light bulb went off.
但对我而言，就像灵光乍现一样。
I found that, contrary to what I'd seen in high school, where I saw friends of mine like programming away in the computer lab, heads down, antisocially just doing whatever it was they were doing,
我发现与我在高中时所见不同，那时我看到我的朋友们在计算机实验室里埋头编程，
沉浸在自己的世界中，看起来很孤僻，只是单纯地在做着什么事情。
it really wasn't that, once I got to this particular class and this particular place.
但当我上了这门特别的课程，踏入这个特别的领域后，发现实际情况才不是那样。
It was much more about problem solving more generally and just learning how to express yourself in code, in different languages.
这门课程更多地关注问题解决的方法，以及学习如何用不同的编程语言来表达自己。
So that you can actually solve problems of interest to you.
你就能真正解决自己感兴趣的问题了。
Even if you have no intention of being a computer scientist or an engineer, but just want to be able to solve problems, analyze data do interesting things, in the arts, humanities, social sciences,
即使你无意成为一名计算机科学家或工程师，
只是希望能够在艺术、人文、社科、物理或是别的等等领域
physical sciences, or really any other field.
解决问题、分析数据、做有趣的事情。
And indeed, this particular path led me to computer science, but the hope for CS50 more generally is that, indeed, you
事实上，这条特别的道路将我引向了计算机科学。但总体上 CS50 的目标是
just find your way to applying principles that you'll learn over the coming months to whatever field is of interest to you.
你会在接下来的几个月里学到一些原则，
并希望你能找到应用这些原则的方法，无论你对哪个领域感兴趣。
With that said, it was definitely a lot of work and not without its frustrations for me.
这对我来说绝对是一项艰巨的工作，而且有不少挫折。
But there was no better feeling than like banging your head proverbial against the wall for some number of hours, even days, trying to fix a bug, a mistake in your code.
花费几个小时，甚至几天的时间，努力修复代码中的错误和 bug ，就像拿头撞墙一样嗯怼。
And then, oh my God, the rush of emotion of accomplishment of pride of exhaustion when you finally solve some problem that's really been weighing on you.
然后，我的天啊，终于解决了某个一直压在心头的难题时，
那种成就感、自豪感、疲惫感一下子激荡开来。
It's just so incredibly gratifying but also empowering.
这让我感到特别欣慰，同时也锻炼了自己的能力。
Because unlike a lot of fields, like computer science was built by humans themselves.
因为与很多领域不同，计算机科学是由人类自己建立起来的。
*注：指计算机系统是一套人造物，而非数学或者物理一样发现自然规律。
And so if a human built this, surely, you, another human, can understand it as well.
因此，前人搭建起大厦，你肯定也能理解它。
And so even though there's going to be some distractions along the way, you're going to see what looks incredibly cryptic, if you've never programmed before.
尽管一路上会有些许波折，而且如果你以前没有编程经验，你可能会觉得这些内容相当神秘。
Over time and with practice, everything just starts to make more sense.
随着时间推移和实践积累，一切都会变得明晰。
And with time and with practice, you just get better at this particular field.
时间加上实践，你会在这一领域越发娴熟。
And indeed, really, the key to success in programming in general is just to allow yourself enough time.
事实上，编程成功的关键在于给自己留出足够的时间。
And so at least, thankfully, I quickly got into the habit of starting early in the week, for instance, when writing actual code.
而幸运的是，我很快养成了一周早早开始写代码的习惯。
Why? Because you're going to run up against a wall.
为啥？因为你会碰壁。
You're not going to see some bug.
你可能找不到某些错误（bug）的原因。
Something's not going to jump out at you, and that's fine.
有时候问题可能没那么显而易见，这特别正常。
That's when you call it a day, take a break, move onto something else, and then just come back to it.
这时，你可以暂时收工休息，做点别的，然后再回来继续解决它。
And that's what keeps programming fun for me, even all of these years later, whether it's teaching or actually applying it.
这正是多年后，无论是教授编程还是实际应用编程，都让我觉得编程依然有趣的原因。
But there's, down the road, a history of an MIT hack, and it looked a little something like this, in yesteryear.
在过去的历史中，MIT 曾经发生过一次恶作剧，大致情况是这样的。
And there was a little sigh the MIT students, when they made this hack.
当时，MIT 的学生制造了一次恶作剧，
On the wall it says, getting an education from MIT is like drinking from a fire hose, which indeed they have connected to what should have been otherwise just a water fountain.
墙上写着："在 MIT 学知识就像从消防栓喝水"。
他们还把消防栓连接到原本只是普通饮水机的地方。
*注：这是形容 MIT 课程内容量大管饱，非常有挑战性和难度。
And that's going to be what it feels like, sometimes, not just in computer science per se, but just an unfamiliar field.
这有时候也许会让人感到有点吃不消，
不仅仅在计算机科学，任何一个不熟悉的领域都一样。
If you're not from STEM, if you're not from CS, that's fine.
如果你不是来自 STEM（科学、技术、工程、数学），或者 CS（计算机专业），那也没关系。
But so much of it, ultimately, is going to be absorbed by you and going to be within your grasp by terms end.
但最终，你会吸收其中的大部分知识，并且在学期结束时牢牢掌握。
So just keep in mind, that's very much the intent, but you'll be amazed what you're able to create, to accomplish, just three or so months hence.
所以请记住，这正是课程的目标。你将会惊讶于在接下来的三个月左右，你所能创造和完成的事情。
Indeed, 2/3 of you, contrary to what you might think are assume, have never taken a CS class before.
事实上，你们当中有三分之二的人从未上过 CS 课程，这与你们可能认为的情况恰恰相反。
So it's absolutely not the case that the person to the left or the right surely must know more than you.
所以，绝对不是说左边或右边的人肯定比你懂得多。
Indeed, it's quite the opposite.
而情况恰恰相反。
And as you'll see in the coming weeks, as you write your own code and solve your own problems, what ultimately matters in this course is not so much where you end up relative to your classmates
在接下来的几周里，随着你编写自己的代码并解决问题，
你会明白在这门课程中最重要的并不是相对于你的同学取得什么样的成绩，
but where you end up relative to yourself when you began.
而是相对于你开始时自己，取得了什么样的进步和成长。
And it really is all about that delta, whether you've programmed or not, just getting something out of a class like this.
真正重要的是前后的改变，
不管你以前是否有过编程经验，从这样的课程中都能得到一些宝贵收获。
And if it does take time, and if you do feel those frustrations, but you simultaneously eventually feel that sense of accomplishment, that just means it's all working.
这确实需要时间，如果你感到沮丧，但同时最终体会到成就感，
那就意味着一切都在起作用。这是很正常的过程。
And indeed, hopefully, all the more worthwhile and gratifying, ultimately, as a result.
嗯，希望所有的努力最终都变得更加值得和令人满足。
So what are we going to do in the coming weeks?
那么，未来几周我们该做些什么呢？
So here we are in week zero.
现在是第 0 周。
We'll soon see why computers and computer scientists start counting, if you will, from 0.
我们马上就会知道，为什么计算机和计算机科学家要从 0 开始计数。
But week 0, is one in which we explore computational thinking, thinking like a computer, and starting to clean up your thought processes.
但第 0 周，我们将探索计算思维，像计算机一样思考，并开始整理你的思维过程。
Getting you to think, to solve problems more methodically, and then ultimately, translating that into code.
让你更系统地思考、更有方法地解决问题，最终将这些转化为代码。
And some of you might recognize this environment here, a.k.a. Scratch, coincidentally also from MIT.
有些人可能认识这个环境，也叫做 Scratch，恰巧它也来自麻省理工学院。
You might have used it in grade school.
你可能在小学时用过。
We'll use it today and a little bit this weekend in the course's first homework assignment or problem set.
我们将在今天和本周末的第一份作业或问题集中用到这个。
But not so much to play around in a way that you might have if you did use it in yesteryears, but to explore ideas of computer science and programming
但这并不是为了让你像过去那样玩一玩，而是为了探索计算机科学和编程中
that we're going to use and reuse every week hereafter as well.
那些我们以后每周都重复使用的理念。
Thereafter, we're going to transition just next week to week one, so to speak.
此后，我们将在下周过渡到 Week 1。
Whereby, we'll introduce you to a more traditional language, a lower level language, an older language called C.
在这个过程中，会介绍一种更传统、较低级别的编程语言，一种古老的语言，叫做 C 语言。
And in C, you're going to use your keyboard, not so much your mouse and pointing and clicking, but you're going to write code that soon is going to look a little something like this.
在 C 语言中，你将更多地使用键盘，而不是鼠标选择和点击。
你将编写的代码很快会看起来类似于这样。
And if you've programmed before, you can probably glean what this is going to do.
如果你以前编过程序，大概就能明白这要做什么。
If you've never programmed before, which is the case for most of you, this too will soon make sense.
如果你以前从未学过编程（大多数人都是这种情况），也很快就明白了。
But this is the most canonical program that most any programmer ever writes
其实这是大多数程序员编写的最经典的程序——
called Hello, World, and indeed, that and all of the surrounding syntax above and below just that sentence Hello, World, will soon make all the more sense.
叫做 "Hello, World"。这句话及其上下文中的所有语法，很快都会变得更加容易理解。
You'll learn how to use industry-standard tools, so to speak.
你将学习如何使用业界标准的工具，可以这么说。
Pictured here is something called Visual Studio code, or VS Code.
图中所示的是 Visual Studio Code，简称 VS Code。
You'll use a cloud based version of it initially, so you don't have to suffer with any technical difficulties or headaches like that.
最初你将使用基于云的版本，因此不必担心为了解决任何技术问题而烦恼。
It'll just work right off the bat, but we'll use that to others ultimately to then explore ideas in computer science, principles that you can apply.
它一开始就能直接工作，我们将用 VS Code
探索计算机科学中的其他想法和原则，以便你可以应用它们。
And we'll take a look underneath the hood, so to speak, of your computer at your memory or RAM, Random Access Memory, where all of the data is ultimately going to be stored.
我们将从电脑盖下看一看内存也就是 RAM（随机存取存储器），所有数据最终都将存储在这里。
We'll also take a look thereafter at bugs. A bug is a mistake in a program.
之后，我们还将研究程序中的错误。错误在程序中被称为 bug。
Here is an actual bug in an actual computer in yesteryear, but we'll teach you how to debug programs, find your own mistakes, find others' mistakes, and improve that code as well.
这是一张真虫子（bug）图片，我们会教你如何调试（debug）程序，
找到自己的错误（bug），找到别人的bug，并改进代码。
We'll transition then to algorithms, step-by-step instructions for solving some problems, which we'll touch on today too.
然后，我们将过渡到算法，也就是解决一些问题的分步指导，我们今天也会涉及到一点点。
And if you picture here, this is actually a pretty representative problem.
看看这个，这实际上是一个相当典型的问题。
Odds are, you haven't had to deal with something like this, but it's representative sorting, for instance.
你可能从前没接触过，但这是一种代表性的排序方式。
If you think of each of these small bars as being a small number, each of the bigger bars is being a bigger number,
如果你把每个短条形看作一个小数，长条形看作一个更大的数，
you might wonder, well, how could you as a human sort all of these bars, like get all the short bars over here, all the big bars over there?
你可能会想，咱人类会怎么把所有这些条形进行排序，
把所有短的条形移到这边，所有长的条形移到那边？
Well, odds are, if you're like me, you would probably kind of eyeball it, and if you could physically interact, you might just start grabbing the smallest elements first, put them over on the left.
好吧，也许会像我一样先看看，如果你可以用身体互动，
你可能会先抓取最小的元素，把它们放在左边。
Maybe grab the biggest elements, put them over on the right. But what's your algorithm there?
也可以抓住最大的元素，把它们放在右边。这里面的算法是什么？
Like how would you teach someone younger than you, who's never done that before, how to do it?
就像你会如何教一个比你年轻、从未做过这种事的人来执行？
How would you compel your Mac or PC or phone to do something like that?
你如何驱使你的 Mac、PC 或手机做这样的事情？
You can't just wave your hand, and say, oh, figure it out. Move things around.
你不能只是挥挥手，然后说，哦，想想办法，把东西搬来搬去。
You have to express yourself more methodically. So we'll translate even ideas like this into code too.
你得更有条理地表达自己。因此，我们将把像这样的想法转化为代码。
And that's what the Googles and others of the world are doing constantly, as they sort and organize the world's information.
这正是 Google 和世界上其他公司在不断做的事情，因为它们要对世界上的信息进行分类和整理。
We'll use metaphors along the way, if it helps.
举个例子来帮助大家理解。
We'll talk about your computer's memory as being like a postal address.
我们把电脑内存比作一个邮政地址。
Like every mailbox in the world has some form of postal address, street, city, state, country, and the like, and it turns out, that's how your Mac, your PC, and your phone also work.
就像世界上的每个邮箱都有某种形式的邮政地址：街道、城市、州、国家等等
事实上，你的 Mac、PC 和手机也是这样的原理。
You've got a whole bunch of memory, like the picture before, but you can think of it really as individual mailboxes.
你有一大堆内存，就像刚才展示的图片，但你可以把它看作是一个个独立的邮箱。
And you can put anything you want in those mailboxes, and you can go to a mailbox to grab information that's from it.
你可以在这些邮箱中放置任何你想要的东西，还能进入邮箱获取其中的信息。
So at the end of the day, that's really all your computer is doing with information.
所以归根结底，你的计算机在处理信息时实际上也是在做这些事情。
It's just organizing it, not into mailboxes per se, but a term you probably know called bytes, for instance, instead.
它只是将信息组织起来，不是像实际邮箱一样，
而是用一个你可能熟悉的术语称为字节（byte）来代替。
We'll talk about problems that arise even nowadays.
我们来谈谈到现在还会出现的问题。
In fact, most of you are familiar with your Mac, PC, even phone like spontaneously rebooting sometimes, crashing, the little annoying spinning beach ball or hourglass icon that happens.
你们中的大多数人对于 Mac、PC 甚至手机的突然重启、崩溃，
以及出现的讨厌的旋转沙滩球或沙漏图标都很眼熟。
*注：沙滩球出现在 Mac，沙漏出现在 Windows ，代表系统运行卡顿或缓慢。
Like what is with that?
这是咋回事？
Well, those are just bugs in programs that humans at Apple and Google and Microsoft and others, they screwed up, and they wrote buggy code.
嗯，那些只是在苹果、谷歌、微软和其他公司的程序中出现的错误，
他们搞砸了，写出了带 bug 的代码。
And your computer, when it encounters those mistakes, doesn't know what to do.
而你的电脑在遇到这些错误时，不知道该怎么办。
And so 9 times out of 10, so to speak, it just crashes or freezes or the like, but that kind of stuff will make more sense.
所以可以说，十有八九会出现死机或冻结之类的情况。这些问题马上会变得更加容易理解。
So even the real world will make sense, and pictured here are some lower level terms we'll eventually get to mid-semester.
这里展示的是我们在学期中期将逐渐了解的一些底层术语。
But generally speaking, when something is going this way, as per this arrow, and something is going this way, as per this arrow, like that does not end well.
一般来说，当一些事情按照这个箭头的方向进行，
另一些事情按照这个箭头的方向进行，这样的情况通常不会有好的结果。
And that often is what happens when your computer crashes.
这往往就是电脑崩溃时发生的情况。
Someone's using memory up here, but someone else is using memory down here, and then they're not really talking left hand and right hand.
有人自上往下使用内存（memory），但另一个人自下往上使用内存，
然后他们并没有进行良好的沟通。
*注：这里是说堆栈溢出，先不用深究。
So that is just a high level overview of some of the problems we'll encounter, but we'll focus to on data, ultimately.
这只是一些我们将遇到的问题的高度概括。先来看看数据。
So pictured here is something fairly technical called a hash table.
因此，这里展示的是一种相当技术性的东西，叫做哈希表（hash table）。
It's an amalgam of something we're going to soon call an array and also something we call a link to list.
它是数组（array）和链表 （linked-list）的结合。
And these are just fancy terms for describing how you can organize information even more flexibly than just putting individual values in mailboxes.
这些只是用来描述如何更加灵活地组织信息的高级术语，比简单地把单个值放入邮箱更加复杂。
Like how could you build structures, like actual data structures so to speak, two-dimensional structures at that?
比如，你该如何构建结构，比如可以说是实际的数据结构，二维结构？
And so what you're seeing here is a glimpse, as some of you might have recognized, of some Harry Potter universe names, but they're organized somewhat alphabetically.
你们在这里看到的是哈利-波特宇宙中的一些名字，
有些人可能已经认出来了，它们是按字母顺序排列的。
And notice, that any time there's multiple people with a name that starts with H, like Hermione, Harry, and Hagrid, well, they can't all fit in that mailbox, if each of these squares along the left is that same mailbox.
注意，有多个名字以H开头的人，比如Hermione Harry  Hagrid，它们不能同时放入一个邮箱里，如果每个沿左侧的方块都代表同一个邮箱的话。
So you have to chain them together. Well, you'll learn how to do that in code.
所以你必须将它们串起来。你将学会怎么用代码做到这件事。
So that even if you get more data than you expect, if your business is booming, and you're some web-based business,
即使你获得比预期更多的数据，如果你的业务蓬勃发展，成为一家基于网络的企业，
how do you keep adding and adding information to your software to actually keep up with it?
你该如何不断添加和处理信息，以确保你的软件跟得上业务的发展呢？
But this, again, is what code's going to soon look like, as soon as next week,
这些内容很快就会变成代码的样子，在下周就能看到了。
in week one, this here being C, but we'll transition in a few weeks to a more modern, higher level language, so to speak, called Python.
第一周我们讲述 C 语言。但几周后，我们将过渡到一种更现代、更高级的语言—— Python。
Indeed, the course very deliberately, back in my day and now this, introduces you first to C, which funny enough, many people don't tend to program in certainly every day.
这门课程在我那个时候和现在，都有意地首先向你介绍 C 语言，
有趣的是，很多人并不经常使用 C 语言进行编程。
I use C, generally, September, October, November, December, when teaching CS50 itself. But it's everywhere, nonetheless.
我通常在 9 月、10 月、11 月和 12 月的时候，教授 CS50 课程时使用 C 语言。
但无论如何，C 语言无处不在。
In fact, even today's other languages, with which you might be familiar, like Python and Java and yet others still, you see this same primitive language underneath the hood, because it's so darn fast.
其实吧，即使是你可能熟悉的现今的其他语言，比如Python、Java等等，
你仍然会看到在底层有 C，因为它实在是太快了。
And as you'll learn over the coming weeks, it really gives you access to and an understanding of what's going on conceptually down here.
随着你在接下来的几周里学习，你将真正了解并理解这里的概念和实现。
So that thereafter, after CS50, when you're writing code, you can think at a very high level what's actually going on.
所以在 CS50 这门课之后，当你编写代码时，你就可以从一个非常高的层面来思考实际发生了什么。
So in fact, in just a few weeks, what looks like this in C is going to look instead like this in Python.
再过几周，在 C 语言中看起来是这样的，在 Python 中就会变成这样。
And you'll better understand what's going on underneath the hood, and odds are, after this class, you'll reach for a language
你将更好地理解底层的运作原理，在这门课程之后，
like Python more frequently than C, but you're going to benefit from that bottom-up understanding thereof.
你很可能更频繁地选择像 Python 这样的语言，而不是 C 语言，但你将从底层的理解中受益。
Thereafter and towards term's end, we'll introduce you to a few other ideas, like where do you put large amounts of data?
在学期末，我们还会向你介绍一些其他的想法，比如你应该把大量的数据放在哪里？
In things called databases, not things like spreadsheets, like here, but actual databases.
这些东西被称为数据库，而不是像这里的电子表格那样，而是真正的数据库。
We're using those same kinds of data structures, you lay things out in an interesting way in memory.
我们使用的是这种数据结构，以一种有趣的方式将事物排列在内存中。
Thereafter, we'll transition to a very familiar environment that you and I use every day, the web.
之后，我们将过渡到一个你我每天都在使用的非常熟悉的环境——网页。
Like the web has become rather the User Interface, or UI, that we use everywhere, on the laptops, desktops, and even mobile devices, nowadays.
如今，网页已经成为我们使用的各种设备的用户界面（user interface），
无论是在笔记本电脑、台式机还是移动设备上。
Well, pictured here is a language called HTML.
这里展示的是一种名为 HTML 的语言。
It's not a programming language.
它不是一种编程语言。
It's a markup language, and some of you might have made home pages or portfolios in the past.
这是一种标记语言，有些人过去可能制作过主页或作品集。
But you'll understand what's going on here, but more powerfully, you'll understand how the computer sees that same kind of code, builds up a hierarchical family tree-type structure in memory.
你会理解这些东西的含义，更重要的是，
你将理解计算机是如何看待这种代码的，它会在内存中构建起一种层次化的家族树状结构。
And then you can manipulate that tree with code to actually add more and more information, chat messages, anything on the screen that you like.
然后，你就可以用代码操作这棵树，在屏幕上添加越来越多的信息、聊天信息等任何你喜欢的内容。
And finally, we'll tie all of this together by introducing what are called frameworks and libraries, third-party code that makes it a lot easier to solve problems of interest to you.
最后，我们将通过引入框架和库把所有这些内容串起来，
这些第三方代码可以使你更容易地解决自己感兴趣的问题。
And so in particular, here, this is the very first web app that I myself made back in like 1997.
尤其是这里，这是我自己在 1997 年制作的第一个网络应用程序。
I was part of the first-year intramural sports program, not as an athlete but as the programmer, and I was teaching myself how to build web applications.
我参加了一年级的校内体育项目，但不是作为运动员，
而是作为程序员，自学如何构建网络应用程序。
I only knew C and maybe a little bit of something else at the time.
当时我只知道 C，别的知之甚少。
But this became, for Harvard at least, the very first website for the first-year intramural sports program, and it wasn't just a static website with links and images and the like.
但至少对哈佛大学来说，这成了一年级校内体育项目的第一个网站，
而且它才不仅仅是一个带有链接和图片等的静态网站。
It was interactive. You could register for sports.
它是可交互的，你可以报名参加体育运动。
We could input exactly who was in a tournament bracket or the like, and it could actually automatically keep track of this data.
我们可以准确地输入谁进入了锦标赛或类似的比赛，它实际上可以自动跟踪这些数据。
So there too, after just three months of a class like this, you'll go from writing quite simply this week and next Hello, World
在经过短短三个月的这样一门课程后，你将从最初的写 "Hello, World" 这样简单的程序，
to building things like this for whether it's web, mobile, or other platforms as well, if you so choose.
发展到构建类似于这样的项目，无论是用于 Web 、移动设备还是其他平台，如果你愿意的话。
But we'll get you off of the course's infrastructure, by the end of the term.
在学期结束时，我们将让你脱离课程的基础设施，
You won't be using any toy environments along the way.
不使用任何玩具环境。
We'll empower you, ultimately, to write code after CS50, especially if this is the only CS class you ever take, on your own Mac or PC, using the same software, but not the cloud-based version thereof.
最终，我们将让你有能力在 CS50 结束后自己编写代码，尤其是如果这是你唯一上的计算机科学课程，
你可以在自己的 Mac 或 PC 上使用相同的软件，而不是云端版本。
But all of this software is itself free and can be used by you powerfully after the course's own end.
所有这些软件本身都是免费的，在课程结束后，可以自由继续使用。
But along the way, as you may know, there is this tradition within the class, particularly in healthy times, of a number of events that really brings people get together,
你可能知道，在这门课程中有一个传统，特别是在健康时期，有许多活动让大家聚在一起，
not just collaboratively and academically, but to just solve problems and generally engage with each other as well.
不仅仅是在学术上合作，而且还一起解决问题，相互交流互动。
Coming up first, CS50 Puzzle Day, which is meant to be not jigsaw puzzles but logic puzzles that require no prior experience with computer science or programming.
首先是 "CS50 拼图日"，这不是拼图游戏，而是不需要任何计算机科学或编程经验的逻辑谜题。
But it's just an opportunity to quietly work on a packet of puzzles with some number of friends for prizes and more.
这是一个机会，可以和一些朋友一起静静地解决一套谜题，有机会赢得奖品和更多的乐趣。
Later in the semester, once you tackle your final projects, the capstone of the course, where we don't give you a homework to write, you yourself come up with something to build.
在学期后期，一旦你着手完成最终项目，这也是课程的高潮部分，
我们不会给你布置一份作业来完成，而是让你自己想一个项目来构建。
*注意看 David 讲得大汗淋漓，哈哈
We'll get together generally around 7:00 PM in the evening, wrap up around 7:00 AM, if you so choose.
我们差不多在晚上7点左右聚在一起，并在早上7点左右结束，如果你愿意的话。
And it's an evening, a 12-hour opportunity to collaborate with classmates on your very own final project, in a large space on campus, that ends-- if you're awake with us-- at 5:00 AM.
这是一个为期12小时的机会，在校园的一个大空间里与同学们合作完成你自己的最终项目，
如果你和我们一起保持清醒，结束时间将是凌晨5点。
We can hop on some CS50 shuttles and go down the road for some pancakes at IHOP around 6:00.
我们可以乘坐 CS50 的班车，在早上6点左右前往附近的 IHOP 吃些煎饼。
*注：IHOP 是一家美国连锁餐厅，主要以早餐食品著称，特别是煎饼、煎蛋和烤面包。
Of course-- of course, this is 6:00, 7:00 AM at that point
当然——这时候可是早上六、七点钟呢
but it's an opportunity finally to lead into what's called the CS50 fair, which is an end of semester celebration, an exhibition, of everything that you'll accomplish over the coming months.
这是学期结束的庆祝活动，一个展示你在接下来几个月里所取得的一切成果的展览。
And in fact, pictured here are some of your predecessors in healthy times.
图里面是非疫情时候，你们的一些学长学姐。
The CS50 fair allows you to come with your laptop or phone and exhibits of students, faculty, and staff across campus put together something in person
在 CS50 展览会上，你可以带着笔记本电脑或手机，
和学生、教职员工们一起在现场和视频上展示创作的东西，
and on video that people can delight in seeing, as you exhibit what it is you created and what you learned over the course of the several weeks.
让人们可以欣赏你的创作成果以及这段时间学到的种种。
And ultimately, a chance to just share and inspire others as well.
这也是一个分享和激励他人的机会。
And you'll all walk home, ultimately, with your own I took CS50 T-shirts saying as much as well.
最终，你们都将带着自己的 "我参加了 CS50" T恤衫回家。
So with that high level overview of the course,
以上就是本课程的概况，
I propose that we begin to take a look at what computer science itself is and what it is we're going to be doing over the next several weeks at this lower level too.
我想着咱得先看看计算机科学本身是什么，
以及在接下来的几周里，我们要在这个较底层的层次做些什么。
So what is computer science?
那么，什么是计算机科学？
Right?
If you're maybe like me or new people like my friends in high school, you probably assume that it means programming.
如果你像我和高中朋友一样是新手，你可能会认为计算机科学就是编程。
And that's absolutely a big part of it for a lot of people, because with code, you can write, you can express ideas, and solve actual problems, especially involving data.
对很多人来说，编程确实是其中的一个重要部分，
因为通过编写代码，你可以表达想法，解决实际问题，特别是涉及数据的问题。
But computer science itself is really the study of information, if you will.
但计算机科学本身其实就是一门研究信息的学科。
How do you represent it, and how do you actually process it?
你如何表现信息，又如何实际处理信息？
And in that sense, computational thinking is just the application of ideas from computer science, a course like this, to problems of interest to you
从这个意义上说，计算思维就是将计算机科学中的思想，
例如像这门课程中学到的内容，应用到你感兴趣的问题上，
again, in the arts, humanities, sciences, social sciences, whatever the domain of interest is to you.
无论是在艺术、人文学科、科学、社会科学，还是别的你感兴趣的领域。
So with that, if computer science is all about information and with it the solving of problems, well, what does it actually mean to solve a problem?
所以，如果计算机科学关乎信息和问题的解决，那解决问题究竟意味着什么呢？
Let's see if we can't propose a model into which all of the lessons learned will ultimately follow.
让我们来看看是否可以提出一个模型，将所有学到的教训都归纳整理。
And I'd propose that this is problem solving. You've got some input, which is like the problem you want to solve. The goal is to solve it.
我认为这就是解决问题。有一些输入，这就像是你想要解决的问题。目标就是解决问题。
So that's the so-called output, and then somewhere in here, the proverbial black box, is some kind of secret sauce that gets the work done.
这就是所谓的输出。然后在这个黑盒子里，有某种能完成工作的秘方。
And in the coming months, we'll have to decide, well, how are we going to represent these inputs and outputs, and really, how do we code up?
在接下来的几个月里，我们得决定如何表示这些输入和输出，以及我们要如何编写代码。
How do we write solutions for what it is that's solving the problem of interest to us?
我们怎样才能写出解决我们感兴趣问题的解决方案？
So when it comes to representation of information, like there's a lot of ways we can do this.
因此，说到信息的表现形式，我们有很多方法可以做到这一点。
And for instance, if the problem at hand quite simply is to take attendance at the beginning of class, on the first day of school, well, how could we go about doing this?
举例来说，如果当前的问题很简单，
就是在开学第一天上课时进行考勤，那么，我们该如何去做呢？
Well, we could actually use a system called unary. Well, what is that?
实际上，我们可以使用一种叫做 "unary" 的系统。那是个啥？
Well, that's a fancy way of saying 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, maybe 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.
这是一种用来表示数字的方式，就是通过1、2、3、4、5... 这样的方式。
And I can use my digits-- pun intended-- on my fingers to actually count everyone up.
我还能用我的手指数出每个人的人数。
And eventually, you need toes and whatnots, if you have to count so high.
最后，你还需要脚趾什么的，如果你非要往高了数。
But unary is a very simple system of using a single symbol, a human finger in this case, to just solve some problem, like counting the number of people in the room.
但是，unary 是一个非常简单的系统，
它使用一个符号（这里是人的手指）来解决一些问题，比如计算房间里的人数。
*暂停警告
*注：unary我没有翻译成一进制，因为没有中文里"进位"的含义。
想想小学用的数学小棒，也是没有进位一说，只是单纯的累加。
与十进制相对比一下，
111其实是10^2*1+10^1*1+10^0*1，也就是以10的幂次为基底；
如果我们用unary的方式解读，111就是1^2*1+1^1*1+1^0*1，等于十进制的3。
Let's make this slightly more technical for a moment, a little more mathy.
让我们把这个问题稍微技术化一点，数学化一点。
That's just called base-1, where the base under which you're operating has one digit in it, like literally a human finger, and maybe multiple such fingers, if you need to count higher.
这就是所谓的基数为 1 ，你所操作的基数中只有一位数，
就像人的手指一样，如果你需要数得更高，就得拿别的手指。
But of course, most of you, if not all of you, generally, vaguely know that computers use something other than unary-- and even you and I probably don't use this that often--
当然，你们中的大多数人都隐约知道计算机使用的不是 unary，咱也不经常用 unary。
they use what language or alphabet instead.
而是用一些语言或字母来代替。
Yeah.
So binary, so binary is indeed the system that computers somehow use.
是的，计算机实际使用的是二进制（binary）。
So in this case, bi implying two, and so computers have two digits, it turns out, at their disposal.
在这种情况下，"bi" 意味着 "2"，所以在每一位，计算机有0 1两个数可以使用。
And in fact, if you've ever heard the technical term bit, which is like a smaller version of a byte-- more on that soon.
如果你听说过技术术语比特（bit），它是比字节（byte）更小的单位——马上会提到更多。
Well, a binary digit is the origin of that term "Bit," because if you get rid of some of the letters, and are left from binary digit with just B-I-T, thus is a bit.
"binary digit" 是 "bit" 一词的由来，去掉一些字母，"binary digit" 只剩下 B-I-T，这就是比特。
A bit is just a 0 and 1.
bit 就是 0 和 1。
It's two more digits than you might have on your own finger, and of course, it's fewer though than you and I have.
大意：unary下，一根手指只能够表达1。binary下，一个bit能表达0, 1，就能呈现出两种状态。
一只手只能表达出0~5，那么如果让每根手指弯曲代表0，伸直代表1，一只手就可以表示出2^5种状态。
信息承载量大大提高，需要的位数减少，也就是David所说的"fewer though than you and I have"。
可以思考一下二者的差别，binary多利用的是，手指间的位置信息。
同样的一个手势，在上面两种解读下就有了不同的意义。
比如00010，unary下为1，binary下就为2^1*1+2^0*0，为2。
计算机来说只认识0和1，
我们只是采用不同的编码方式把各种信息编码（encoding）为01二进制串，
用不同的解码算法，把二进制串解码（decoding）成正确的格式。
David后面会有更加详细生动的演绎。
*暂停警告
You and I typically use, as humans, the decimal system.
人们通常使用十进制系统。
Dec meaning 10, because you and I generally use 0 through 9.
Dec 表示 10，咱一般使用数字 0 到 9。
So on the one hand-- another pun intended-- you've got unary.
你知道了 unary。
Computers use binary. We humans generally think and talk in terms of decimal.
而计算机用的是二进制。我们人类通常用十进制思考和交谈。
But at the end of the day, these are fundamentally going to be the same thing, which is to say that it's all pretty accessible to us.
但归根结底，这些基本上是一样的，理解起来很轻松。
Even if you're not a computer person, I daresay you're about to be.
即使你现在不是电脑达人，那也不远了。
So what is a bit? Well, a bit then is a 0 or a 1. That is a so-called binary digit.
那么什么是比特呢？那么，一个比特就是一个 0 或一个 1，也就是二进制位。
But how do computers only speak in binary?
但计算机是怎么只用二进制作为语言的？
How do they solve problems, represent information, using only binary?
他们如何仅用二进制解决问题、表示信息？
Well, at the end of the day, if they want to represent 0 and 1, we need to do so physically somehow.
说到底，如果想表示 0 和 1，我们就需要通过某种物理方式来实现。
And I daresay that maybe the simplest way to think about a bit, a 0 or a 1, is like a light bulb.
最简单的方法就是把比特、0 或 1 想象成灯泡。
And so by human convention, let's just assume that if you were a computer, be it a laptop, desktop, phone, or the like, and you want to represent the number 0
按照人类的习惯，我们假设你自己是一台电子设备，你想表示的数字是 0
you know what, you just keep the light switch off.
你只要把电灯开关关上就行了。
You keep a light bulb off.
把灯泡关掉。
If by contrast, you're that same computer, and you want to represent the number 1, you take that same switch, that same light bulb, and just turn it on.
相比之下，如果你是那台电脑，想表示数字 1，你就可以打开开关，亮起灯泡。
So a light bulb that's on represents a 1, and a light bulb that's off represents a 0.
因此，亮着的灯泡代表 "1"，熄灭的灯泡代表 "0"。
So why is this relevant to computers?
为什么这与计算机有关？
Well, at the end of the day, you and I are charging our laptops or phones at night.
咱晚上的时候给笔记本电脑或手机充电。
So there's some physical resource being replenished there, whether you're on battery or some power cord.
无论使用的是电池还是电源线，都会有一些物理资源得到补充。
And so inside of a computer are just thousands, millions of tiny little switches, nowadays.
如今的电脑内部有成千上万个小开关。
You can think of them metaphorically as light bulbs, but they don't actually shine light.
你可以把它们比喻成灯泡，但实际上它们并不发光。
But there are tiny, tiny little switches, and those switches, if you've ever heard the term, are just called transistors.
但是，还有一些很小很小的开关，这些开关，如果你听说过这个词，就是晶体管。
So like computers have millions of transistors that can either be flipped on to represent 1's or flipped off to represent 0's.
计算机拥有数百万个晶体管，这些晶体管可以打开表示 1，也可以关闭表示 0。
And from that very simple mechanism, electricity is there, or it's not, a 1 or a 0.
这个机制非常简单，电存在或不存在就对应 1 或 0。
Computers can actually count, obviously, from 0 to 1, but it turns out, even higher, if they use a little more electricity as well.
显然，计算机可以从 0 数到 1，但事实证明，如果多用一点电，还可以数得更高。
So how might I do this?
那么，我该怎么做呢？
Well, let me go ahead and propose that I just grab one of our own light bulbs here on stage.
好吧，我们试试来，我在台上拿一个我们自己的灯泡。
This one is off.
这个关了。
So for instance, if this were miniaturized inside of your Mac, PC, or phone, this would be a transistor, and indeed, here's the little switch on the bottom.
因此，举例来说，如果把它微型化，装在 Mac、PC 或手机里，这就是一个晶体管，一个小开关。
And if your computer wants to represent a 0, it just leaves the switch off, and the light is not shining.
如果你的电脑想表示 0，它就会把开关关掉，灯也不会亮。
If you want to represent a 1, well now, I've counted as high as 1, because the switch is now on.
如果你想表示 1，那么现在，我已经数到了 1，因为开关现在打开了。
I've grabbed a little electricity.
我抓来了一点电。
I'm holding on to it inside of the computer, and so now I see that this is a 1.
我把它放在电脑里，所以现在我看到这是个 1。
All right, but unfortunately, with just one switch, one light bulb,
好吧，可只有一个开关，一个灯泡，
I can only count from 0 to 1.
我只能从 0 数到 1。
How do I count out higher, might you think, intuitively?
你可能会直觉地想，我怎么才能算得更高呢？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Say it again.
再说一遍？
AUDIENCE: More lightbulbs.
听众：更多灯泡
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, so more light bulbs.
就是啊，所以要多装灯泡。
So let me do this.
那就让我来吧。
Let me just grab something to put these on, so I can use a few of them at a time.
让我先拿个架子把它们放上去，这样就可以一次展示几个了。
And let me propose that here, instead of having just one light bulb, let me give myself maybe three in total.
让我在此提议，与其只有一个灯泡，不如一共装上三个灯泡。
So all of them are initially off, and if you think of this in miniature form, in your mind's eye, this is like a computer with three transistors.
因此，所有的晶体管最初都是关闭的，
如果你把它想象成微缩形式，在你的脑海中，这就是一台有三个晶体管的计算机。
Three switches representing now the number you and I know as 0.
三个开关现在代表你我都知道的数字 0。
Why? They're just all off.
为什么？他们都关掉的。
So how does a computer go about representing the number 1?
那么，计算机如何表示数字 1 呢？
Well, it turns on one of these light bulbs.
嗯，我打开其中一个灯泡。
And how does the computer represent the number 2?
电脑又是如何表示数字 2 的？
Well, you might think, if I may, you just turn on a second light bulb.
好吧，你可能会想，如果可以的话，你只需打开第二个灯泡。
And if you might think, how does a computer represent 3?
如果你想，计算机如何表示 3？
You just turn on the third light bulb.
你只需打开第三个灯泡。
And so as such, with three bits, a computer would seem to be able to count from 0 on up to 1, 2, 3.
因此，有了三个比特，计算机似乎就能从 0 开始数到 1、2、3。
But it turns out, if I'm a little smarter here,
但事实证明，如果稍微聪明一点，
I can actually count higher than that.
其实还能表示得比这个多。
Why? Well, I'm just considering the combination of bulbs being on here.
为什么？我只是在考虑灯泡在这里的组合。
What if I do something like this?
如果我这样做呢？
This is still 0, I will claim, but what if I propose now that this will be how a computer represents 1-- on, off, off.
现在是 0，但如果我现在提出约定，这样子代表 1 呢？
This, though, will be how the computer represents 2.
而这是计算机表示 2 的方式。
Notice, I didn't turn on the same two.
请注意，我没有打开同样的两个。
I'm just turning on the one in the middle.
我正在打开中间那个。
This I now claim will be how a computer represents 3.
我说，这是计算机表示 3 的方式——
This is going to be-- in just a second-- how a computer represents the number we know as 4, and yet, I'm still only using three bulbs.
稍等... 计算机这样表示 4 这个数字，但我仍然只用了三个灯泡。
This is going to be the number the computer represents as 5.
计算机这样表示数字 5。
This is going to be how the computer represents the number 6, and then lastly, it turns out, with three light bulbs, if you're smart about it, you can count it seems as high as 7.
计算机表示6需要这样。事实证明，如果你聪明的话，三个灯泡就能把数字数到 7。
Now, even if you lost track of what I was turning on and why,
现在，即使你还不知道我打开关闭的逻辑，
I claim there were eight different patterns, from all of them off to all of them on.
这有八种不同的模式，从全部关闭到全部打开。
But notice that I started to permute them.
但请注意，我开始对它们进行排列组合。
I took into account which ones were on and which ones were off.
我考虑了哪些是打开的，哪些是关闭的。
Why, though, do these represent the numbers we know as 0 through 7?
为什么这些数字代表我们所熟知的 0 到 7 呢？
Well, let me go ahead, and maybe let's do this.
好吧，我接着来，也许可以这样。
Instead of just considering there to be light bulbs, let's assign some special significance to each of them, based on where it is.
让我们根据灯泡所在的位置，为每一个灯泡赋予一些特殊的意义，而不是仅仅考虑灯泡的开闭。
And maybe for this, could we get maybe three volunteers, three volunteer?
也许我们可以找三名志愿者？
OK. You're being volunteered.
好的你自愿来。
OK. Come on up.
好的，上来吧。
If you want to go over to the stage there.
如果你想去那边的台阶。
Yeah. You want to come on up as well, and over here as well.
你也上来，你也上来吧，到这边来。
So there are some stairs on either end.
两边都有楼梯的。
Maybe a round of applause for our first volunteers of term.
给本学期的第一批志愿者来点掌声。
[APPLAUSE]
All right. So you want to be our number 1, and if you want to go ahead and stand roughly right here.
你是 1 号，往前走走差不多站在这里就好。
How about do you want to be number 2?
你来 2 号可以吧？
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
DAVID J. MALAN: Come on over right to the right of here, and you'll be number 4, it turns out.
请到右边来，你是 4 号。
If you want to come over here, on this end, let's give you all a moment to introduce yourselves briefly to your classmates, if you'd like.
如果你们愿意，可以过来，给一点时间，向同学们简单介绍一下自己吧。
AUDIENCE: Hi.
I'm Ellie.
I'm a senior.
DAVID J. MALAN: Nice to meet.
很高兴见到你。
AUDIENCE: I'm [? Rayhanna, ?] and I'm a first year.
DAVID J. MALAN: Welcome.
欢迎。
AUDIENCE: Hi. I'm Joseph, and I am a first year.
DAVID J. MALAN: Welcome.
欢迎。
All right. So so glad to have all three of you up here. Thank you.
好的很高兴你们三位都来了，谢谢你们。
[APPLAUSE]
Let me propose now that we'd like you three to represent how about the number 0.
现在我提议，请你们三位代表数字 0。
And I claim now that if each of you now represents a switch, you have fancier light bulbs now.
我来介绍，如果你们每个人现在都代表一个开关，那么现在就有了更高级的灯泡。
One is a 1. One is a 2. One is a 4, but each of you is still just has a switch on the bottom, in fact, of your plastic devices.
一个是 1，一个是 2，一个是 4，这些塑料设备底部都有一个开关。
I claim these three volunteers are representing the number 0.
我说，现在这三位志愿者代表的是数字 0。
Let me ask you all now, how might you represent the number 1?
现在让我来问问大家，你们如何表示数字 1？
How should you cooperate here?
你们应该如何配合？
OK. So we would have on, off, off, which I think matches what I did with my three light bulbs as well, if you want to go and turn yours off.
好的。所以，现在是开、关、关，
如果要关掉，和刚才关掉灯泡的方式差不多。
How might you three represent the number 2?
怎么表示数字 2？
OK, so off, on, off now, from right to left.
好了，现在从右到左，关、开、关。
How would you three represent the number 3?
如何表示数字 3？
Ah, so that's why my two light bulbs went on at the end.
啊，这就是刚才让两个灯泡都亮的原因。
How would you three represent the number 4?
如何表示数字 4？
Perfect. Number 5, number 6, and number 7?
棒。5、6、7呢？
All right, and give us one more.
好的，再加一个。
How would you represent 8?
怎么表示 8？
AUDIENCE: We can't.
我们不能
DAVID J. MALAN: OK. You can't.
确实，不可以。
How about then one more volunteer, one more volunteer?
那就再来一名志愿者，一名志愿者，怎么样？
OK. Come on up.
来吧。
All right. What's your name?
好吧，你叫什么名字？
AUDIENCE: My name is [? Moin. ?]
DAVID J. MALAN: If you want to say it into there.
DAVID J. MALAN: All right, [? and Moin, ?] you're going to be number 8, and if now you all-- actually, let's make this how would you represent number 8, all collectively, as 4 bits or for switches?
好的Moin，你拿的数字8，你们会如何用4位或4个开关来表示数字8？
OK, 8, and now lastly, give me 15.
最后，演示一下 15。
Everyone's awkwardly doing arithmetic in their head, oh, using unary.
大家都在脑海中做算术呢，噢，在使用 unary。
Yeah.
Is that everyone--
每个人都要点亮。
Yes.
OK.
Round of applause.
来点掌声。
OK.
Thank you all.
谢谢大家。
If you want to leave your numbers over here, we have a CS50 stress ball for you, but thank you for volunteering.
请在这里留下数字牌，我们准备了一个 CS50 压力球，感谢志愿服务。
You can turn those numbers off and leave them over here.
可以把这些数字牌关掉，放在这里。
So thank you.
谢谢你们。
So how do we go about-- how do we go from there to creating these patterns?
那么我们要怎么着手来制定模式呢？
Well, even though we still had three bits, initially, and three switches, later four bits and four switches, ultimately, we still
最初我们有三位，后来是四位
used the same approach fundamentally to actually representing information.
最终我们在根本上仍然使用相同的方法来表示信息
And now why were they those patterns, and why did I very deliberately have our volunteers line up in that way?
我为什么要有意让志愿者们这样排队？
Well, I wanted them using base-2, a.k.a. binary, but with binary there comes certain rules.
我想让他们使用二进制，也就是 binary，但二进制也有一定的规则。
And even if you're not familiar with binary beyond that it exists and relates somehow to computers, it's actually pretty much identical to the system you and I use every day
即使你对二进制并不熟悉，只知道它的存在并与计算机有某种联系，
但它实际上与你我每天使用的十进制系统基本相同。
known as base 10, a.k.a. decimal.
十进制以十为基数，又叫decimal。
So let's consider, if you will, by rewinding to primary school for just a moment, like how decimal works.
把时间倒回小学课堂，想想十进制是怎么工作的。
And you'll see that even if you're not a computer person, you actually are.
你看，即使你不是计算机专业的人，其实你也早懂的。
You just have to tweak your mental model ever so slightly.
只需要稍微调整一点点心智模式。
So here is the number that you're probably viewing as 123, but why is that?
这里的数字你会认为是 123，但这是为什么呢？
Well, it's not really 123.
其实也不是 123。
This is just a pattern of three symbols on the screen, 1, 2, 3, and your mind is rapidly assigning mathematical meaning to them, 123, but why is that?
这只是屏幕上三个图案，1、2、3，你的大脑迅速赋予它们数学意义，123，但这是为什么呢？
Well, if you're like me, you probably learned back in the day, when you have a three-digit number like, this the rightmost number is in the 1's place, the middle digit is the 10's place,
很久以前学过，当你有一个三位数时，最右边的数字在个位，
中间的数字在十位，最左边的数字在百位，这有什么关系呢？
the leftmost digit is in the 100's place, and why is that relevant?
很久以前学过，当你有一个三位数时，最右边的数字在个位，
中间的数字在十位，最左边的数字在百位，这有什么关系呢？
Well, if you then quickly do some mental math, as you and I just do instantly nowadays
我们快速心算一下，
that just means 100 times 1 plus 10 times 2 plus 1 times 3, of course, 100 plus 20 plus 3 gives us the number you and I know as 123.
这意味着 100*1 加上 10*2 再加上 1*3，当然是 123。
But beyond that, how do we get to just two digits instead of as many as 9 in the decimal system?
再往深想想，我们怎么用两个数字 0 1 而不是 0 到 9，来得到十进制数？
Well, let's generalize this.
好吧，我们来归纳一下。
In the decimal system, you and I know, if we've got three digits represented by these hashes here, yes, it's the 1's place, 10's place, 100's place,
在十进制系统中，用这里的#符号分别代表个位、十位和百位
and if we keep going 1,000's, 10,000's, and so forth, but why is that?
如果我们继续下去，就是千位、万位等等，但是这是为什么呢？
Well, base terminology is now a little more germane.
好了，现在用更加书面的术语表述。
That's technically the 10 to the 0th column, the 10 to the 1, 10 to the 2.
从技术上讲，这就是10的0次方列、10的1次方列和10的2次方列。
So these are powers of 10, where 10 is your base.
所以这些都是以10为基数的幂。
Computers just simplify things a little bit, because computers, at the end of the day, only have access to electricity, on or off.
计算机只是把事情简化了一点，因为计算机只能使用电力，开或者关。
They don't have access to 10 different types of electricity, just 2, on or off, if you will.
无法使用 10 种不同类型的电力，只有 2 种，要么开要么关。
Well, they just use a different base.
他们只是使用了不同的基数。
And the rightmost digit would be in the so-called 2 to the 0ths.
而最右边的数字是 2 的 0 次方。
Then the middle digit is 2 to the 1.
然后中间的数字是 2 的 1 次方。
The left most is 2 to the 2, a.k.a.
最左边的数字是 2 的 2 次方。
1's place, 2's place, 4's place, and as we kept going, 8, and if we keep going, 16, 32, 64, 128, and so forth, but the idea is fundamentally the same.
也就是 1 的位置、2 的位置、4 的位置，随着继续进行，
8，然后 16、32、64、128 等等，但基本思想是相同的。
So why is this how the computer represents the number you and I know is 0?
那么，为什么你我都知道的数字 "0 "会被电脑这样表示呢？
Well, off, off, off, from right to left or in this case left to right, is just 0.
那么，全关，就是 0。
Why? Because that's 4 times 0 plus 2 times 0 plus 1 times 0 is, of course, 0.
为什么呢？因为 4*0 + 2*0 + 1*0 当然就是 0。
This is why 001 represents 1.
这就是为什么 001 代表 1。
This is why 010 represents 2 and 3 and 4 and 5 and 6 and 7 on up.
这就是为什么 010 代表 2。然后是 3、4、5、6 和 7。
And why did we need a 4th bit to represent 8?
为什么我们需要第 4 位来表示 8 呢？
Well, we kind of needed to carry the 1, so to speak, using our familiar human terminology.
可以使用熟悉的概念来解释，我们需要进位。
But for that we need a 4th bit, another transistor, and this now represents the number 8.
但是为此，我们需要第 4 位，另一个晶体管，现在这个表示数字 8。
And that's why we ended with on-- from left to right-- off, off, off.
这就是为什么我们以 "开 "结束 -- 从左到右 -- "关"、"关"、"关"。
So I keep saying on and off, or the light bulb is on or off, but really, I just mean 1 or 0.
所以我一直在说 "开 "和 "关"，或者灯泡 "开 "或 "关"，但实际上，我的意思只是 "1" 或 "0"。
And so computers and we humans think of things digitally as just being 0's and 1's, but mechanically, you can think of it indeed is these light bulbs.
所以计算机和我们人类将数字表示为 0 和 1，但从机械角度来看，你可以把它看作是这些灯泡。
Now, a bit is not very useful. Even 3 bits, 4 bits, not that useful.
现在，一个比特用处不大。即使是 3 位、4 位，也没多大用。
You can count to 7 or 15, generally speaking, bytes are a more useful unit of measure.
你当然可以数到 7 或 15，但一般来说，字节（byte）是更有用的计量单位。
And anyone familiar how many bits is in a byte?
有谁知道一个字节有多少位？
Yeah. So 8 bits are in a byte. You can think of it as an octet equivalently.
是的一个字节有 8 个比特。你可以把它看成一个八位组。
In some contexts, there are nuances there, but think of a byte as just being 8 bits, and that's just a more useful measure.
在某些情况下，会有一些细微差别，但把一个字节看作是 8 位，这只是一个更有用的衡量标准。
*注：有些特殊的系统可能使用更大的字节；以及字节有大端法和小端法两种表示方式。
So what does this mean in real terms?
那么，这意味着什么呢？
So if you've ever downloaded like a music file or a photograph or a video, those are measured in bytes.
你去下载音乐文件、照片或视频，这些都是以字节为单位的。
Probably not small numbers of bytes, probably kilobytes for thousands of bytes, megabytes for millions of bytes, gigabytes for billions of bytes, especially for video.
可能不是小量的字节，可能是几千字节的千字节（KB），
数百万字节的兆字节（MB），数十亿字节的千兆字节（GB），尤其是对于视频来说。
*注：1Byte = 8bit，注意大小写
That just means you have a lot of patterns of 8 bits, some combination of 0's and 1's on your computer's hard drive.
这意味着你的计算机硬盘上有很多 8 位的模式，一些 0 和 1 的组合。
Here then, with a byte of bits, 8 bits, is how a computer would typically represent the number 0.
在这里，计算机通常用 8 位比特，也就是一个字节，来表示数字 0。
And if that same computer uses all 8 of its bits, its full byte, to change it to 1-- anyone who's quick with math or have seen this before, how high can a computer count with 8 bits or 1?
如果这八个比特全部都置为1——
任何擅长数学或之前见过这个的人，计算机用8位二进制最高能计数到多少？
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
Yeah, 255. Why is that?
是的，255。为什么是 255？
Well, we're not going to turn this into a constant math exercise.
好吧，我们不打算一直做计算练习题了。
Indeed, after today, we're not really going to think about or talk about bits at this low level.
其实过了今天，我们就不会再考虑或谈论这么基础层级的比特了。
But this is the 1's place, 2's, 4's, 8s, 16, 32, 64, 128, and if I do all of that math from left to right, that indeed gives me 255.
但这是 1 的位置，2，4，8，16，32，64，128，如果我从左往右算，确实是 255。
It ignores how we might represent negative numbers, but perhaps more on those some other day.
它忽略了表示负数的规则，但也许改天会有更多关于负数的内容。
*注：后续请参看《深入理解计算机系统》（CMU 15-213）第二章，数据的表示和操作。
对于数据的表示规则有更详细的解释。
But computers, of course, do so much more than numbers and math and all this low level stuff.
当然，计算机能做的远不止数字、数学和这些底层的东西。
We send text messages, write documents, emails, and the like.
我们发送短信、撰写文件和电子邮件等等。
So how might a computer represent something like the letter A?
那么，计算机该如何表示字母 A 呢？
I claim, at the end of the day, your Mac, your PC, your phone just has lots of transistors, lots of switches that it can use in units of 8, in units of bytes.
我得说，归根结底，你的Mac、PC、手机都有很多晶体管，很多开关，它们以字节为单位使用。
How, though, if it's already using those patterns of 0's and 1's apparently to represent numbers from 0 on up, how do you go about representing letters of the alphabet, might you think?
我们已经知道，计算机使用这些 0 和 1 的模式来表示从 0 开始的数字，
那么你会如何表示字母呢？你可能会想到什么方法？
Yeah?
OK.
So we could assign a number to every letter.
所以我们可以给每个字母分配一个数字。
OK.
So let me just conjecture, well, let's just call A 0, for simplicity, B 1, C 2, and now let me play devil's advocate.
我来猜想一下，为了简单起见，我们把 A 称为 0，B 称为 1，C 称为 2。
OK, how do I now represent 0 or 1 or 2?
好了，我现在该如何表示 0、1 或 2 呢？
Well, we've maybe created a problem for ourselves, if now we have to steal some numbers to represent letters.
是的，如果我们现在必须借用一些数字来表示字母，可能会出现一些问题。
We kind of have to pick a lane, but there's a solution to that too that we'll see.
我们必须得做出权衡，但这也有解决办法，我们以后会看到。
And it turns out the world is not quite as simple as A being 0.
事实证明，世界并不像 A 为 0 那么简单。
A typically is represented, by computers everywhere, phones everywhere, with the number 65, the decimal number 65.
一个典型的例子是，各地的电脑和电话都用十进制数字 65 来表示。
Using 8 bits, if we turn some of the 0's to 1's, let me just stipulate, you can represent the letter A using 8 bits, by turning certain ones on
使用 8 比特，如果我们设置一些位为 1，我只是假设一下，
你可以用 8 位表示字母 A ，通过打开某些位置的开关和关闭其他位置的开关，
and certain ones off, but we will try not to focus on that binary level too much.
但我们将尽量不过多地关注二进制层面。
So if A is 65, it turns out that B is going to be 66, and C is going to be 67, and so forth, and so where does that get us?
因此，如果 A 是 65，那么 B 将是 66，C 将是 67，以此类推，我们会得到什么呢？
Well, it turns out there's a whole system that maps numbers to letters.
原来，有一整套系统可以将数字映射到字母。
And here, as I alluded to verbally a moment ago, is the pattern of 0's and 1's via which you'd represent 65.
正如我刚才口头提到的，这里是 0 和 1 的模式，你可以通过它来表示 65。
And just quick check here, we won't constantly do math 1's place, that's easy, 2's, 4's, 8's, 16's, 32's, 64's place.
这里只需快速检查一下，我们不会经常做 1 位的数学运算。这很简单，2、4、8、16、32、64。
So 64 plus 1 gives us 65.
所以 64 加 1 等于 65。
So once I do that, how do I get to all of the others?
那么，一旦我做到了这一点，我怎样才能获得所有其他的信息呢？
Well, it turns out a bunch of Americans years ago came up with this
原来，很多年前一群美国人想出了这个——
ASCII, the American Standard Code for Information Interchange.
ASCII，美国信息交换标准码。
Now, what does that mean?
现在，这是什么意思？
Well, it's just an acronym describing what really you proposed, a mapping between numbers and letters, not quite as simple as 0, 1, 2.
是的，它只是一个缩写，描述了你所提出的数字和字母之间的映射关系，
不像 0 对 A、1 对 B 这样简单。
Starts at 65, 66, 67 for capital letters, but here are most of the letters in use today, at least with this system.
对于大写字母，它从 65 开始，然后是 66、67。
这里列出了现今使用的大部分字母，至少在这个系统中是这样。
So this is just a big chart from online, and you'll see in the middle of this chart, here, here's my 65, A. Here's my 66,
这是网上的一个大图表，你会在图表中间看到，这里是65 A，这里是 66 B。
B, C, and let's see, 72 is H, 73 is I, and so forth.
B、C，接着看，72 是 H，73 是 I，以此类推。
So there's a mapping, at least for English, between all of these numbers and all of these letters.
因此，至少在英语中，所有这些数字和字母之间都有一个映射关系。
And if we focus here, those are the beginning of our uppercase alphabet.
如果我们把注意力集中在这里，这里就是大写字母的开头。
So suppose then that today, tomorrow, you receive a text message from someone, and underneath the hood, now that you're a computer person,
那么假设某天，你收到了某人发来的短信，而你是个电脑高手，
you figure out a way to see what pattern of 0's and 1's was sent.
你想查看发送的是什么 0 和 1 模式。
In this case, it's wireless as opposed to wired, but it's still some pattern of 0's and 1's.
在这种情况下，它是无线的，而不是有线的，但它仍然是一些 0 和 1 的模式。
And your phone is turning some switches of its own on and off to represent that message from a friend.
而你的手机正在开关一些开关，以表示朋友发来的信息。
Suppose that the three patterns you received were these three bytes, from left to right, spelling out a three-letter word.
假如收到的是这三个字节，从左到右，拼成一个三个字母的单词。
Well, if we do out the math, 1's place, 2's place, and so forth-- I'll spoil it for you.
好吧，如果我们算出 1 的位置、2 的位置等等——就不告诉你了。
Suppose that you received a text message that doesn't literally say 72, 73, 33, but you've received a pattern of 8 plus 8 plus 8, 24 bits
假设收到的短信并不是字面上的 72、73、33，而是一个由 8 位加 8 位加 8 位组成的 24 位模式，
that if you do out the math represent the decimal number 72, 73, 33.
如果你计算一下，它代表了十进制数72、73、33。
Anyone recall what message you might have received from the green and white charts?
有谁还记得刚才展示那张绿白图表中的信息？
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Hi.
DAVID J. MALAN: Hi.
Yes, hi is the message, but 72, 73 gives us H and I. What's 33?
是的，"HI"是信息，72、73 代表 H 和 I。
Any guesses to 33?
猜得到 33 吗？
Yeah, over here.
是啊，在这里。
Yeah.
So it's an exclamation point.
所以这是一个感叹号。
How would you know that?
你怎么知道？
Well, you really do need some kind of cheat sheet, a.k.a.
好吧，你确实需要一些小抄，也就是......
ASCII in this case.
ASCII 编码表。
And if we look elsewhere-- let me highlight the left of the chart-- you can see that next to 33 in decimal is indeed the exclamation point.
如果再看看其他地方，让我突出显示图表的左边，
你会发现，在十进制的 33 旁边就是感叹号。
So back in the day, a bunch of humans got in a room, decided that, hey, when we start building PCs and later Macs and phones
所以在过去，一群人聚在一起决定，嘿，我们开始制造个人电脑吧，后来还有Mac和手机，
we all just have to agree on this form of representation of letters of the English alphabet, in this case.
在这种情况下，我们必须要对英文字母的这种表现形式达成共识。
We just need to agree on this mapping.
我们只需就这一映射达成一致。
But somewhat curiously, notice this.
但有点奇怪的是，请注意这一点。
It turns out that, once you paint yourself into this corner and start using 65 for A, 66 for B, well, how do you represent 65 the number and 66 the number,
事实证明，一旦你开始用 65 表示 A，66 表示 B，那么该如何表示 65 和 66 这些数字呢？
if you want to do math or use Excel or something like that?
如果你想做数学题或使用 Excel 什么的。
Does anyone see the solution, perhaps?
有谁能找到解决办法吗？
How do you represent the number 1 in ASCII?
如何用 ASCII 码表示数字 1？
Yeah, in the middle?
中间这位？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
是的。
So this is getting a little maybe inception or something, but you could represent numbers with other numbers.
是的，这有点像梦中梦什么的，但的确可以用其他数字来表示数字。
And so if you want to represent the number you and I know as 1, like when you type it on your keyboard, turns out the computer stores that as the decimal number 49.
因此，如果你想表示 1，比如在键盘上输入 1，结果计算机会把它存储为十进制数字 49。
If you hit 2 on your keyboard, the computer is not storing 2, per se.
如果在键盘上敲下 2，计算机本身并没有存储 2。
It's storing the decimal number 50.
它存储的是十进制数 50。
Now, thankfully, the paradox stops there.
现在万幸，矛盾到此为止。
We just have a mapping now of numbers to numbers.
我们现在只需将数字与数字进行映射。
But really, at the end of the day-- and you're going to learn this when we start writing code in that other language, C, next week-- it's just context-dependent, at the end of the day.
但实际上，归根结底——下周我们开始用 C 语言
编写代码时，你就会学到这一点——这只是取决于上下文。
Inside of your Mac, PC, and phone, there's just all of these permutations of bits, all of these patterns of 0's and 1's.
在你的 Mac、PC 和手机里，有所有这些比特的排列组合，所有这些 0 和 1 的模式。
And generally speaking, when you open up a text message that you've received from someone, it's 0's and 1's.
一般来说，当你打开收到的短信时，里面都是 0 和 1。
But obviously, if it's a text message, the whole point of text messages is to send text, and so those patterns of 0's and 1's, by default, will typically be interpreted as letters of the alphabet.
但很明显，如果是文字信息，全部意义就在于发送的文本，
因此这些 0 和 1 的模式，默认情况下通常会被解释为字母表中的字母。
So you won't see 0's and 1's.
因此，你看不到 0 和 1。
You won't see decimal numbers.
也不会看到十进制数。
You'll see the English message that your friend intended.
看到的是朋友发来的英文消息。
By contrast, if you open up something like Excel, that same pattern 0's zeros and 1's might indeed work out to be 72, 73, 33.
相比之下，如果你打开 Excel 等软件，同样的 0 和 1 的模式可能确实是 72、73、33。
You might see cells in your spreadsheet with literally those three numbers.
您可能会在电子表格中看到写有这三个数字的单元格。
Why?
Because spreadsheets are all about numbers and number crunching and math, in many cases.
因为电子表格在很多情况下都是关于数字、数字运算和数学的。
If by contrast, you open up Photoshop and try to look at that same pattern of 0's and 1's, it's not going to be 72, 73, 33.
相比之下，如果打开 Photoshop，尝试查看同样的 0 1 二进制串，就不会是 72、73、33 了。
It's not going to be 0's and 1's.
它不会是二进制表示。
It's not going to be hi.
它不会是"Hi"。
It's going to be some color of the rainbow.
它将是彩虹中的某种颜色。
You're going to use those patterns of 0's and 1's, it turns out too, to represent colors.
原来，这些 0 1 串也可以来表示颜色。
*注：上面几个例子是说，对于同一个二进制串，不同的解释方式会得到不同的结果。
And indeed, so long as you and I just agree, as humans long have, what these patterns are going to be, all of our systems, many of our systems nowadays are indeed interoperable.
只要你我能形成约定，就可以创建一种模式，就像人类长期以来所做一样。
因为模式带有通用性，现在的许多系统都可以进行互操作。
But I'm being very biased here, and indeed, the A and ASCII is very American-centric.
但这里实际上很有偏见，事实上，ASCII 非常以美国为中心。
What do you not see in this chart?
你在这张图表中看不到什么？
If you speak any other language than English, odds are, you're not seeing characters you know and love and need every day to type or send messages.
如果你说的是英语以外的其他语言，
那么你很可能看不到你熟悉和喜爱的、每天都输入或发送信息的字符。
Well, there's a huge character set that's not supported here, whether it's accented characters and a lot of Asian alphabets.
ASCII 不支持大量字符集，包括重音字符和大量亚洲字母。
You have many more symbols than can fit even on this screen here.
那些有特别多字符，这个屏幕是展示不下的。
And so humans kind of painted themselves into a corner, early on, or really,
所以早期，人类有点陷入了一个困境，或者更准确地说，
Americans did.
美国人这样做了。
But on a typical keyboard, US English keyboard, yeah, you have A's and B's and C's, uppercase and lowercase, but you also have accented characters here.
在典型的键盘上，即美国英语键盘上，有 A、B、C等大写和小写字母，也有重音字符。
And nowadays, not sure if this is maybe necessary, but nowadays, you have other characters on your keyboard, like these.
如今，不知道是否还有必要这样做，不过键盘上还有其他字符，比如这些。
And these are a playful incarnation of what's actually a technical solution to this problem.
实际技术解决了刚才提到的问题，所以有了这些有趣的东西。
If I claim for the moment that ASCII historically used 7 bits to represent letters-- and let's just round that up to a byte--
让我告诉你，ASCII历史上使用7位来表示字母，我们就将其四舍五入为一个字节，8位来表示字母，
8 bits to represent letters, ASCII can represent as many as 255, or really 256, total characters.
ASCII 可以表示多达255个，或者实际上是256个不同的字符。
Why 256?
Well, if you have them all 0, that's 0, and the highest number
如果全 0，那就是 0，最大的数字是
I claimed a moment ago was 255.
我刚才说的是 255。
So that's 256 total possibilities.
因此，总共有 256 种可能性。
That's not many letters.
这可没多少字符。
It's fine for English, but not a lot of human languages.
对英语还行，但对很多人类语言就不行了。
So what might the intuitive solution be, if you want to represent accented characters, Asian characters, emoji, even like these, which are just keys on a keyboard nowadays?
如果想要表示带重音的字符、亚洲字符、emoji，
还有键盘上的别的字符，直觉上有什么解决办法？
What's the intuitive solution, if a byte's too few?
如果一个字节太少，直观的解决方案是什么？
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Add another digit.
听众：再加一位数
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
是的。
So add another digit.
所以再加一位数。
Just like we had a 4th volunteer come on up to give us a 4th bid, let's just throw hardware at the problem and use a few more bits.
就像我们让第 4 个志愿者上来举起第四个号牌一样，
我们让硬件来解决问题就可以了，使用更多的位。
So maybe instead of 1 byte, let's use 2, or heck, let's use 3 or 4 bytes.
因此，也许可以用 2 个字节代替 1 个字节，或者干脆用 3 或 4 个字节。
Even though it's getting a little expensive-- we're going from 8 to 16 to 24 or 32 bits-- that's how computers do things, these days.
尽管它会有更高的成本——我们正在从 8 位变为 16 位，再变为 24 位或 32 位，不过如今计算机就是这么做的。
And thankfully, we have so much memory inside of our computers and phones, we can certainly spare a few to represent these things.
还好我们的电脑和手机内存可大了，腾出一些内存来表现这些东西没有问题。
And the solution then to ASCII is what we'll call Unicode.
解决 ASCII 码局限性的办法，就是我们所说的统一码（unicode）。
So Unicode is also just a mapping of numbers to letters but in many different languages.
所以Unicode 也只是数字和字母的映射，但容纳了更多语言。
And indeed, the Unicode Consortium is a bunch of people from all different companies-- a lot of different companies and countries and cultures whose mission,
事实上，Unicode 协会是由一群来自不同公司、不同国家和不同文化背景的人组成的，
as an organization, is to capture digitally all forms of human language in this case.
作为一个组织，就是要以数字方式捕捉人类语言的所有形式。
And to ensure that especially smaller demographics of humans speaking lesser-known languages are nonetheless represented and preserved digitally using some mapping of these 0's and 1's.
此外，还要确保那些少数群体使用的鲜为人知的语言，
能够通过这些 0 和 1 的映射，以数字方式得到表达和保存。
It turns out, though, if you start using 32 bits, as many as 32 bits, to represent characters on a keyboard, that's 4 billion possible permutations of 0's and 1's.
事实上讲，如果开始使用多达 32 位来表示键盘上的字符，那么就有 40 亿种 0 和 1 的可能排列组合。
That's way more than we need for most human languages.
这远远超出了大多数人类语言的需求。
So there's a little bit of room in there for some of those more playful things, like those emoji.
因此，还有点空间可以容纳一些更好玩的东西，比如 emoji 什么的。
So for instance, suppose you got a text message with this pattern of 0's and 1's.
举个例子，假设你收到一条短信，短信内容是 0 和 1 的组合。
Or if we do out the math, suppose you receive a text message that, if you do out the math in decimal, is 4,036,991,106.
或者我们算了算，假设你收到一条短信，按十进制计算是 4,036,991,106。
Anyone know what emoji you're looking at?
有人知道这是什么表情符号吗？
It would be weird if you do, but what is this?
你要是知道才奇怪呢，但这是什么？
Well, it turns out that, as of this past year, this is the most popular emoji to be sent by many measures,
其实，这个表情符号截至去年最受欢迎的表情符号——
Face with Tears of Joy.
笑哭
So that is the pattern that a bunch of humans in the Unicode Consortium decided would represent this.
这就是 Unicode 联盟里那群人敲定的表示模式。
But you'll notice, many of you might have iPhones, some of you might have Android devices too, and sometimes, these don't actually look quite the same.
但你会发现，你们中的许多人可能用 iPhone，有些人用安卓设备，
有时，这些设备上的这个表情看起来不太一样。
This happens to be the current version of Face with Tears of Joy on iOS.
这是 iOS 上 "喜极而泣" 的样子。
On Android, it tends to look a little something more like this, and here is kind of a curiosity.
在安卓系统上，它往往看起来是这样的，而这里就有点奇怪了。
Even though you and I look at these things and they look like images, they're not images.
尽管你我看到的这些东西看起来像图像，但它们并不是图像。
They're characters, at least as we've defined them now in Unicode.
它们是字符，至少是我们现在在 Unicode 中定义的字符。
And iOS and Android and Windows and Facebook and other companies and apps, nowadays, really just have different fonts, if you will.
如今，iOS、Android、Windows、Facebook 以及其他公司和应用程序的字体都不尽相同。
So just like fonts with English and other languages can give you different characters with serifs or not, emoji are themselves, yes, drawings that someone made, but they're really just a font.
因此，就像英文字体和其他语言的字体可以给你提供有衬线或无衬线的不同字符一样，
emoji 本身也是有人绘制的图画，但它们实际上只是一种字体。
And so that same pattern of 0's and 1's might just render slightly differently on someone's phone or another.
因此，同样是 0 和 1 的模式，不同人手机上呈现的效果可能会略有不同。
If you've ever gotten like an icon on your phone that's broken, and you've been sent an emoji, but it's like a square or something arbitrary and not sensible
如果你的手机上出现了一个没有正确展示的图标，或者你收到了一个表情符号，
但是它却是一个奇怪方块而不是正常的表情符号，
it might just mean that you have not updated to the latest version of iOS or Android, which just updates the font of supported emoji.
可能意味着你还没有更新到最新版本的iOS或Android，它会更新支持的表情符号的字体。
Because those folks at Unicode, pretty much every year nowadays, are adding more and more emoji to that particular character set.
因为如今，Unicode 的工作人员几乎每年都会在这个字符集中添加越来越多的表情符号。
Now, I went down the rabbit hole of figuring out the other day just which are the most popular emoji these days.
前几天，我找出了最近最流行的表情符号。
*注：rabbit hole 指的是一个非常引人入胜和耗时的话题。
On Twitter specifically, this past year, the most popular emoji, by contrast, was Loudly Crying Face.
相比之下，去年 Twitter 上最流行的表情符号是 "大声哭泣"。
I don't know if that says more about 2021 or about Twitter, but you'll see different trends, certainly, in how these are used.
我不知道哪个更能说明 2021 年的情况，但你肯定能看到人们使用 emoji 的不同趋势。
But even humans themselves didn't necessarily think two steps ahead, and now a lot of the emoji are the default yellow color.
但是，人类没那么多先见之明，现在很多表情符号都是默认的黄色。
But there's a lot of emoji that aren't these cartoon characters, but they're meant to represent humans in various professions or gestures or the like.
但还有很多表情符号并不是这些卡通人物，而是表示各种职业、手势或其他事物的符号。
And nowadays too, you've probably noticed on your phone and Macs and PCs, there are different skin tones that you can assign to certain emojis.
如今，你可能也注意到了，在你的手机、Mac 和 PC 上，你可以为某些表情符号指定不同的肤色。
If it's supported by the company and by Unicode, you can actually touch and hold on a certain emoji, and then you can choose the appropriate skin tone to represent yourself or someone else.
如果软件和 Unicode 支持，
你就可以触摸并按住某个表情符号，然后选择合适的肤色来代表自己或他人。
And that then modifies the display.
修改会呈现在显示器上。
Well, let's just think for a moment here, how did Apple and Google and Microsoft and others go about implementing support for emoji with different skin tones?
我们不妨想一想，苹果、谷歌和微软等公司是如何实现对不同肤色表情符号的支持的？
How could you do this?
你会怎么做呢？
If you want to represent some smiling emoji but in five, in this case, different skin tones, you could come up with what?
如果你想用五个不同肤色表示一些微笑的表情符号，你能想到什么办法？
Five different patterns that are identical, structurally, except for the skin tone used in places in that image.
五种不同的图案在结构上完全相同，只是在这个图案的某些地方肤色不同。
But that's a little inefficient to just do copy, paste, paste, paste, paste, and change the color in Photoshop, if you will.
如果只是复制、粘贴、粘贴、粘贴、粘贴，然后在 Photoshop 中更改颜色，效率就有点低了。
That's going to use more bits, more information than you might need to.
这样会浪费很多比特存储不需要的信息。
How else, if you now start to think a little bit more like a computer scientist, if at the end of the day, all you have are 0's and 1's
现在来像计算机科学家那样思考问题，说到底你所拥有的只是 0 和 1，那还能怎样呢？
how else could you implement skin tones, might you think?
你觉得还能如何实现肤色？
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: RGB.
观众：RGB.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
好的。
So RGB, we'll come to that in just a moment.
那 RGB，我们稍后再谈。
That stands for Red, Green, Blue. That's one way.
RGB 代表红、绿、蓝。这是一种方法。
In this case, though, I'm seeking an alternative to just using five different patterns of 0's and 1's to represent the same emoji but different skin tones.
不过现在，对于不同肤色的相同表情符号，我正在寻找一种替代方法表示，
而不仅仅是用五个不同的图案来表示。
So not quite RGB.
因此不完全是 RGB。
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
好的。
So store one copy of the emoji and then store different variants of the color that you want to assign to that emoji.
因此，先存储一个表情符号的版本，然后存储，该表情符号指定颜色后的不同变体。
*注：这里的意思是，重用一组表情里相同的部分，只用额外位标识不同的部分，以节省空间。
Yeah.
So this is actually an example of-- do you want to elaborate?
所以这实际上是一个例子 —— 你想详细说明一下吗？
AUDIENCE: You could use a loop.
听众：你可以使用循环。
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
大卫-J-马兰：好的。
So you can use a loop to actually output these things.
因此，你可以使用循环来实际输出这些内容。
More on that in a moment.
稍后详细说说。
Let me go down this road for just a moment.
让我先顺着思路往下走。
This would be in some sense a better design, if you will, but why?
这在某种意义上是一种更好的设计，但为什么呢？
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: A filter?
听众：一个滤镜？
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
大卫-J-马兰：好的。
So filter, if we think of in the Instagram sense.
所以，如果我们从 Instagram 的角度来考虑，这就是滤镜。
You can change the color of something, and that could be related here too.
用滤镜可以改变某些东西的颜色，这也可能与解决这个问题有关。
AUDIENCE: Could it be another font [INAUDIBLE]
听众：会不会是另一种字体？
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, interesting.
哦，有点意思。
So maybe it could be just a completely different font.
所以，也许只是一种完全不同的字体。
And you have five different fonts that are almost identical, except for the various interpretations of skin tone for those same emoji.
可这样的话，这五种字体里大部分的表情是重复的，除了对同一表情符号的不同肤色解释。
Let me spoil.
让我先透露一下。
I think if we go down this one particular road, the way the Unicode folks decided to do this some years ago
我认为应该走这条特定的道路，那就是 Unicode 的工作人员在几年前决定的方式，
where the first byte or bytes that you receive via text or email just represent like the structure of the emoji, the default yellow version, thereof.
通过文本或电子邮件收到的前一个或几个字节仅仅表示表情符号的结构，
即黄色版本的默认表情符号。
But if it's immediately followed by a certain pattern of bits that these humans standardize to represent each of these different shades of skin tone
但是，如果紧随其后的是这些人类作为标准的、代表每种不同色调肤色的特定比特模式，
then the phone, the Mac, the PC will change that default color, yellow in most cases, to whatever the more apt human tone is.
那么手机、Mac 和 PC 将会将默认颜色（在大多数情况下为黄色）更改为更合适的肤色。
So you just use twice as many bits, but you don't use five times as many bits.
所以你只需使用两倍于先前的比特，但也比重复五次要好。
So what do I mean?
我说的是什么意思？
You don't have five completely distinct patterns, per se.
这一组表情本身并没有五种完全不同的模式。
For each of these possible variants, you have a representation of just the emoji itself, structurally, and then reusable patterns for those five skin tones.
对于这些可变的表情，
你有一个仅表示表情符号本身结构的表示，然后还有五种肤色的可重复使用的模式。
Unfortunately, that wasn't quite versatile enough for other features that were in the pipeline, and nowadays too, and there's a double meaning now to representation.
遗憾的是，这对于正在进行中的其他功能来说并不太灵活，现在也是如此。
Emojis intended to focus on certain professions, and early on too, were certain professions associated with certain genders and vice versa.
从早期开始，表情符号中就存在一些职业，但某些职业与性别关联起来了。
And you couldn't necessarily be one gender or another, in a certain profession or another.
可你的职业并不能定义你的性别。
There were these combinatorics that just weren't possible.
但穷尽所有组合是不可能实现的。
But nowadays, as you might have seen, you can have couples in love for instance that actually look a little more like three emojis, but just kind of combined into one.
现在，你可能先前就见过，比如说，你可以看到一对热恋中的情侣，
他们实际上看起来更像三个表情符号，只是有点合二为一。
And indeed, this is just one key press on your phone, and you can combine different emoji on the left and then the right with the emoji in the middle.
事实上，这只需在手机上简单操作，
就能将左边和右边的不同表情符号与中间的表情符号组合在一起。
And so it turns out how computers nowadays represent these patterns are one set of bits for the character on the left, one set of bits for a character on the right,
因此，现在的计算机在表示这些模式时，左边的字符用一组比特表示，右边的字符用一组比特表示、
one set of bits for whatever emoji you want in the middle.
再一组比特表示你想放中间的表情符号。
And then you assemble more complicated compositions of emoji by just reusing those same patterns and bits and bits.
然后，你只需重复使用这些相同的图案和零碎的部分，就能组合出更复杂的表情符号。
The Unicode folks don't have to come up with a whole new representation for some very specific incarnation.
Unicode 的工作人员不必为某个非常特定的表情符号创造一个全新的表示方式。
They can create one for person, for male, for, female for other characters that you might want to display, and reuse those same patterns of 0's and 1's.
他们为人、男性、女性和其他你想要显示的字符创建一个表示方式，
并重复使用这些相同的 0 1 模式。
And so here, you see the imperfection, of or lack of foresight, of humans for building a system early on that was entirely American-centric, no characters, emoji, or the like, that's evolved too.
在这个变迁中，你可以看到人类的不完美，或者说缺乏远见，
因为人类在早期建立了一个完全以美国为中心的系统，
缺少字符、表情符号什么的，但现在也发展完善起来了。
And so that's an important detail in computing, nowadays.
是的，这在计算机中是一个重要的细节。
It too is evolving, and the languages you're about to learn in the coming days, those too are evolving as well.
它仍然在不断发展，而你们在接下来的日子里将要学习的语言，也同样在不断发展。
And new features are getting added, and even programming languages have version numbers.
新功能不断增加，甚至编程语言也有版本号。
You might have a different version of an app on your phone.
大家手机上可能有不同版本的应用程序。
Programming languages too have different versions as well.
编程语言也有不同的版本。
Questions then thus far on how information is represented using ASCII or Unicode or anything in between?
到目前为止，在如何使用 ASCII 或 Unicode 或其它编码方式来表示信息方面，大家还有疑问吗？
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, good question.
哦，问得好。
So to recap, why can't you just-- well, let me summarize that as why can't you similarly use different patterns to change the context of what these patterns of bits represent, whether it's
他是问，为什么不能就用一些比特位来标识这些二进制串表示的内容，
*注：在前面提到，对同一数据的不同解释方法会影响得到的结果。
所以为什么不用一些位来标识该怎么解释数据？就不会产生歧义了。
whether it's a number or a letter or a graphic?
无论是数字、字母还是图形？
*注：在前面提到，对同一数据的不同解释方法会影响得到的结果。
所以为什么不用一些位来标识该怎么解释数据？就不会产生歧义了。
In actuality, that's kind of what's happening underneath the hood.
实际上，在计算机底层就是这样的。
It's not standardized in quite the same way, but starting next week, when we transition from scratch to C, you'll learn about types, data types.
只不过没有像unicode一样完全标准化。
从下周开始，当我们从Scratch过渡到C时，你将学习数据类型。
Where the onus initially is going to be on you, the programmer, to tell the program whether or not this pattern of bits should be interpreted as a number or as a letter or as a color or something else.
最初，你作为程序员的责任是告诉程序，
这些比特模式应该被解释为数字、字母、颜色还是别的什么。
Nowadays, though, and toward the end of the semester, you'll use languages, like Python, where the computer just figures it out
然后到学期末，你将使用像Python这样的语言，计算机会通过上下文自动判断，
for you by context, which makes it even easier and faster to program as well.
这使得编程变得更加容易和快速。
Other questions on Unicode, ASCII or the like?
有关 Unicode、ASCII 还有其他疑问吗？
All right. Well, how about just a few other forms of information?
好吧那么，其他形式的信息呢？
RGB was called out earlier, Red, Green, Blue.
前面提到了 RGB，即红、绿、蓝。
How do images get represented in computers?
计算机如何处理图像？
Well, in fact, it's typically an assembly of some amount of red, some amount of green, some amount of blue, but there are other representations.
实际上颜色通常是由红色、绿色和蓝色组合而成，但也有其他表现形式。
If you're a graphic designer, you might know them, but RGB is still pretty common.
如果你是平面设计师，你可能知道它们，RGB 还是很常见的。
What does this mean?
这意味着什么？
This means to represent every dot on your phone or every dot on your TV or your laptop or desktop, there is a number representing how much red that dot should show,
这意味着，手机上的每一个点、电视上的每一个点、笔记本电脑或台式机上的每一个点，
都有一个代表该点应显示多少红色的数字，
a number representing how much green, and a number representing how much blue it should show, red, green, blue, respectively.
有一个代表该点应显示多少绿色的数字，还有一个数字代表多少蓝色。记住分别是，红、绿、蓝。
So for instance, if a dot on your screen were using these three numbers, these three values or bytes, 72, 73, 33, in a text message or email, that would be interpreted as I claimed "HI!."
例如，如果在文本消息或电子邮件中使用了这三个值：
72、73、33，那么这将被解释为我所说的"HI!"。
But in Photoshop or in some graphical program, that same pattern would be interpreted as let's call it a medium amount of red, a medium amount of green, and a little bit of blue.
但是在 Photoshop 或一些图形程序中，这同样的模式会被解释为，
中等量的红色、中等量的绿色和一点点蓝色。
And why medium and little?
为什么是 "中 "和 "少"？
Turns out, each of these are bytes, the smallest value you can have in a byte we said is 0.
原来，这些都是字节，我们说的字节中最小的值是 0。
The largest value you can have a byte is 255, so I'm just kind of spitballing here.
一个字节的最大值是 255，所以我只是随便举了个例子。
This is like medium, medium, and a low amount of red, green, blue, specifically.
这就像是中等量的红色、中等量的绿色和一点点蓝色，具体来说是这样的。
Those three colors, like wavelengths of light, are combined in such a way that you would have this dot on the screen, a sort of murky shade of yellow or brown.
这三种颜色，就像光的波长一样，以这样的方式组合在一起，
你就会在屏幕上看到这个点，呈现出一种混浊的黄色或棕色。
That is how a computer would store precisely that color, and in fact, we've seen this color.
这就是计算机精确存储颜色的方式，实际上，我们之前也见过这种颜色。
When you type in Face with Tears of Joy, generally, on your screen, it looks like this, typically much smaller.
一般来说，当您在屏幕上输入 emoji "喜极而泣"时，它看起来是这样的，但通常要小得多。
But let's zoom in, or let's Zoom in a little more.
不过，让我们放大一点，再放大一点。
What are you starting to see, if you know the term?
如果你知道这个词，你看到的是什么？
AUDIENCE: Pixels.
观众：像素。
DAVID J. MALAN: So pixels, it's getting very pixelated.
是像素，它变得非常像素化。
A pixel is just a dot on the screen, and if you really zoom in on it, you can literally see all of the dots that compose an emoji
一个像素就是屏幕上的一个点，如果你真的放大它，
in this case on iOS, in the font that Apple is using to represent this particular pattern of 0's and 1's.
你可以清楚地看到在 iOS 系统中，
用来表示这个特定 0 和 1 模式的字体中，组成一个表情符号的所有点（像素）。
So one of those yellow dots-- and there's many of them all kind of blend together here-- each dot on the screen I claim is 3 bytes.
屏幕上的每一个黄点需要 3 个字节。
How much red, green, blue for this dot?
这个点需要多少红、绿、蓝？
How much red green blue for this dot?
这个点需要多少红绿蓝？
And you'll notice too, that when it gets to be sort of brownish here, the dots really stand out.
你也会注意到，当它变成褐色时，小点就会非常显眼。
The 3 values, the 3 bytes, a.k.a. 24 bits, are just slightly different.
这 3 个值、3 个字节（又称 24 位）只是略有不同。
And so underneath the hood, this is why images, photographs that you take or gif that you download, get so darn big, potentially, because you have a number representing every dot on the screen.
这就是你拍摄的图片或下载的 gif 为什么这样大，因为屏幕上的每一个点都需要用数字代表。
Well, if this I claim is indeed how images are typically represented, using pattern of bits that are assigned to some amount of red, green, or blue, how do you get video?
嗯，如果我刚才介绍的确实是图像通常的表示方式，
即使用位模式来表示一定数量的红色、绿色或蓝色，那么视频是如何产生的呢？
What is a video, if at the end of the day, all we have are 0's and 1's?
说到底我们所拥有的只是 0 和 1，那么视频又怎么表示呢？
What's a video, perhaps?
视频其实是什么？
Yeah?
Let's go here, way in back.
马上就来深入讨论。
Yeah. Pixels really changing values over time. and do you want to confirm or deny, the hand that went up here?
是的，视频实际上是像素随时间在变化。请问你举手是有什么事吗？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, or equivalently, a sequence of images that, over time, are changing on the screen.
是的，或者等价地说，视频是一系列图像，随着时间在屏幕上变化。
So both of those are valid interpretations, and just for fun, if you grew up with these picture books, you might remember a little something like this. if we could dim the lights?
这两种解释都是有道理的。来点好玩的，
如果你们小时候看过这些图画书，你们可能会记得类似这样的场景。调暗灯光可以吗？
[MUSIC PLAYING]
So that's the old school analog way to implement a video, in the sense that that artist wrote out like hundreds of pieces of paper, with almost identical images, but where the ink from their pencil
那就是旧式的模拟视频实现方式，艺术家会手写上百张几乎相同的图纸，但他们的笔迹和颜色
or pen was slightly moving.
会稍微有所变化。
And if you digitize that, such that each of those strokes are represented with dots instead, that's really what you're seeing is a sequence of all of these images flying across the screen.
如果你将这些手绘的图像数字化，用点阵来表示每一笔，
那么你实际上看到的就是一系列图像在屏幕上快速切换。
And if we dive into the real world, if you've ever watched a film, a Hollywood movie is typically 24 FPS, Frames Per Second.
现实世界中，如果你看过电影，好莱坞电影通常是每秒 24 帧（FPS）。
That really means you're seeing 24 images per second, or on TV or in soap operas, it's often 30 frames per second.
这实际上意味着你每秒看到 24 张图像，而在电视或肥皂剧中，通常是每秒 30 帧。
That makes things look a little more smooth.
这使得画面看起来更加流畅。
So it's not actual motion picture, if you will.
所以它并不是真正的动态影像。
It's sequences of pictures, and your brain and mind are interpolating that, oh, this is smooth movement, even though we're just seeing a lot of pictures really fast.
它其实是一系列图片的序列，而你的大脑会插值，认为这是平滑的运动，
即使我们只是快速地看到很多图片。
Now, that gets really big, and we'll talk later in the semester how you can compress information, so that you're not using way more bits than you actually need to.
现在，这个过程会产生非常大的数据量，
我们将在本学期晚些时候讨论如何压缩信息，从而避免使用比实际需要更多的存储空间。
And there's fancy algorithms that folks have developed, but at the end of the day, that's really all a video might be is a sequence of images.
虽然人们开发出了各种花哨的算法，但归根结底，视频可能只是一连串的图像而已。
Conversely, if you want to represent the music that accompanies that or something else, if any of you play an instrument and can read sheet music, how could you digitize this?
那如果你想表示伴随视频的音乐或其他内容，如果你们中有人会演奏乐器并且能读乐谱，
你们可以将这些数字化，如何做呢？
[PIANO MUSIC]
Like how could you represent musical notes in a computer?
比如，如何在计算机中表现音符？
You and I hear them when we play files, but what's really going on underneath the hood?
我们在播放文件时能听到它们的声音，但底层发生了什么？
Any musicians, piano players?
有人会演奏乐器吗？
Anyone?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Hertz value?
听众：赫兹值？
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, so Hertz value, so some frequency.
好的，赫兹值，也就是某种频率。
So sound is some frequency, and it's kind of hitting your eardrum.
声音是一种频率，它会撞击你的耳膜。
And that's what makes it sound low or high or somewhere in between.
这就是声音低沉、高亢或介于两者之间的原因。
So maybe we could assign, just like there's letters A through G here, maybe we could assign specific frequency values, which are just going to be numbers measured in something
也许我们可以像这里的字母 A 到 G 一样，为音乐分配特定的频率值，
which are just going to be numbers measured in something called Hertz, something per second.
这些频率值只是以赫兹（Hz）为单位的数字，表示每秒发生的次数。
And maybe we could have a few other numbers for each of these notes, not just the note or the frequency.
或许我们还可以为每个音符添加一些其他数字，不仅仅是音符或频率。
Maybe, we could represent the loudness of it, like how hard or how softly a human might equivalently press it.
也许我们可以表示音符的响度，就像人类可能会用多么大力气按键一样。
Maybe a third number, like duration, like how long is there finger on the keyboard?
或者再添加一个数字，比如音符持续的时间，就像手指在键盘上停留了多久。
So you can imagine quantifying something like music that in the real world is perfectly continuous as something more discrete, by representing each note over time as just some sequence of values.
你可以想象将一些在现实世界中是完全连续的东西，
量化为更离散的形式，通过在时间上表示每个音符为一系列值。
And there's so many different ways to do this, MIDI, if you've heard, mp3's, AAC.
有很多不同的方式可以做到这一点，MIDI、mp3、AAC 等。
Almost all of the file extensions you see on your Mac or PC, if you see them at all, ultimately just mean there's a different form of representation for, in this case, something like sound.
几乎你在 Mac 或 PC 上看到的所有文件扩展名，
最终都意味着某种形式的表现，就像在这种情况下，音频文件。
So let me just stipulate, there are these and many more ways to represent inputs and outputs, and thankfully, humans have standardized a lot of this.
因此，我只想说，现在有这么多更多的方法来表示输入和输出，
幸运的是，人类已经对很多这些进行了标准化。
They don't always agree, and this is why we have different file formats for Apple numbers and Microsoft Excel and Google Spreadsheets and stupid incompatibilities like that.
它们并不总是一致的，这就是为什么苹果的 Numbers、
微软的 Excel 和谷歌的 Spreadsheets 之类的软件有不同的文件格式，导致了恼人的不兼容性。
But generally speaking, humans have standardized how we represent the inputs and outputs to and from problems.
但总体而言，人类已经标准化了如何表示问题的输入和输出。
But let's now focus on this Black box, so to speak, in the middle, this abstraction.
但现在让我们聚焦于这个黑盒子，所谓的中间层，这个抽象层面。
So abstraction is technically a term that you'll see all over the place in computer science, and really, problem solving
因此，从技术上讲，抽象是一个在计算机科学中随处可见的术语，而实际上，问题解决也是如此。
that just refers to the simplification of something, so that you don't focus on the lower level implementation details.
抽象就是指简化某些东西，使你不必关注低层次的实现细节。
You really just focus on the high level goals or the process itself.
你只需关注高层次的目标或过程本身。
Therefore, your car, if you have a license and have driven or have been in a car, a car, so far as you're concerned, is probably an abstraction.
因此，如果你有驾照、开过车或坐过车，那么你的车，对你来说很可能是一个抽象概念。
Most of us, if you're like me, probably don't really know or care how the engine works and all the parts that are moving.
咱大多数人可能并不真正了解或关心发动机的工作原理和所有运动部件。
To you, it's just a way of getting from point A to point B. It's an abstraction, but someone, hopefully the mechanic, does know those lower level implementation details.
对你而言，它只是从 A 点到 B 点的一种方式。
它是一种抽象，但有机械师，了解这些更低级别的实现细节。
If you had to understand how a car works every time you want to go to school or to the store, it's probably going to be a pretty slow process.
如果每次你想去学校或去商店都必须理解汽车是如何工作的，那可能会变得相当慢。
You just want to think and operate at this higher level of abstraction, and we're going to do this all the time when writing code and solving problems.
你只是希望在更高级别的抽象层次上思考和操作，我们在编写代码和解决问题时将一直这样做。
So what then is in this black box, this abstraction at the moment?
那么，在这个黑盒子里，在这个抽象的概念里，究竟有什么呢？
Well, generally, it's what a computer scientist would call an algorithm, step-by-step instructions for solving some problem.
一般来说，计算机科学家会称之为算法，即解决某个问题的分步指令。
Now, let's consider the implementation details, that is to say how you might solve certain problems, and let's take a old school example but in modern form.
现在，让我们考虑一下实现细节，也就是说如何解决某些问题，让我们举一个例子。
This icon, if you have an iPhone, is, of course for your contacts application.
这个图标，如果你有iPhone的话，当然是你的联系人应用程序图标。
And if you've got a whole bunch of family members or friends or colleagues in your phonebook, you have some kind of contacts pictured here, and it's alphabetized typically by first name and last name.
如果你的通讯录里有许多家人、朋友或同事，你在这里会看到一些联系人的图片，通常按照名字的首字母和姓氏进行字母顺序排列。
And odds are, you and I are in the habit, if they're not already a favorite, of like clicking on Search and then using autocomplete.
而且很有可能，我们都习惯于在不是收藏联系人的情况下，点击搜索然后使用自动补全。
And what happens when you start typing autocomplete?
当你开始输入自动补全时会发生什么呢？
Well if you type in the letter H, you'll see only, presumably,
当你输入字母H时，你会看到，
Hagrid, Harry, Hermione, and so forth.
只有 Hagrid、Harry、Hermione 等等。
If you type in H-A that shows you only Hagrid and Harry, and it all happens super fast.
如果输入 H-A，则只显示海格和哈利，而且速度超快。
So how is that happening?
这是怎么回事呢？
Well, typically, you could just start at the top and look to the bottom, searching for all of the H's or all of the H-A's, but for larger data sets that's going to get slow.
通常情况下，你可以从顶部开始，一直到底部，
搜索所有的 H 或所有的 H-A，但对于较大的数据集来说，这样做会很慢。
For the Googles of the world, that's going to get really slow.
对于世界级的公司谷歌来说，这将变得非常缓慢。
And even on our phones when you have hundreds, thousands of contacts, eventually, even that kind of approach, that algorithm step by step it might be slow.
即使在我们的手机上，当你有成百上千个联系人时，
即使是这种算法一步一步来，也可能会很慢。
So how might we go about searching for someone in a phonebook like this, like say John Harvard?
那么，我们该如何在这样的电话簿中搜索某个人，比如 John Harvard？
Well, here's an old school incarnation of this, and odds are, you might not have had occasion to even physically use this thing, nowadays.
这就是一个老旧的电话簿，而如今，你可能连实际使用它的机会都没有了。
And in fact, this is a bit of a white lie, because this is the yellow pages, which means this is a book of companies not people.
其实我撒了个弥天大谎，因为这是黄页，这是一本关于公司而不是联系人的书。
But this is all you can find, and at that, it's even hard to find this.
但你只能找到这个了，甚至连这些都很难找到。
But this is the same thing in analog form, physical form.
至少这物理形式是一样的。
So if I wanted to search for someone like John Harvard, how could I do that?
那么，如果我想搜索 John Harvard 这样的人，该怎么做呢？
Well, I could start on page 1, and I could start searching for page 2, page 3, page 4, page 5.
好吧，我可以从第 1 页开始，然后开始搜索第 2 页、第 3 页、第 4 页、第 5 页。
A little hard to do physically, especially since no one's used this phone book in a lot of years.
要做到这一点有点困难，尤其是这本电话簿已经很多年没人用了。
But is this algorithm correct, turning page by page, very inelegantly?
但是，有点不太优雅地一页一页翻找，这种算法是否正确？
Is this correct?
这样做对吗？
Will I find John Harvard, if he's in here?
如果里面有 John Harvard，我能找到他吗？
All right.
So yes.
This is a little stupidly tedious, because if there's like 1,000 pages, he might be a few hundred pages into this, but it's correct.
这有点愚蠢又乏味，因为如果有 1000 页的话，可能需要翻查几百页，但这是正确的。
At some point, I will find him, and if he's on the page, I'll be able to call.
总有一天，我会找到他，如果他在簿上，我就能打电话给他。
Why?
Because presumably, the names are alphabetized in here, and there's no cheat sheet on the edge.
因为可以假定这些名字在这里是按字母顺序排列的，在边缘没有快速索引。
So I have to search for John Harvard from left to right, searching for H, if it's alphabetized by last name.
所以我必须从左到右搜索 John Harvard，如果按照姓氏的首字母进行字母顺序排列的话。
Well, what would be marginally better?
那么，有什么稍微好一点的方法呢？
Well, how about two pages at a time?
如果一次翻动两页呢？
It's hard to do with a 20-year-old phone book, where the pages are grown together, but 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12.
在一个 20 年历史的电话簿上可能有些困难，因为页面可能会黏在一起。
按两页来查找，2、4、6、8、10、12...
This algorithm, is this correct?
这个算法，正确吗？
AUDIENCE: No.
听众：不是。
DAVID J. MALAN: All right, so no.
戴维-J-马兰：好吧，确实不对。
Why?
AUDIENCE: You're skipping pages.
听众：你在跳页。
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
是的。
So I'm skipping every other page.
我每隔一页都会跳过。
So if I don't consider that, and I find myself in like the I section or the J section, well, I might accidentally conclude,
如果我没有考虑到这一点，并且我发现自己在 I 或者 J 部分，我可能会错误地得出结论说：
nope, I haven't found John Harvard yet, just because I skipped him, because it was sandwiched between two pages.
不，我还没有找到 John Harvard ，但这只是因为我跳过了他，他夹在两页之间。
Now, I can fix this, I think, if I do hit the I section, well, let me just double back one page, just in case he was in that last page.
现在，我可以修复这个问题，如果我找到 I 开头了，我可以往回退一页，以防他就在那页。
So it's recoverable, but it's almost twice as fast, minus that hiccup there.
因此，这个问题是可以补救的，除去刚才的小插曲，速度几乎快了一倍。
But what most of us would do, and what your phones are doing, albeit digitally, is they open up roughly to the middle of the phonebook.
不过大多数人以及你们的手机，尽管是数字化的，它们会大致翻开电话簿的中间。
And they look down, and they say, oh, I'm in roughly the M section.
他们低头一看，说，哦，我大概在 M 部分。
So I'm roughly halfway through the 1,000-page phonebook.
因此，1000 页的电话簿我大概翻了一半。
But what do I now know about John Harvard?
但我现在对 John Harvard 了解多少呢？
Where is he, to my left or to my right?
他在哪里，是在我左手边这部分还是在右边这部分？
All right.
So alphabetically, he's presumably to my left, and so here I can, both metaphorically and physically, tear the problem in half.
从字母顺序来看，他在我左边，所以我可以同时在逻辑上和物理上，把问题分成两半。
You don't need to be impressed.
你不需要感到惊讶，
It's really easy down the spine that way, but I know that John Harvard is to the left here.
这么撕下来不太费劲的。不管怎样现在我知道了 John Harvard 就在左边。
But now I can throw, unnecessarily dramatically, half and page one out of the way, and what do I now know?
然后我可以把没用的一半，...还有第一页一起扔掉，有点戏剧性了哈，但现在我知道了什么？
I've gone from 1,000 pages to like 500.
我已经从 1000 页减少到 500 页左右。
I can repeat roughly the same algorithm.
我可以重复大致相同的算法。
Go to the half of this, and so this time, I went back a little too far.
这一次我退回得有点过头了。
I'm in now the E section.
我现在在 E 部分。
So what do I know?
那我知道了什么？
Is John Harvard to my left or to my right?
John Harvard 是在我左边还是右边？
To my right, so I can, again, tear the problem in half.
在我右边，所以我可以再次把问题分成两半。
Throw this half away, and now I'm really flying.
扔掉这一半，这样找真的很快。
I'm doing it verbally slowly, but that went from 1,000 pages to 500 to now 250.
我现在慢慢口述，一开始有 1000 页，后来减少到 500 页，然后再到 250 页。
And now I can do it again, 125.
然后我再次进行处理，减少到 125 页。
I do it again, roughly like 67, and keep doing it again and again and again, until I get left with, hopefully, just one single page or in this case an ad for, ironically, a mechanic.
再来一次，大约 67 页，不断重复这个过程，一遍又一遍，直到最后只剩下，
我们希望只剩下一页，呃这个例子中是一个广告，有点好笑，它是一个修车厂的广告。
OK, so what is the implication for our performance?
那么，这对性能有什么影响呢？
Well, let's just do this sort of in the abstract, if you will, if that first algorithm were to be plotted just quickly on a chart without even numbers.
好的，我们来抽象地进行描述，
假设我们将第一个算法的运行时间绘制在一个图表上，不考虑具体的数字。
Here's my x-axis, size of problem on the x-axis.
这里是我们的 x 轴，问题的规模在 x 轴上表示。
So the bigger the problem, the farther out that way.
问题越大，x 轴上的数值越大。
Time to solve the problem.
是时候解决问题了。
The higher you go up on the y-axis, the more time you're taking to solve it.
解决问题所需的时间在 y 轴上表示，y 轴上的数值越大，解决问题所需的时间越长。
How would we draw the running time, the amount of time taken to run that first algorithm?
那么我们如何绘制第一个算法的运行时间曲线呢？
Well, it's going to be a straight line.
嗯，这将是一条直线。
Why?
Because if you add one more page next year because more people move to Cambridge, you're going to add one more page turn potentially, so one more second, one more unit of time.
因为如果明年我们再增加一页（问题规模增大），由于更多人搬到了剑桥，
你可能需要再翻一页，因而增加一秒，增加一个时间单位。
So it's a straight line.
所以这是一条直线。
And we'll abstract it away as "n."
我们用 "n" 来抽象表示这个直线。
If there's n pages in the phone book, the slope of this line is essentially n.
如果电话簿有 n 页，那么这条直线的斜率基本上就是 n。
The second algorithm, wherein I was doing two pages at a time, was twice as fast, but it's still a straight line.
第二个算法，其中我一次处理两页，速度是原来的两倍，但它仍然是一条直线。
And in fact, let me just draw some dotted lines here.
实际上，让我在这里画一些虚线。
If the phone book is this big, with my first algorithm, it might take this many units of time, this many steps, this many page turns.
如果电话簿这么大，用第一个算法，可能需要这么多时间单位，这么多步骤，这么多翻页次数。
But with that second algorithm, notice that the intersection is much lower on the yellow line than on the red.
但是对于第二个算法，请注意交点要比红线低得多。
So n over 2 means there's half as many pages here, if n is the number of pages.
因此， n 除以 2 意味着这里有一半的页面，如果 n 是页面数量的话。
So indeed, that algorithm-- the second one-- is twice as fast minus the little hiccup that I have to double back one page.
所以确实，第二个算法效率是第一个的两倍，不提我不得不返回一页的小插曲的话。
But that's not a big deal if I'm still doing things twice as fast.
不过，如果做这件事的速度只比别人快一倍，那也没什么大不了的。
But the third algorithm looks fundamentally different.
但是第三个算法看起来根本就不一样。
It looks like this.
它看起来是这样的。
Logarithms, if you recall from high school or prior-- if you don't, that's fine too.
对数函数，如果你还记得高中或之前学过的话，如果不记得也没关系。
It's just a fundamentally different function, a different shape.
它形状上和前两个有根本上的不同。
And notice that the green line is going up and up and up but a much slower rate of increase, which means crazy things are possible.
请注意绿线在上升，但增长速度要慢得多，这意味着一个很难以置信的结论。
If two towns in Massachusetts, like Cambridge and Allston, across the river, merge next year, for instance, in terms of their phone book, they're phone book just got twice as big.
如果马萨诸塞州的两个小镇，比如河对岸的剑桥和阿尔斯顿明年合并，
那么就电话簿而言，它们的电话簿就变大了一倍。
For the first algorithm, that's going to take me twice as many steps to go through.
对于第一种算法，我需要花两倍的时间来完成。
The second algorithm, almost it's going to take me 50% more steps to go through, two at a time.
第二种算法，差不多要多花一半的步骤，一次两步。
But the third algorithm, that I ended with, tearing things again and again, dividing and conquering, if you will, in half and in half and in half, how many more steps will my third algorithm
对于我最后提到的第三个算法，
不断地二分，分而治之，将问题一分为二，再一分为二，再一分为二，
take if Cambridge and Allston merge into a phone book that's twice as big?
如果剑桥和奥尔斯顿合并成一个电话簿，
而这个电话簿的规模是之前的两倍，我的第三个算法将需要多出多少步骤呢？
AUDIENCE: One more step.
听众：只多一步。
DAVID J. MALAN: Just one more step, right?
就多了一步，对吧？
No big deal.
没什么大不了的。
You just take a really big bite out of the problem once you decide if John Harvard is to the left or to the right.
一旦你确定 John Harvard 在电话簿的左边还是右边，你就一下子解决了很大一部分问题。
And so you've made much faster progress.
因此，你取得了更快的进展。
And so this, in essence, is what your computer, your phone is probably doing underneath the hood when searching for Harry or Hermione or Hagrid or anyone else because it's that much faster,
因此，这本质上就是你的计算机、手机在搜索 Harry 或 Hermione 或 Hagrid
或其他任何人时所做的事情，因为这样做会快得多，
especially when you have large data.
尤其是在数据量较大的情况下。
If you don't have that many contacts, it probably doesn't matter if you search from top to bottom or more in the form of this divide-and-conquer algorithm.
如果你的联系人不是很多，
那么按照从上到下的顺序搜索或者采用分而治之的算法可能并没有太大区别。
But if you're the Googles of the world or you're analyzing large data sets, indeed, this is going to add up quite quickly.
但是，如果你是像谷歌这样的公司，或者你正在分析大规模的数据集，
这种算法的效率差异就会迅速显现出来。
So where do we go with this?
那么我们接下来要做什么呢？
Well, we're going to introduce next something called pseudocode.
我们将介绍一种叫做伪代码的东西。
How can I translate what I did verbally there, sort of intuitively, to actual code?
如何将我之前口述的内容，也就是直观的算法思路，转换成实际的编程代码？
Well, this won't be Scratch.
好吧，这不是 Scratch
This won't be C or Python just yet.
这还不是 C 语言或 Python 语言。
It's just going to be an English-like syntax.
这只是一种类似英语的语法。
And this is how many programmers would start solving a problem.
许多程序员就是这样开始解决问题的。
They don't start typing out code in C or Python or the like.
他们不会开始用 C、Python 或类似的语言输入代码。
They use English or whatever their human language is to jot down an outline for their ideas.
他们用英语或其他人类语言记下自己的想法大纲。
My first step, really, was picking up the phone book.
其实，我的第一步就是拿起电话簿。
My second step was opening to the middle of the phone book.
我的第二步是打开电话簿的中间部分。
My third step was somewhat different-- look at the page, because why?
我的第三步有些不同——看页面，因为为什么？
My fourth step was if person I'm looking for is on the page, I then do what?
我的第四步是，如果我要找的人出现在页面上，我应该怎么做？
It never happened in my example, but I call the person.
在我的例子中，这种情况从未发生过，但我们该给对方打电话。
So I'm done.
然后流程结束了。
Else if the person is earlier in the book alphabetically, as John Harvard was in the case of my H, then
否则，如果要查找的人在电话簿中的字母顺序靠前，
就像在我的例子中 John Harvard 的 “H” 一样，
I should search to the middle of the left of the phone book.
那么我应该搜索电话簿的左半部分的中间位置。
And then I should go back to step three.
然后我应该回到第三步，
Step 3 is look at the page, thereby repeating the same process again and again.
第三步是查看这一页，重复相同的过程。
Step 9, though, might be else if the person is later in the book, then let's go ahead and open to the middle of the right half of the book and then go back to line 3.
第九步，我们可以考虑另一种情况，即如果要查找的人在电话簿中的字母顺序靠后，
那么让我们打开电话簿的右半部分的中间位置，然后回到第三步。
Else there's a fourth scenario we should probably consider, lest my search process freeze or crash or give me one of those spinning beach balls with a bug.
另外，还有第四种情况需要考虑，
以防止我的搜索过程冻结、崩溃或出现错误，给我展示一个旋转的沙滩球。
*注：旋转沙滩球是 macOS 中的错误提示。
Yeah--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, what if John Harvard isn't in the phone book?
如果电话簿上没有 John Harvard 呢？
I'd prefer that my algorithm, my phone not just reboot or freeze.
我希望我的算法、我的手机不会重启或卡住。
I should handle that with some kind of catch all.
我们应该把所有问题一网打尽。
Else, so to speak, let's just quit the program.
Else，所以，我们应该退出程序。
So there's well-defined behavior for every possible scenario of the four.
这样对于这四种可能的情况，就有了明确定义的行为。
Now, let's call out a few of these salient terms.
现在，让我们指出其中一些关键术语。
It turns out, if I highlight in yellow here, there's a pattern to what I've been doing here.
我在这里用黄色标出所做的事情的模式。
These are all of my English verbs.
这些都是用英语表示的动作。
And in a moment, we're going to start calling those verbs "functions."
接下来，我们将把这些动作称为"函数"。
When you program or write code and you want the program or the computer to do something for you, some action or verb, we're going to refer to those actions or verbs
当你编程或写代码时，如果你想让程序或计算机为你执行一些操作或动作，
as these things called "functions," like those here.
我们将把这些操作或动作称为"函数"（function）。
By contrast, I've just highlighted, instead, my "if," my "else if," my "else if," and "else."
另一方面，我用黄色标出"if"、"else if"、"else if"和"else"。
This is going to represent what we're going to start calling a "conditional," a proverbial fork in the road where you can either go this way or that way, do this thing or this other thing.
这将代表称之为"条件"的东西，类似于在道路上的岔路口，
你可以选择这条路还是那条路，做这件事还是那件事。
And you're going to decide which of those things to do based on what I've now highlighted here, which are going to be called "Boolean expressions"--
你将根据我现在标出的内容来决定要做哪些事情，这些内容将被称为 "布尔表达式"。
Boole, referring to a mathematician, last name Boole.
布尔，指一位数学家，姓布尔。
A Boolean expression is just a question with a yes/no, a true/false, a 1 or a 0 answer, if you will.
布尔表达式只是一个问题，有 "是"/"否"、"真"/"假"、"1 "或 "0 "等答案。
And it governs whether you do this thing or this thing or this thing or that.
它决定着你是做这件事，还是做这件事，还是做这件事，还是做那件事。
The indentation, in this case, is important.
在这种情况下，缩进是很重要的。
The fact that I've indented line 5 implies, by convention in programming, that I should only do line 5 if the answer to line 4 is a yes or a true, and same for these other indented lines as well.
我对第5行进行缩进意味着按照编程的惯例，
只有当第4行的答案是是或真时，才执行第5行，其他缩进的行也是类似的。
And the last characteristic here is this here.
最后一个特点在这里。
Someone called this out earlier, in fact.
事实上，早些时候就有人指出了这一点。
*注：在讨论 emoji 如何表达不同肤色时，有学生提到了循环。
These lines, 8 and 11, are now highlighted and represent what?
现在突出显示这两行，即第 8 行和第 11 行，它们代表什么？
What might we call these in code if you've done-- yeah, so these are loops, some kind of cycles that result in my doing the same thing again and again,
是的，这些是循环，是我反复做同样事情的某种循环。
but there's a key detail with this algorithm in pseudocode.
但在伪代码中，这种算法有一个关键细节。
Even though it's telling me to go back to line 3, why is this algorithm eventually going to stop?
它都告诉我要回到第 3 行，但为什么这种算法最终会结束呢？
Why do I not constantly keep looking for John Harvard forever by nature of these loops telling me to keep going back to line 3?
你为什么不会因为这些让你不断地回到第3行的循环，
无穷无尽地寻找 John Harvard 呢？
Good.
Eventually, he'll be on the page or, to your point earlier, he won't be at all and we're out of pages, and so we just quit.
最终，他会出现在某一页上，或者就像之前提到的，
他根本不在电话簿上，我们已经翻遍了所有页面，这时我们就会退出。
And that's the key about going to the left half or the right half.
这就是在左半部分或右半部分查找的关键。
It doesn't matter if you do the same thing again and again.
循环做同样的事情并不重要，
You're not going to get stuck in a so-called infinite loop so long as you keep dividing the problem and shrinking it into something smaller, smaller, smaller.
只要你继续将问题分割并缩小到更小、更小的规模，你不会陷入所谓的无限循环。
Eventually, there's going to be no problem left to solve.
最终，所有问题都被解决。
So even if you don't think of yourself as a computer person, even if you've never written code
即使你不认为自己是一个懂计算机的人，即使你从未写过代码，
what you'll find in the coming days is that these ideas that we've just kind of harnessed from real life are at your fingertips already.
你将会发现，在接下来的课程里，这些来自现实生活的想法和灵感仍然伴你同行。
And a lot of the process of learning to code is just going to be some bumps in the road because you can't quite see the new syntax in a familiar way.
学习编程的过程可能会有一些小波折，因为你可能还不能完全理解新的语法。
But you'll find that the ideas, in fact, are going to be more familiar than you might otherwise think.
但你会发现，事实上，这些想法会比你想象的更加熟悉。
And so we'll see in a bit-- and we'll take a break in a moment to take a breather-- that you will see these same ideas in a moment in the context of Scratch,
所以我们待会儿会看到—— 我们马上会休息一下——
你会在Scratch的环境中看到这些相同的想法，
an actual programming language via which we'll drag and drop puzzle pieces to make actual code work.
Scratch 是一种实际的编程语言，我们可以通过拖放拼图来编写实际的代码。
We'll see some variants of these ideas, things called "arguments" and "return values" and "variables."
我们将看到一些这些想法的变体，比如"参数"、"返回值"和"变量"。
But we'll ultimately convert it into this somehow.
但最终，我们将把它转换成这样的代码。
Anyone want to wager what this program will do if fed to your Mac or PC or phone?
有人愿意打赌，如果将这个程序输入到你的Mac、PC或手机中，它会做什么吗？
Here's just a massive pattern of zeros and ones.
这里只是一大堆的0和1。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: It will indeed say, rather disappointingly, apparently, just, "Hello, world."
它确实会说，有点让人失望，只是 "Hello, world"。
And indeed, baked into all of these 0's and 1's are not just the H-E-L-L-O, but also the verbs, the action of printing something to the screen.
而且，这些 0 和 1 中不仅仅包含了 H-E-L-L-O，还包含了打印内容到屏幕的动作。
And there's other stuff too so that the program knows how to start and how to stop, a lot of stuff that we won't have to worry about, that whoever designed the computer or the language did.
还有其他的东西，程序才知道如何启动和停止，
有很多东西我们不必担心，这是计算机或编程语言设计者考虑的。
But at the end of the day, you're never going to be writing the 0's and 1's yourselves, though our ancestors, once upon a time, did in some form.
但归根结底，你将永远不会亲自编写这些 0 和 1 ，
尽管我们的祖先在很久以前的某个时候可能是以某种形式这样做的。
We'll be using a much higher-level language, like this in C, or better yet, in just a moment, like in Scratch, like this.
我们将使用更高级的语言，比如这个 C 语言，或者更好的是，
很快我们将使用像 Scratch 这样的语言，就像这样。
And indeed, this is why today we focus on and begin with Scratch, this graphical programming language
确实，这就是为什么我们今天专注于 Scratch，并以它为起点。
so we have a way of expressing ourselves with functions, conditionals, loops, and more
这是一种图形化编程语言，因此我们可以用函数、条件、循环等方式表达自己，
but in a way that doesn't have stupid parentheses and curly braces and all of these visual distractions in the way and will translate that thereafter to this lower-level language.
但不需要烦人的括号、花括号和其他视觉上的干扰，而之后会将其转换为 C 这种更低层级的语言。
But for now, that was a lot.
那现在呢，刚才的内容确实很多，
That was definitely a fire hose. Let's go ahead and take a 10-minute break. Feel free to get up or stay here.
知识就像从消防水龙带中一涌而出。让我们休息 10 分钟吧。
你可以站起来活动一下，或者留在这里休息。
And we'll resume in a bit with some actual code.
过一会儿我们会继续，开始一些真正的编程代码。
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[MUSIC - THE WEATHER GIRLS, "IT'S RAINING MEN"] [MUSIC PLAYING]
[THUNDER RUMBLING]
- (SINGING) Hi.
Hi.
We're your Weather Girls, and have we got news for you.
You better listen.
Get ready, all you lonely girls.
And leave those umbrellas at home.
All right.
Humidity is rising.
Hmm, rising.
Barometer's getting low.
How low, girl?
According to all sources-- what sources, now-- the street's the place to go.
We better hurry up.
'Cause tonight, for the first time, just about half-past 10:00-- half-past 10:00-- for the first time in history, it's going to start raining men-- start raining men!
It's raining men, hallelujah!
It's raining men, amen!
I'm going to go out.
I'm going to let myself get absolutely soaking wet!
It's raining men, hallelujah!
DAVID J. MALAN: [CHUCKLES] All right, so--
[END PLAYBACK]
[APPLAUSE]
So this then is Scratch, a graphical programming language from our friends down the road at MIT's Media Lab
这就是我们麻省理工学院媒体实验室的朋友们推出的图形编程语言 Scratch，
that indeed some of you might have used in grade school or the like, for playing and writing code and the like, but you maybe didn't necessarily think about how some of these primitives ultimately worked.
有些人可能在小学或类似场合使用过它，用于玩耍和编写代码等，
但你可能并没有深入考虑这些基本概念是如何工作的。
And in fact, everything you've done-- if you've used Scratch before-- and everything you'll see today is going to apply to all of the weeks to come, as we explore these things called "functions"
实际上，你所做的一切—— 如果你以前使用过 Scratch——
以及你今天将要看到的内容，将适用于接下来的所有周，
and "loops" and "conditionals," "Boolean expressions" and more.
我们将探索这些被称为"函数"、"循环"、"条件语句"、"布尔表达式"等等的概念。
With Scratch, because it's so graphical and animated-congruent, can you create animations, like this one, interactive art, and software more generally.
通过 Scratch ，由于它是如此图形化和动画化，
你可以创建动画，比如这个示例，交互式艺术和其他类型的软件。
But you'll do so by dragging and dropping puzzle pieces that only lock together if it makes logical sense to do so.
但是，你将通过拖放拼图块来实现这些功能，
只有当逻辑上合理时，这些拼图块才会锁定在一起。
And you won't have to deal with, in this first week of class, is curly braces, parentheses, all of the weird symbology that you might recall seeing, when we just wanted to say, "Hello, world."
在这门课程的第一周，你不需要处理大括号、括号和其他奇怪的符号，
而我们只想说 "Hello, world."。
Now, this particular program, "Raining Men," was written by a former CS50 teaching fellow, Andrew Berry, who's actually now the general manager of the Cleveland
现在，这个特定的程序叫做 "Raining Men"，是由前 CS50 助教 Andrew Berry 编写的，
他现在是美国橄榄球队克利夫兰棕榈队的总经理。
Browns, the American football team.
And so these are just some of the programs that some of your predecessors in the class have created.
这些只是你们前辈在课程中创建的一些程序。
And you'll see, in the remainder of class here, a couple of others as well, and more in the course's first assignment, namely, problem set zero.
在接下来的课程中，你还会看到其他一些程序，以及课程的第一个作业，即问题集 0。
So how do we get there?
那么我们怎么开始呢？
Well, first a quick tour of what it is we're going to do.
首先，简单介绍一下我们要做的内容。
This, in Scratch, is perhaps the simplest program you can write.
在 Scratch 中，这也许是你能编写的最简单的程序。
And even if you've never seen Scratch or any programming language before, you can probably guess that this just says, on the screen somehow,
即使你以前从未见过Scratch或其他编程语言，你可能也能猜到这个程序只是在屏幕上显示
"Hello, World."
But what you don't have to do is type esoteric commands and weird syntax, those curly braces and parentheses I keep alluding to.
但你不需要输入奇怪的命令和复杂的语法，就像我之前一直提到的大括号和括号一样。
You just drag this yellow puzzle piece.
你只需要拖动这个黄色的拼图块，
You drag this purple puzzle piece.
再拖动这个紫色的拼图块，
Let them magnetically lock together, so to speak.
让它们像磁铁一样自动吸附在一起。
Click a button and boom.
点击一个按钮，就大功告成了。
With those same building blocks and several others, can you make exactly the sorts of things that Andrew brought to life as well.
有了这些积木和其他一些积木，你也可以像 Andrew 一样创造出各种各样的东西。
So here's what we're about to see.
下面我们就来看看。
At Scratch.MIT.edu is a cloud-based programming environment on MIT servers.
在 scratch.mit.edu 上有一个基于云的编程环境，托管在麻省理工学院的服务器上。
*注：需要科学的上网环境
You can also download it offline on your own Mac or PC.
您还可以在自己的 Mac 或 PC 上离线下载。
And it gives you an interface like this.
它会给你一个这样的界面。
On the left-hand side of the screen, you'll see a blocks palette.
在屏幕左侧，你会看到一个积木面板。
These puzzle pieces, a.k.a. blocks, come in different colors which rather categorize them.
这些拼图或者叫积木，有不同的颜色，这也是对它们的分类。
So pictured here, for instance, in blue, are a whole bunch of motion-related blocks.
例如，图中蓝色部分就是一大堆与运动相关的图块。
So Andrew used a whole bunch of those to have the singer and the men moving around on the screen in synchronicity with the song that was playing in the background.
于是，安德鲁用了一大堆这样的道具，让歌手和男主角在屏幕上随着背景音乐同步移动。
Meanwhile, in the middle of this interface is going to be the code area.
同时，这个界面的中间将是代码区。
And this is where Andrew, and soon you, will drag and drop some of those puzzle pieces and other colors as well
在这里，安德鲁和你将拖放各种颜色的拼图块，
and lock them together to get your character-- soon to be invented-- to do something on the screen.
并将它们锁定在一起，让你的角色在屏幕上做一些事情。
Indeed, at the bottom right here, will you see, ultimately, a sprite area, where a sprite is a technical term for like a character in a video game or a programming environment like this.
的确，在这里的右下方，你将会看到一个精灵区域，
精灵是指在视频游戏或像这样的编程环境中的角色。
By default, historically, Scratch is the cat, the mascot, if you will, for this programming environment.
在历史上，Scratch 默认的精灵是一只猫，也可以说是这个编程环境的吉祥物。
And so here we see, by default, just one sprite selected because on the top right of the screen is the stage for that sprite.
所以在这里我们看到，默认情况下只选择了一个精灵，在屏幕的右上角是该精灵的舞台。
And you can click and zoom in to make it full screen.
你可以点击并缩放它，使其全屏显示。
But this is the world in which Scratch-- by default, the cat-- will live.
但这是 Scratch 的世界——默认情况下是一只猫——将会生活的地方。
But you can change Scratch's costume so that it looks like a singer or the man falling from the sky or the like or anything else
但你可以改变 Scratch 的造型，让它看起来像一个歌手，或者从天上掉下来的人，或者其他任何东西，
either creating the art yourself or importing some of the things that come with it or elsewhere online.
你可以自己创作，也可以从网上或其他地方引进一些艺术品。
So what is this world that Scratch rather lives in?
那么，Scratch 所处的世界究竟是怎样的呢？
Well, generally speaking, we won't have to care too much about numbers because we'll be able to ask questions
一般来说，我们不需要太关心具体的坐标，因为我们可以问一些交互式的问题，
like interactive ones, like is Scratch the cat, or any character otherwise, touching the edge of the screen, touching something else?
比如 Scratch 猫或其他任何角色是否触碰到了屏幕边缘或其他东西。
But Scratch does exist in this two-dimensional coordinate-system world.
但是 Scratch 确实存在于这个二维坐标系统的世界中。
So when the cat or any character is dead center in the middle, that would be xy location 0,0, if you will.
所以当猫或任何角色位于中心位置时，它的x y坐标是 0,0 。
Meanwhile, over here is 240 pixels, or dots, all the way to the right.
同时，在这里是 240 像素，或者说点，一直到最右边。
So this would be 240,0, where y is 0 because it's right on that midline.
因此这里是 240,0 ，其中y是0，因为它正好在中线上，
So it's neither up or below.
既不在上方也不在下方。
Over here to the left, of course, would be -240 and 0.
在左边，当然就是 -240 和 0 。
Above the cat would be x equals 0, because it's right on that vertical midline, and 180.
猫上方的 x 坐标是0，因为它正好在竖直中线上，而 y 坐标是180。
And then down here, as you might guess, would be 0, negative 180.
然后在下方，你可能会猜到，就是 0，-180。
Generally speaking, we don't have to care about those precise pixel coordinates.
一般来说，我们不需要过于关注这些精确的像素坐标。
But it's helpful, ultimately, if you do want the cat to move up, down, left, or right.
但如果你希望猫能够向上、向下、向左或向右移动，
Having some sense of direction according to the x-axis and y-axis as well can help you express your ideas, ultimately.
了解一些关于 x 轴和 y 轴方向的知识，会帮助你更好地表达自己的想法。
So what might some of those ideas be?
那么，这些想法可能是什么呢？
Well, let's do this.
好吧，开整。
I'm going to go ahead and create, on Scratch.MIT.edu, just an empty screen like this one here.
我要在 scratch.mit.edu 上创建一个这样的空屏幕。
And so this is the exact same interface.
因此，这是完全相同的界面。
But now I'm in my browser, full screen, so that I can start writing some code.
但现在我在浏览器中，全屏显示，这样我就可以开始写代码了。
And let's get that cat to say something actually on the screen.
让那只猫在屏幕上说点什么吧。
Now, this takes a little bit of practice.
现在，这需要一点练习。
But honestly, just by scrolling through these puzzle pieces can you quickly get a sense of what's possible, not just categorically, but specifically.
但是，仅仅通过滚动这些拼图块，你就能迅速了解到可能发生的事情，
不仅是按类别划分的，还有具体的操作。
And I'll jump around because I've done this, of course, before.
我会到处跳转，因为当然我之前做过这个。
But I'm going to go to events, in yellow, first.
我首先会选择黄色的事件类别。
And I'm going to drag and drop this first block, called when Green Flag clicked.
然后我会拖拽这个第一个拼图块，叫做 "当点击绿旗时"。
And I've zoomed in there just to make it a little more legible.
我放大一下，让它更加清晰可读。
And notice that the shape of this Green Flag just so happens to mirror this Green Flag here at top, next to this red Stop Sign, of sorts.
注意，这个绿旗的形状恰好与屏幕顶部旁边的红色停止标志相对应。
And the Green Flag is going to mean go and the red Stop Sign is going to mean stop, to start or stop our program.
绿旗表示开始，红色停止标志表示停止，用于启动或停止我们的程序。
Next week, you're going to be writing a textual command at your keyboard to do the exact same idea.
下周，你将通过在键盘上输入文本命令来实现相同的功能。
But for now, it's a button.
但现在，它只是一个按钮。
So when Green Flag clicked, what do I want Scratch to do?
那么，当点击绿旗时，我想让 Scratch 做什么呢？
Well, how about we have Scratch just initially say something like, "Hello, world," which indeed, historically, is the first program that most any programmer might write.
那么，我们让 Scratch 一开始就说一些像 "Hello, world" 这样的话怎么样，
这实际上是大多数程序员可能会编写的第一个程序。
So anything related to what the cat looks like it's doing is actually going to be under looks, here in purple.
关于猫看起来在做什么的任何内容实际上都在这里的 "Looks"（外观）类别下，用紫色表示。
So I'm going to drag over Say "hello."
所以我要拖拽过来 "Say hello" 这个积木。
And you'll notice something curious and different about this purple block.
你会发现这个紫色块有些奇特和与众不同。
It says, of course, "Say" in purple.
当然，上面用紫色写着 "说"。
But then there's this white oval and some text that, by default, is "hello" because MIT just decided that, by default, the placeholder will be "hello."
然后，有一个白色椭圆和一些文本，而默认情况下，文本是 "hello"，
因为麻省理工学院决定将默认的占位符设为 "hello"。
But anytime you see this white oval, it's an opportunity to provide an input into the function called Say.
但无论何时你看到这个白色椭圆，这就是为 Say 函数提供的输入。
And so here I'm borrowing terminology from before.
所以这里我再提一下之前的术语。
Problem solving, again, is all about inputs producing outputs.
解决问题实际上是关于输入产生输出。
And in between there is some algorithm.
在这输入输出之间，是一些算法。
In a moment, we're going to start referring to algorithms quite frequently as "functions."
接下来，我们将经常将算法称为"函数"，
Why?
Because it's the implementation of some algorithm.
因为它是某种算法的实现。
So let me override the default with, "Hello, world."
让我用 "Hello, world" 来覆盖默认值。
I'll zoom out.
我要放大一下。
And now if I go to the top right of the screen and click the Green Flag, we'll see, hopefully, my very first program in code.
现在，如果我转到屏幕右上方，点击 "绿旗"，我们就能看到我的第一个程序代码了。
Now, it wasn't a huge lift, right?
现在，这可真是一个巨大的突破，是吧？
It only was a matter of dragging and dropping puzzle pieces.
拖放拼图块就可以了。
But what has now happened?
但现在发生了什么呢？
Well, it turns out that two things have happened.
结果有两件事发生了。
When I, the human, clicked on that Green Flag,
当我点击绿旗时，
I triggered, what we're going to start calling now, an "event."
我触发了，我们现在称之为 "事件" 的东西。
An event is generally something graphical or interactive that just happens in a computer program.
事件通常是计算机程序中发生的图形化或交互式的事情。
You and I trigger events on our phones all day long.
我们每天都在手机上触发事件。
Whenever you tap or drag or long press or pinch or any of those gestures in vogue nowadays on phones, you are triggering events.
无论是在手机上点击、拖动、长按、捏合手势，或者现在流行的其他手势，都会触发事件。
And people at Apple and Google and elsewhere have written code that listen for those events and do something when that event happens.
苹果、谷歌和其他地方的开发人员编写了代码来监听这些事件，并在事件发生时执行某些操作。
That's what I just did.
这就是我刚刚做的。
When Green Flag is clicked, I want something to happen, namely, I want this purple function, this verb, this action called
当点击绿旗时，我希望发生一些事情，即我希望这个紫色的函数，
Say, to do something.
称为 Say 的动作，做一些事情。
What do I want it to do?
我想让它做什么？
I want it to say what this input is.
我想让它说明这个输入是什么。
And I'm going to introduce another vocabulary term.
我还要介绍另一个词汇。
The white ovals here are, yes, inputs, very generically.
没错，这里的白色椭圆就是输入，非常通用。
But in a programmer's terminology, they're called "arguments," otherwise known as "parameters."
但在程序员的术语中，它们被称为参数，argument 或者 parameter。
And that just means an input to a function that modifies its behavior in some way.
它们是传递给函数的输入值，可以在某种程度上修改函数的行为。
When I click Stop, that's just another event.
当我点击 "Stop" 时，那只是另一个事件。
And that one is just built into Scratch.
这个事件是内置在 Scratch 中的。
Scratch knows that when you click the green Stop Sign, everything should just stop automatically.
Scratch 知道当你点击绿色的停止标志时，一切都应该自动停止。
I don't have to write code to support that feature.
我不需要编写代码来支持这个功能。
So that's all fine and good, "Hello, world."
所以 "Hello, world" 都挺好的。
But if I keep doing stop and start and stop and start, it's going to do the same thing again and again.
但是如果我一直按停止、开始、停止、开始，它会一遍又一遍地做同样的事情。
And it's really not that interesting, at the end of the day, maybe gratifying once, but it'd be nice if this were a little more interactive.
说实话，这样做可能一开始还挺有趣，但最终可能变得乏味。
也许一次还行，但如果能让它更加交互就更好了。
So it turns out that we can do that too.
原来，我们也可以这样做。
But we need a different mental model instead.
但我们需要一种不同的思维模式。
So in this case here, when we think about this function,
在这种情况下，当我们
Say, in this input, "Hello, world," this actually maps pretty cleanly to this model earlier, that I propose is problem solving, is computer science, if you will.
考虑这个 Say 函数，以及它的输入 "Hello, world" 时，实际上与之前提到的模型相当吻合。
这个模型可以称为问题解决，或者说计算机科学。
The input to the current problem is going to be in white here,
当前问题的输入是白色部分的"Hello, world"。
"Hello, world."
The algorithm is the "say" algorithm.
而算法则是 "say" 这个动作。
Now, I don't know how MIT got it to print out the little, pretty speech bubble on the screen.
现在，我不知道 MIT 是如何在屏幕上打印出那个漂亮的对话气泡的。
But they wrote those underlying low-level implementation details.
但他们编写了底层的低级实现细节。
And they gave me and you a purple function, called Say, that just does that for you.
然后他们为我和你提供了一个紫色的函数，叫做 "Say"，它会自动为你完成这个工作。
You and I don't have to reinvent that wheel.
你我不必重新发明轮子。
The output of Say is another technical term, now, called a "side effect."
"Say" 函数的输出是另一个技术术语，称为 "副作用"。
A side effect is usually something visual that happens, like as a side effect of you calling a function.
副作用通常是指一些可视化的现象，比如调用一个函数的副作用。
And so the side effect here is that the cat has this speech bubble magically appear, inside of which is "Hello, world."
因此，在这里，副作用是猫角色的对话气泡神奇地出现，其中写着 "Hello, world"。
So we have an input.
所以我们有一个输入。
We have an output.
还有一个输出。
We have an algorithm.
我们有一种算法。
But now we're talking about these ideas in the context of programming.
但现在我们是在编程的背景下讨论这些想法。
So now the input is an "argument."
因此，现在的输入是一个 "参数"。
The algorithm is a "function."
算法是一种 "函数"。
And the output, in this case, is a "side effect"-- terminology that you'll just hear more and more.
在这种情况下，输出是一种 "副作用"—— 你会听到越来越多这样的术语。
And it'll eventually sink in, but not to worry if the terminology doesn't come naturally early on.
最终我们会明白这一点，但不用担心，虽然这些术语没有很经常出现在我们的生活中。
So what more might I do with this?
那么，我还能用 Scratch 做些什么呢？
Let me go back to Scratch here and make this maybe perhaps more interactive and actually get the cat to say something a little more dynamically.
回到 Scratch，让它更具互动性，让猫咪更生动地说点什么。
So instead of "Hello, world," why don't we get him to say hello to me or to you or anyone else?
所以，与其说 "Hello, world"，不如让他对你我或其他人说 "你好"。
So let me do this.
那就让我来演示。
Let me go under, say-- let me get rid of this first.
让我到下面去，先把 Say 函数拿开。
And you'll notice this neat trick.
你还会发现一个小窍门。
As soon as you start dragging on a block, if it gets close to it, it kind of goes gray, and it can be magnetically snapped together.
当你开始拖动一个块，靠近另一个，它就会变成灰色，然后就会被磁力吸到一起。
You don't have to do it very precisely.
你不必做得非常精确。
Conversely, if I want to get rid of a puzzle piece,
反过来，如果我想去掉一块拼图，
I can just drag it anywhere on the left, let go, and that deletes it.
我可以把它拖到左边的任何位置，然后放手，这样就可以删除它了。
Or you can Right-click or Control-click and a little menu will let you delete it as well.
或者，你也可以右键单击或按住 Control 键单击，一个小菜单也可以删除它。
Well, let me do this instead.
好吧，让我来做一遍。
Under Sensing, which I know is there because I've done this before, are a whole bunch of things related to Sensing, whereby the cat can kind of feel out its world, in some sense.
在 "Sensing" 类别下，有许多与感知相关的功能，猫角色可以通过这些功能感知周围的世界。
It can do things like ask this question, "Am I touching the mouse pointer?"-- like the user's cursor.
它可以做一些事情，比如问这个问题："我是否触摸了鼠标指针？"—— 就像用户的光标一样
"Am I touching a specific color that you can override to be anything you want?"
"我是否触摸了特定颜色，你可以将其更改为任何你想要的颜色？"
"Is the distance to the mouse pointer some specific value?"
"到鼠标指针的距离是多少？"
But for now, I'm going to focus on this, this blue puzzle piece that asks a question, which itself is this white oval that I can apparently change, and then it's going to wait for a response.
但现在，我将关注这个蓝色的拼图块，它是一个用来问问题的拼图块，
它本身是一个白色的椭圆，我显然可以更改它的内容，然后它会等待回答。
But this puzzle piece is a little different.
但这块拼图有点不同。
It's a little special.
它有点特别。
It comes with a freebie.
它还附带赠品。
It comes with what we're going to call, technically, a "return value."
技术上，我们称之为 "返回值"。
So some functions don't just do something on the screen.
因此，有些功能并不只是在屏幕上做一些事情。
They hand you back, so to speak, a value that you can do anything that you want with.
可以说，他们返还给你一个值，你可以用这个值做任何你想做的事。
Nothing happens immediately unless you do something with that so-called return value.
除非你对所谓的返回值进行操作，否则什么都不会发生。
So let me go ahead and drag this thing over here, ask, "What's your name?"
让我把这东西拖过来，问 "你叫什么名字？"
And I'll use the default question.
就用它这个默认的。
That seems a reasonable place to start.
作为开始还挺不错的。
I'm not going to override that default. And now let me go ahead and zoom out.
我没有覆盖默认值，现在让我缩小点。
Let me go back to Looks.
让我回到 "外观"。
Let me go to Say.
让我们到 Say 函数。
And let me just form the English sentence I want.
让我来组一个想要的英语句子。
So let me zoom in here and type in "hello," maybe comma, space.
所以，让我放大这里，输入 "Hello"，也许是逗号、空格。
I could do "David," but that's obviously not right because I'm asking for a name, and then I'm like, in advance, hard-coding my name.
我可以用 "David"，但这显然不对，
因为我是在询问一个名字，然后我提前硬编码了我的名字。
*注：硬编码指程序不会因为输入的不同，发生不同的变化。把本应是变量的东西设置为常量。
That's not what I want.
这不是我想要的。
I just want, "hello," comma.
我只想说 "Hello"，逗号。
And now let me zoom out and grab one more Say block.
现在，让我把镜头拉远，再抓一个 Say 块。
Let me maybe Say here.
让我把 Say 放这里。
OK, I don't want to say, "Hello, hello."
好吧，我不想说 "Hello，Hello"
I don't want to just type in my own name because, again, then what's the point of asking the user for their name?
我不想直接输入自己的名字，不然问名字有什么意义呢？
But notice this.
但请注意这一点。
If I go back to the sensing block, this is where that oval that's blue, called Answer, is useful.
如果我回到感知类别，这就是那个蓝色的椭圆，叫做"Answer"，马上派上用场。
This will be the so-called "return value" of that function.
这就是该函数的"返回值"。
So I'm just going to go ahead and do this and drag and drop.
所以，我要接着做，拖过去。
Even though it's not the right size, it is the right shape.
虽然它的大小不对，但形状是正确的。
And so Scratch will be smart about it and grow to fill that puzzle piece for you.
所以 Scratch 会自动调整大小来填充这个拼图块。
Let me zoom out now.
现在让我缩小一下视图。
And now let me click the Green Flag.
点击绿旗。
You'll see that Scratch is indeed prompting me with a speech bubble,
你会看到Scratch确实用一个对话气泡提示我说：
"What's your name?"
"你叫什么名字？"
Notice the little text box below the cat is asking, what's your name?
注意猫角色下方的文本框正在询问："你叫什么名字？"
So I'm going to type in D-A-V-I-D and hit Enter.
所以我要输入D-A-V-I-D并按回车键。
Or I can click the blue check.
或者我可以点击蓝色的勾号。
Enter.
OK, it's a little weird.
好吧，这有点奇怪。
I wanted him to say, "hello," not just my name.
我想让他说 "你好"，而不仅仅是我的名字。
So let me Stop.
停停。
Let me start it again.
重新开始。
All right, hello, what's your name?
好吧，你好，你叫什么名字？
D-A-V-I-D. Enter.
Huh-- kind of rude.
啊... 有点没礼貌。
Why is there this bug?
为什么会出现这个bug？
Like, I wanted to say, "Hello, David," not just "David."
我想说 "你好，David"，而不只是 "David"。
And yet twice it has failed to do so.
然而，它两次都没有做到这一点。
Yeah--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, the computer's processing my directions, my actions, really quickly.
是的，电脑处理指令和行动真的特别快。
And so it actually is doing it.
因此，它实际上是这样做的，先显示"Hello, "，很快切换到"David"。
It's just, you and I, in the room, are just way too slow to notice that it said-- (QUICKLY) "Hello, David."
只是，我们反应太慢，没注意到它说——"Hello, David."
It just seems to have just said, "David."
它似乎只说了 "David"。
So all right, how can I fix this?
那么好吧，我该如何解决这个问题呢？
Well, here's where you start to poke around and think about how you might solve this.
好的，这时候你可以开始探索和思考如何解决问题。
Let me go back under Looks.
让我回到外观类别。
Maybe there's a smarter way to do this.
也许有一种更智能的方法来解决这个问题。
Maybe I could do--
也许我可以这样做——
OK, I could do this.
好的，我可以这样做。
How about instead of just Say "hello," there's apparently another puzzle piece where I can time it so I can maybe slow things down a little bit.
我要试试这样。我不仅要说 "hello"，还可以在两次说话之间加入一些时间间隔，以减慢速度。
So let me do this.
试试这样做。
Let me throw away all of this.
我要先删除掉之前的代码。
Let me drag a Say "hello" for 2 seconds.
然后我拖拽一个 "Say hello for 2 seconds"
Let me drag another Say "hello" for 2 seconds.
再拖拽另一个 "Say hello for 2 seconds"
Let me change the first one to, indeed, "hello" comma.
我要把第一个拼图块里的文本改为 "hello，"。
And then let me go back to Sensing.
然后我回到感知类别，
Let me grab that same answer because I threw it away a second ago, and I'll just change it.
再次拖拽那个返回值 answer，因为我之前把它删除了，
现在我只需要修改一下文本就可以了，
I don't even have to delete "hello."
我甚至不用删除 "hello"。
I can just overwrite it like this.
覆盖掉就可以。
So now I think we'll kind of pump the brakes and see things more slowly.
所以，现在我们踩下了刹车，可以慢点来。
Let me Stop.
先停下来。
Let me start.
重新开始。
D-A-V-I-D, Enter.
D-A-V-I-D，回车。
Hello, David.
OK, so it's better, like it seems to be working.
好吧，现在好多了，起作用了。
I think your hypothesis was right, just looks kind of stupid, right?
我们的设想没问题，只是看起来有点呆是吧？
Like, the fact that it's saying Hello--
就像它在说 "你好...
[PAUSE]
--David, like we can do better.
...David" ，我们可以做好点。
And like, literally every piece of software on your phone or Mac or PC is better than that.
而且，你手机、Mac 或 PC 上的每款软件都比它好。
It adds words together in the user interfaces you and I are familiar with.
它通过我们熟悉的用户界面将单词拼接在一起。
So let's go a little more fishing here.
所以，让我们在这里再多思考一会儿。
Let me throw away these.
扔掉这些先。
Let me go back to Looks and just get the simpler Say.
回到 "外观"，抓起 Say 函数。
I want this to say, "Hello" comma name, where name comes from that Answer return value.
我想让它说 "Hello, " name，其中 name 来自 Answer 的返回值。
So how can I do this?
那么，我该怎么做呢？
Well, let me go under Operations, which we haven't been before.
好的，打开 Operations（运算）类别，这是我们以前没有接触过的。
There's a lot of stuff in here.
这里有很多东西。
Some of it's mathematically related, adding, subtracting, and so forth.
有些与数学相关，例如加法、减法等等。
You can generate random numbers which might be useful.
你可以生成随机数，这可能会有用。
And if I keep scrolling down, there's this Join "apple" and "banana."
如果我继续向下滚动，会找到一个拼图块，叫做 Join "apple" and "banana"。
But that's just placeholder text.
但这只是占位符文本。
You can join one piece of text with another piece of text, by default "apple" and "banana."
你可以将一段文本与另一段文本连接起来，默认情况下是"apple"和"banana"。
But let's change it to "hello" and my name.
但让我们把它改成"hello"和我的名字。
So this, too, wrong size but right shape.
这也是正确的形状，但是大小不对。
So let me let it snap into place.
让我把它吸附到合适的位置。
Let me go ahead now and do "hello" comma.
现在让我继续输入 "hello，"。
And now I think I just want to go grab that Answer return value.
然后我想要去获取那个返回值 answer 。
Let me drag the same oval as before, clobber-- that is, overwrite-- banana.
让我拖拽之前相同的椭圆，覆盖掉 "banana"。
So now I'm kind of composing functions.
所以现在我正在组合函数。
The output of one function, Join, is going to be the input of another function, Say.
一个函数 Join 的输出将成为另一个函数 Say 的输入。
So let's see what happens now that they're kind of stacked on top of each other or nested, so to speak.
现在让我们看看它们彼此堆叠或者说嵌套在一起之后会发生什么。
Click the Green Flag, D-A-V-I-D. Enter.
点击绿旗，D-A-V-I-D。回车。
"Hello, David."
All right, that was pretty fast.
好吧，这也太快了。
Let's just do it once more.
让我们再来一次。
Stop.
Start.
Here we go, D-A-V-I-D. Enter.
点击绿旗，D-A-V-I-D。回车。
OK.
All right, it's not the most exciting program in the world.
好的，这可能不是世界上最激动人心的程序。
But it's more correct.
但它更加正确，
It's better designed just because that's what you would kind of expect the software to do
它设计得更好，因为这是你期望软件能做的事情，
and not be some kind of lame user interface that's just inserting random delays to just make it kind of work, like that's a workaround, a hack, if you will.
而不是一些仅仅通过插入随机延迟来使它“大概工作”的可怜用户界面，
这样只是一种变通，一种权宜之计，你可以这样说。
But there's some cool things you can do with Scratch.
不过，用 Scratch 也能做一些很酷的事情。
And we won't really go down the rabbit hole of all of the fun and family-friendly features that it has.
我们不会深入探讨所有有趣的功能。
But there is one that's kind of cool here.
但有一个功能还是挺酷的。
Let me go into the Extensions button at the bottom left of my screen.
让我点击屏幕左下角的 "Extensions" 按钮。
And this one's kind of cool.
这个还挺酷的。
Let me go to Text to Speech.
我选择"Text to Speech"。
And you'll notice that this one requires internet because it's cloud based.
你会注意到这个功能需要互联网，因为它是基于云的。
But this just gave me some new puzzle pieces in a new category,
但是这给我提供了一些新的拼图块，属于一个新的类别，
Text to Speech.
名为 "文字转语音"。
And these green ones do exactly what they say.
这些绿色的拼图块做的就是它们名字里面写的。
So let me do this.
那就让我来吧。
Let me zoom out again.
再次缩小视图。
Let me keep the Join block.
我保留Join拼图块，
And I'm just going to temporarily toss it over here.
但暂时把它放在这里。
It's not going to delete itself because I didn't drag it over to the other side.
它不会自己删除，因为我没有把它拖到另一边。
But I'm going to get rid of the Say block, in purple.
但是我要删除紫色的 Say 拼图块。
I'm going to do the Speak block here, in green, and let it snap into place.
我在这里用绿色的 Speak 拼图块替换它，并让它吸附到合适的位置。
And then I'm going to drag and drop this onto the input to Speak.
然后我要将这个返回值 Answer 拼图块拖放到 Speak 的输入上。
And now, perhaps a little more adorably, let's try this.
现在，也许会更加可爱一些，我们来试一下。
Green Flag, what's your name?
点击绿旗，出现 "你叫什么名字？"
D-A-V-I-D. Enter.
D-A-V-I-D，回车。
And--
COMPUTER: Hello, David.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
大卫-J-马兰：好的。
[LAUGHTER]
It's a little robotic.
有点像机器人。
But at least now it has synthesized speech.
但至少现在有了合成语音。
And I've kind of got my own, like, Siri or Google Assistant or Alexa thing going on here now, where it's now recognized whatever text it is, and it's played it.
现在我们有了 Siri 或 Google Assistant 或 Alexa，可以识别文字并播放出来。
Well, let's make this an actual cat that doesn't talk in that weird human voice.
好吧，让我们把它变成一只真正的猫，它不会用那种奇怪的人类声音说话。
Let me go ahead and get rid of most of this stuff.
让我删除大部分东西。
And let's get the cat to actually meow, like a cat tends to.
让这只猫像猫一样喵喵叫吧。
And let me go under the Sounds block.
让我进入声音类别。
Now MIT gives you a few sounds for free because it's designed around a cat, by default. And I'm going to go ahead and grab this one, Play Sound Meow until done.
MIT 为你提供了一些免费的声音，因为它默认设计是围绕一只猫的。
我要选择这个，播放猫叫声直到结束。
And now-- and we heard a teaser for this earlier in the crowd--
现在—— 刚才就听到有人在下面跟着喵了。
[MEOW]
It's a little piercing, admittedly.
这听起来可能有点刺耳。
Maybe we can lower the volume a little bit there.
或许我们可以把音量降低一点。
But notice, if I want the cat to meow a second time, I'll just click it again.
但请注意，如果我想让猫再喵喵叫一次，我就再点击一次。
[MEOW]
OK, and over there, too, I hear--
好的，大家能听见——
[MEOW]
OK.
All right, so it's kind of cute now, right?
是吧，现在有点可爱了吧？
So it's just meow--
所以，它只是喵，
OK, yes, echo, echo.
对对，有回声。
So it's meowing now every time I hit the Green Flag.
所以现在每次我点绿旗的时候，它都会喵喵叫。
Now, that's great, but even a kid is probably going to--
现在很不错， 不过可能会想，
[MEOW]
--like would prefer that it--
希望它可以，
[MEOW]
--just meow, perhaps, like again and again, without having to keep--
就 "喵喵 "地叫，一次又一次，而不必每次都要，
[MEOW]
--hitting the button.
按下按钮。
So how might we do this?
那么，我们该如何做呢？
All right, well, if I want it to meow multiple times, why don't I just, like, grab it another time and another time?
好的，如果我想让它叫多次，为什么我不直接再拖拽一次、再拖拽一次呢？
Alternatively, you can Right-click or Control-click a puzzle piece and just duplicate it from a little menu that drops down.
或者，你可以右键点击或者按住Control键点击拼图块，
然后从弹出的菜单中选择"Duplicate"，复制。
So here we go, three meows.
好了，现在是三声喵。
[MEOWING]
All right, that's not really a happy cat.
好吧，听起来小猫不太开心。
It sounds maybe hungry.
它是不是有点饿了。
So can we slow that down?
所以我们能不能让它喵得慢一点呢？
Well, maybe.
嗯，也许可以。
In fact, if I poke around, let me go under Control.
如果我四处翻找，进入控制类别。
It looks like there's a Wait block.
看起来有一个等待拼图块。
Wait 1 Second, by default. And notice, Scratch will be pretty accommodating.
默认情况下等待 1 秒。请注意，Scratch 会很通情达理。
If you just hover in between blocks, it will grow to fill that too.
如果你将鼠标悬停在两个拼图块之间，它也会自动填进去。
So I could change it to 1 or 2 or anything, seconds.
所以我可以将等待时间更改为 1 秒、2 秒或其他任何时间。
I'll just leave it at the default for now, 1.
我暂时将其保留默认值 1 秒。
And now I'll go ahead and do this.
现在，我要跑一下看看效果。
[MEOWING]
OK, so cuter and less hungry and just more friendly.
好了，更可爱、更不饿、更友好了。
But this isn't the best design.
但这并不是最好的设计。
It is correct.
它当然正确。
And let's use that as a term of art.
让我们把它作为一个艺术术语来看待。
Correct means the code does what you want it to do.
正确的意思是代码能按照你的意愿执行。
I want the cat to meow three times slowly.
我想让猫慢慢地喵叫三声，
And it did.
它确实做到了。
So I'd wager this is correct.
所以我可以说这是正确的。
But it's not the best design.
但这并不是最佳设计。
And this is where things get more subjective, right?
这里就涉及到更主观的因素，对吧？
Like, you could write accurate sentences in an essay for an English class, but otherwise, it's just completely a mess.
就像你可以在英语课的论文中写出准确的句子，但总体来说它可能是一团糟。
Like, your arguments here and there, and you don't say anything wrong, but you don't say it well.
你的论据到处都是，虽然没有错误，但表达得不好。
In the context of code, we can do better than this.
在编程中，我们可以做得更好。
And Copy/Paste or repeating yourself again and again tends to be bad practice.
而复制/粘贴或者一遍又一遍重复自己往往是不好的做法。
Why?
Suppose that you want to change the Wait to 2 seconds instead of 1.
假设你想将等待时间从 1 秒改为 2 秒。
It's admittedly not a big deal.
这确实不是什么很难的问题。
Fine, I click there, I change it to 2.
好吧，我点击那里，将它改成 2 秒。
I click there, I change it to 2.
我点击那里，将其改为 2 秒。
But what if you meow 5 times, 10 times?
但如果有 5 次、10 次猫叫呢？
Now I have to change the Wait, like, in 5, 10 different places.
现在我必须在 5 个、10 个不同的地方改变等待时间。
Like, that's just stupid.
这实在很愚蠢。
It's taking unnecessary human time, and you're going to screw up eventually, especially if your program is getting longer.
这浪费了不必要的时间，而且你最终会出错，特别是当你的程序变得更长时。
You're going to miss one of the inputs.
你会漏改掉其中一个，
You're going to leave the number wrong.
或者将数字填错。
And that's a bug.
就会出现 bug，正确性也没了。
So just based on what you've seen already or if you've program before, which a few of you have, what's the term of art here that will solve this?
所以基于你已经见过的或者你以前的编程经验，你知道应该用什么术语来解决这个问题吗？
How can we design this better?
如何才能设计得更好？
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: I heard it here.
我听到啦。
Yeah, so a loop-- a loop, some kind of cycle that says, do that again.
是的，所以用循环—— 一个循环，也就是说，再来一次。
Do that again-- not infinitely many times, necessarily, but some finite number.
再做一次—— 不会是无限次，一定是有限次。
Well, you can perhaps see a spoiler on the screen.
好吧，你也许在屏幕上看到剧透了。
Under the same orange Control category is a Repeat block.
就在橙色控制类别下有一个 Repeat 拼图。
And by default, it's proposing 10.
默认情况下，它设置为 10。
But we can change that.
但我们可以改一改。
So let me do this.
来试试吧。
I'm going to throw away most of this Copy/Paste as redundant.
我打算把这些复制/粘贴的大部分内容当作多余的东西扔掉。
I'm going to detach this temporarily just to make room for something else.
把这个暂时拆开，腾出地方放点别的。
And I'm going to drag a Repeat block over here and let that snap into place.
我要把一个 Repeat 块拖到这里，让它就位。
And I'm going to change it for now, just to be 3, for consistency.
和刚才保持统一，我暂时把它改成 3。
And this is the correct shape even though it's too small, but Scratch will accommodate that for us.
形状正确，尽管有点小，但 Scratch 会自动调整。
And now-- same output but arguably better designed.
而现在—— 尽管输出一致，不过可以说设计得更好。
Why?
Because if I want to change the number of meows, I change it in one place, no Copy/Paste messiness.
因为如果我想更改喵星人的数量，
只需在一个地方进行更改即可，不会出现复制/粘贴的混乱情况。
If I want to change the waiting, one place.
如果我想改变等待时间，也只改一个地方。
I don't have to change it in multiple places and not screw up.
我不用在多个地方进行更改，更不会搞砸。
So let me hit the Green Flag.
所以，让我点一下绿旗吧。
[MEOWING]
All right, so-- nice.
嗯，很棒。
Now, it would have been nice if MIT had just given us a meow block that just automates all of this for us.
现在，如果麻省理工学院能给我们一个喵的拼图块，
让我们自动完成所有这些工作，那该多好啊。
Let me wager, they gave us the low-level implementation details.
可以确定的是，他们帮我们实现了低层次的实施细节。
They gave us the Play Sound Meow.
他们给了我们 Play Sound Meow 函数。
But I had to implement a decent number of blocks just to get a cat to meow again and again.
但是，为了让一只猫一次又一次地 "喵喵喵" 叫，我还不得不组合很多拼图。
I feel like we should have gotten that for free from MIT.
我觉得 MIT 该做出来让我们白嫖。
Well, they don't have to be the only ones that invent blocks for us to use.
其实，并不是只有他们发明的函数块才能让我们使用。
You can write your own functions, your own verbs or actions.
你可以自己写函数、动词或动作。
So how can we do this?
那么，我们如何才能做到这一点呢？
Let's make our own puzzle piece, called Meow, that uses this code but creates it in such a way that it's reusable elsewhere.
让我们自己制作一个名为 Meow 的拼图块，
它使用了刚才的代码，但这样创建使它可以在其他地方重复使用。
So let me do this.
来吧。
Under my blocks in pink here, I'm going to go ahead and click, literally, Make a Block.
在粉红色的区块下，我要点击"制作区块"。
Now, here's an interface by which I can give the block a name.
现在，这里有一个接口，我可以通过它给程序块命名。
M-E-O-W will be the name of this block.
M-E-O-W 将是这个块的名称。
And I'm just going to go ahead and quickly click OK.
我要点下"确定"。
That just gives me a very generic, pink puzzle piece that starts with the word Define because scratch is asking me to define, that is, implement or create, this new puzzle piece for me.
那会给我一个非常通用的粉色拼图块，上面写着 "Define"，
因为 Scratch 要求我定义，也就是实现或创建，这个新的拼图块。
Well, what does it mean to Meow?
那么，这对 Meow块 意味着什么呢？
I'm going to claim that it means to do these two steps, to play the sound meow and then just wait for 1 second.
我要说这表示要执行这两个步骤，先播放声音 "meow"，然后等待 1 秒。
But what's powerful about this idea is look at this up top.
但这个想法的强大之处在于，看看上面这个。
Now that I've made a block, it exists in Scratch.
我创建了一个新的拼图块，它现在存在于 Scratch 中。
MIT didn't need to create this for me.
MIT 不需要为我创建这个拼图块。
I created it for myself and even you, if we end up sharing code.
我为自己创建了它，甚至为你创建了它，如果我们最终分享代码的话。
So I can now drag Meow up in here.
所以我现在可以将 Meow 拖到这里。
And what's nice about Meow is that itself is, yes, a function, but it's also an abstraction.
Meow 块的好处是它本身是一个函数，或者说一个抽象概念。
Like, never again do I or even you need to worry or care about what it means to meow or implement it.
以后我们再也不需要关心 Meow 的具体含义或者实现方式。
I can sort of drag it out of the way.
我可以将它拖到一边，
I didn't delete it-- drag it out of the way.
我没有删除它，只是将它拖到一边。
Out of sight, out of mind.
眼不见，心不烦。
Why?
Because my code is now even better designed, in some sense, because it's more readable.
这样我的代码设计得更棒了，易读性更好了。
What is it doing?
它做了什么？
When the Green Flag is clicked, repeat 3 times Meow.
只要点击绿旗，就重复 3 次 "Meow"。
It just says what it means.
这个函数名就是它干的事情。
And so it's a lot easier to read it, and it's a lot easier to think about it, especially if you're using Meow in other projects too.
这样阅读起来就容易多了，思考起来也容易多了，
尤其是当你在其他项目中也使用 Meow 函数的时候。
Now, let me go ahead and click Play.
现在，我们点点播放。
[MEOW]
Same thing.
是一样的。
[MEOW]
So it's not really fundamentally any different.
因此，从根本上说并没有什么不同。
[MEOW]
But I can make this custom puzzle piece, this own function of mine, Meow, even more powerful.
因为函数 Meow 是亲自写的，所以我们可以定制、修改，让它更加有用。
Let me kind of rewind a bit and go to my Meow puzzle piece.
让我来倒带一下，看看 Meow 函数。
And I am going to Control-click or Right-click on my pink puzzle piece.
我来按住 Control 键或右键单击我的粉色拼图。
And I'm going to edit it.
就可以编辑它。
So I kind of regret making Meow so simple.
所以我有点后悔把 Meow 设计得这么简单。
Wouldn't it be nice if Meow took an input, a.k.a. an argument, that tells Meow how many times to meow.
如果 Meow 能接受一个输入，也就是一个参数，
告诉 Meow 要喵叫多少次，那该有多好。
Then I can get rid of that loop and just tell
那个循环就能丢掉了，只需要
Meow how many meows I actually want.
告诉 Meow 我实际上想要多少声猫叫。
So I'm going to click on another button here called, literally, Add an Input.
因此，我要点击这里的另一个按钮，字面意思是 "添加输入"。
And it's going to have placeholder here.
这里会有一个占位符。
So I'm just going to put a placeholder there.
所以我先在这里放一个占位符。
I keep using "n" for number, which is a go to in computer scientist terms.
我一直用 "n "表示数字，我们计算机科学家都是这么约定俗成的。
And I'm going to add some descriptive text just so that it's a little more self-explanatory.
我还要添加点描述性文字，让它更加一目了然。
I'm just going to say Meow n Times.
我们想要的是让它喵 n 次。
But there's only one oval.
其实只有这个椭圆形里的 n 是参数。
Times is just going to be explanatory text.
times 只是解释性文字。
And now notice what has happened.
现在注意看这里发生什么。
Now my puzzle piece takes an input, a.k.a. an argument, that will tell that function to meow some number of times.
现在，这块拼图需要一个输入，也就是一个参数，这个参数会告诉函数喵喵叫多少次。
But it's not just going to work magically.
但这没法神奇地自动生效。
I need to implement that lower level detail.
我们需要实现较低级别的细节。
So let me zoom out.
让我把镜头拉远。
I have to remind myself what this function was.
因为我现在要修改这个函数内容了，要知道这个函数内部是什么。
So I'm going to drag it higher up just so they're on the screen at the same time.
所以我要把它拖到上面一点，让它们同时在屏幕上。
I'm going to go ahead now and temporarily move this over here.
我现在要把它暂时移到这儿。
I'm going to temporarily detach this over here.
再把这个暂时拆开。
Why?
Because what I thing I want to do is move my loop into the function itself, move the Play and the Wait into the loop.
因为我想做的是将循环移到函数体里面，再把播放和等待移到循环里面。
But I don't want a hardcode 3.
并且不想要硬编码 3 。
Notice that n here is its own oval I can drag a copy of n and just let it go there.
注意，n 这个参数在椭圆形里面，我可以拖动 n 产生一个副本，让它去到需要的地方。
So now I have a new version of Meow that takes an argument, n, that tells Meow how many times to meow.
现在，我有了一个新版本的 Meow，它接受一个参数 n，这个参数告诉 Meow 要喵喵叫多少次。
And now let me, again, drag this out of sight, out of mind, because who cares how I implemented it?
现在，让我再一次把这个函数的细节抛到脑后，因为谁会在意我是如何实现的呢？
Once it's implemented, it's sort of done.
只要咱实现了这个函数，就等于完成了（可以无限制到处使用）。
Now my program is even better designed, in some sense.
从某种意义上说，现在我的程序设计得更好了。
Why?
Because now it really just says what it means.
因为现在，它真的是所见即所得了。
There's no loop.
没有循环。
There's no repeat, no implementation details.
没有重复，没有实施细节。
When Green Flag Clicked, Meow 3 Times.
点击绿旗时，喵喵叫 3 次。
And so functions indeed let you implement algorithms, like they're just code that do something for you.
所以说，函数的确可以帮助我们实现算法，
它们说到底也只是一些组织好的、能执行任务的代码。
But they're also themselves abstractions.
要知道函数本身也是抽象的。
Why?
Because once a function exists, it has a name.
因为每创建一个函数，我们都会赋予它名字。
And you can think about it in that term.
你可以从名字就知道这个函数的用途。
And you can use it by its name.
你还可以根据它的名字来调用它。
You don't have to care or remember how the function itself was built, whether it's by you or even MIT.
你不必关心记住函数本身是如何实现的，无论它是来自 MIT 还是你亲手打造的。
So again, here I'll click the Green Flag.
再来一次，我要点一下绿旗。
It's the same thing.
都是一样的。
[MEOWING]
So still correct, but better and better designed.
所以还是正确的，但设计得更好、更完美。
And so any time, here and out, with Scratch, or soon C, and eventually Python
因此，无论何时何地，当你用 Scratch，或者很快就用到的 C，或者最终我们使用的 Python，
when you find yourself doing anything resembling Copy/Paste or again and again grabbing the same code, probably an opportunity to say, wait a minute.
当你发现自己在做任何类似于复制/粘贴的事情，
或者一次又一次地抓取相同的代码时，可能这就是一个时机说，停停。
Let me refactor this, so to speak, that is, rip out the code that seems to be repeated again and again and put it in its own function so you can give it a descriptive name and use and reuse it.
我们来重构一下吧！把那些看起来重复的代码删掉，把它放在自己的函数里面，
这样你就可以给它一个描述性的名字，在任何地方重用它。
Any questions just yet on now saying or these loops or these functions that we're using?
到现在为止说的这些循环或函数，大家还有什么问题想问吗？
Yeah--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: How did I make it so it meows three times?
我是怎么让它喵喵叫三声的？
So I originally only had a puzzle piece called Meow.
所以，我最初只有一块拼图，叫做 Meow。
And I decided to improve it.
我决定改进它。
So I held down Control and I Right-clicked or Control-clicked on the pink puzzle piece at top left.
于是，我用鼠标右键或 Ctrl 加左键，点击左上角的粉红色拼图。
And I clicked Edit.
然后我点击了 "编辑"。
And that brought back the original interface that lets me add some arguments to the puzzle piece itself.
这让我又回到了开始的界面，可以为新拼图添加一些参数。
And I clicked Add an Input on the left here.
然后我点击左侧的 "添加输入"。
And then I clicked on Add a Label over here.
然后点击这里的添加标签。
So that just lets you customize it even further.
这样就可以进一步定制它了。
All right, so we've done this.
好吧，我们已经完成了。
Let's add one of those other primitives too to do something optionally.
让我们再添加一个基础函数，来做点别的事情。
So how about we make the cat meow only if it's being petted by a human, as by moving the mouse to hover over the cat, like a human would pet a cat?
比如，猫咪只在人类抚摸时才叫，
那我们移动鼠标悬停在猫咪上方时让它喵喵叫，怎么样？
Well, let me go ahead and throw away the meowing for now.
好吧，让我先把 Meow 扔掉吧。
And let me simplify it by just using a sound.
猫叫的这个过程就用一声喵来简化。
I'm going to go ahead and do this.
我要这样...
I'm going to go ahead and have a Control block that says If, because I want to implement the idea of if the cursor is touching the cat, then play sound meow.
我还得用 if 条件语句，因为想实现 "如果光标碰到猫，就播放喵喵声" 的想法。
Or I could use my same pink puzzle piece.
或者，我也可以用刚才自己那块粉色拼图。
But I'm going to throw that away and focus only now on the sounds.
但我现在要抛开这些，只关注声音。
And I'm going to do this.
我要这么做
If touching mouse pointer-- so I need to sense something about the world.
如果触摸鼠标指针—— 这应该在 Sensing 感知模块下面。
And we saw this earlier-- so If Touching Mouse Pointer.
我们在前面已经看到过了，所以组合 "if" 和 "触摸鼠标指针"。
So notice this shape here, way too big.
注意这个形状，有点大。
But it is the right shape.
但它的形状是合适的。
So if I hover just right, it'll snap into place.
因此，如果我放的位置恰到好处，它会适配进去。
And this now, in blue, is my Boolean expression, a yes/no question, true false.
现在这个蓝色块是一个布尔表达式，也就是一个是/否、真/假的问题。
"If" is a conditional.
"if" 是一个条件。
And what do I want to do?
我想做什么来着？
Well, if the cat is touching the mouse pointer,
嗯，如果鼠标指针碰到猫的话，
I want to go ahead and play sound meow until done.
我想播放声音喵到完成。
So let's do this.
那就这么办吧。
I'm going to hit Green Flag, click.
我要点一下绿旗。
Now nothing's happened yet because it's a conditional, right?
现在什么都还没发生，因为这是一个条件判断，是吧？
It's only supposed to do something if I'm touching the cat.
只有在我摸猫的时候，它才会有所反应。
Let me move the cursor over to the cat.
让我把光标移到猫身上。
And-- wait for it.
等一等，
Hmm-- another bug.
嗯，出 bug 了。
Why is the cat not meowing even though I very explicitly said, If Touching Mouse Pointer, Meow?
为什么我明明设置了 "如果触摸鼠标指针，就喵喵叫" ，猫却不喵喵叫呢？
Yeah, in the middle--
中间这位请讲。
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, this is-- again, my computer's just so darn fast, like yours.
对的，我们的电脑都快得要命。
I click the Green Flag, it asks the question, am I touching the mouse pointer?
我点击绿旗的时候，它会问，这个时候的鼠标指针是否和猫有接触？
Well, no, because my cursor was up there, not touching the cat.
嗯，没有，因为我的光标在绿旗的位置，没碰到猫。
It's too late.
这太迟了！
The cat's out of the bag.
猫已经出来了，程序结束了。
And so we have to instead solve this by some other means.
因此，我们必须用其他方法来解决这个问题。
How can we fix this?
怎么解决这个问题？
How do we fix that sort of race?
我们该怎么解决这种竞速比赛？
Yeah--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, so why don't we just keep asking the question until I eventually am or am not actually petting the cat?
是啊，那我们为什么不一直问这个问题，直到我最终真的触摸到猫猫呢？
So let me detach this temporarily.
所以，我们暂时放下这个问题。
Let me go under Control.
来到 Control 模块下。
Let me go under-- instead of repeat some finite number of times, let's just do it forever.
到这个类别下看看—— 与其重复个几次，不如让它一直检测是否在摸猫猫。
So sometimes loops that do work forever are a good thing.
所以有时候，一直循环也是件好事。
The clock on your phone, that's in a loop forever because you want it to always tell time and not stop at the end of the day.
你手机上的时钟就是永远在循环，因为你希望它永远显示正确时间，而不是在一天结束时停止。
So sometimes you do want code to loop forever, as in this case.
因此，有时你确实希望代码永远循环下去，就像这个例子一样。
So let me go ahead and drag and drop it there.
我来把它拖到这儿。
Let me, again, click the Green Flag.
让我再点下绿旗。
Nothing's happening yet.
什么都没发生。
But notice, the program is still running.
但请注意，程序仍在运行。
And so if I move my cursor, move my cursor, move my cursor, and--
因此，如果我移动光标，移动光标，移动光标，然后——
[MEOWING]
OK, so maybe we could add some Waiting.
好吧，也许我们可以增加一些停顿。
But the cat does not want to be pet, in this case.
现在这种情况，猫听上去并不想被摸摸（因为没有停顿，在循环叫）。
But it's indeed conditional.
但这确实是个条件判断。
So there we have an incarnation in Scratch of doing something conditionally.
因此，我们在 Scratch 中看到了 "在条件下做某事"。
Now, we can make this really cool, really fast, if you will.
现在，我们可以让它变得超级酷。
Let me stop this version.
我先停止现在这个永久循环。
Let me go ahead and do this.
接着是这样。
Let me go ahead and throw all of this away.
把这些都扔掉吧。
Let me go into my little Extensions bucket over here.
进入这个扩展插件集。
And let me do Video Sensing, since most laptops or phones these days have cameras.
我们想要视频感应，因为现在大多数笔记本电脑或手机都有摄像头。
And there, indeed, I am, with Sanders behind me.
我确实出现在了屏幕里面。
And let me do this.
接着来吧。
When Video Motion-- and let me get out of the way.
当视频动态... 我先离开摄像头。
When Video Motion is Greater Than some value.
当视频动态大于某个值时。
So 10 is the default. This is just a number that measures how much motion there is or isn't.
10 是默认值，这只是一个衡量动作幅度大小的数字。
So small number is like no motion.
所以，数字小就是说没怎么动。
Big number is lots of motion.
数字大就是大幅度的动作。
So I'm going to choose 50, somewhat arbitrarily here-- so 50.
所以我选择 50，有点随意，就 50 吧。
This is not normal to program off to the side.
站在电脑一旁编程，多少有点不正常。
But I'm now going to say this.
我现在要说的是，
When Video Motion is 50, go ahead and Play Sound Meow like this.
当 "Video Motion" 为 50 时，像这样播放一声喵。
So the cat is still in that world.
所以，这只猫还在那个世界里。
I'm going to stop the program and rerun it.
我要停止程序再重新运行。
So here we go, Green Flag.
我们开始吧，点绿旗。
And now here comes-- all right, this is a little creepy, the way I'm petting the cat, but-- and-- [SIGH]
现在要来了—— 好吧，这有点吓人，这种抚摸猫的方式，但是...
[MEOWING]
OK.
[LAUGHTER]
There we go.
好了。
OK, so 50 was too big of a number.
好吧，50 这个数字太大了。
I have to pet the cat faster.
我得特别快地摸猫咪。
[MEOWING]
Whereas this, if--
那这样，如果慢点呢？
I don't know--
我不知道。
[LAUGHTER]
Yeah, so--
[MEOW]
OK, so you can make things even more interactive in this way by just assembling different puzzle pieces.
好了，只要把不同的拼图拼在一起，就能让很多东西参与互动。
And honestly, there are so many different puzzle pieces in here.
其实吧，这里有很多不同的拼图。
We're not going to even scratch the surface of a lot of them.
我们只是浅尝辄止，不会对其中的很多内容细细研究。
But they generally just do what they say.
但他们一般都是所见（函数名）即所得（函数效果）。
And indeed, when you see on the screen here this pallet of puzzle pieces, really a lot of programming, especially early on, when learning a language, is just trying different things and try and fail.
实际上，当你在屏幕上看到这些个拼图块，处于学习一门语言的早期阶段时，
编程就是尝试不同的方法，不断试错和改进。
And if it doesn't work quite right, look for an alternative solution there too, as even I just had to do a moment ago.
如果效果不如预期，也可以寻找其他解决方案，就像我刚才不得不做的那样。
Well, let's go ahead and use, actually, how about another example of something a predecessor of yours made?
好吧，让我们继续，用你们前辈做的另一个例子怎么样？
Let me go ahead and grab a program I opened in advance here called
让我打开一个提前准备好的程序，叫做"打地鼠"。
Whack-A-Mole Might we get a brave volunteer to come up, who is willing to whack a mole with their head, virtually?
我们能不能请一位勇敢的志愿者上来，用头模拟着打鼹鼠？
Maybe-- OK, let's see, how about in way back?
好吧，我想想，后面这位怎么样？
You want to come on down?
你想下来吗？
All right, come on down.
好了，来吧。
Sure, a round of applause for our volunteer.
当然，掌声送给我们的志愿者。
[APPLAUSE]
All right, so here we have-- come on down.
好了，来吧。
AUDIENCE: Hi there.
DAVID J. MALAN: What's your name?
你叫什么名字？
AUDIENCE: I'm Josh.
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, actually, say it into the microphone.
对着麦克风说吧。
AUDIENCE: Hi, I'm Josh.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, nice.
Welcome, Josh.
欢迎， Josh 。
Come on over.
过来吧。
[APPLAUSE]
All right, so same idea here--
好吧，也是一样的。
I'll take the mic back.
我把麦克风拿着。
You'll have to stand in front of the camera.
你得站在摄像头前面。
In just a moment, you're going to have to position your head in a box that your classmate from yesteryear created.
一会儿，你把头放到屏幕中间的框里。
[MUSIC PLAYING]
And we'll start with Beginner.
我们从初级难度开始。
AUDIENCE: OK.
DAVID J. MALAN: So line your head up in the box in a moment.
请把你的头放在框里。
AUDIENCE: All right.
[LAUGHTER]
DAVID J. MALAN: Nice.
12 seconds.
还有 12 秒。
5 seconds.
Notice the score's up to 18 already.
注意分数已经到 18 分了。
Pretty good.
相当不错。
All right, a round of applause for Josh, if we could.
好吧，如果可以的话，请为 Josh 鼓掌。
[APPLAUSE]
So notice how using some fairly simple primitives, things do get interesting pretty fast.
请注意，使用一些相当简单的基元，我们很快就能做出有意思的软件。
And how was that implemented?
那是怎么做到的呢？
Well, there were probably at least four sprites.
嗯，至少得有四个精灵。
So you're not confined to just one cat.
你不能只局限于一只猫。
You can create more and more sprites, change what they look like.
你可以创建越来越多的精灵，改变它们的模样。
So they actually look like a mole, in this case.
在刚才那个例子里面就是鼹鼠。
There's probably some conditionals in there, some loops for 30 seconds.
其中可能包含一些条件判断，一些持续 30 秒的循环。
That's checking if Josh's head's movement is exceeding some value over this way or over this way, then increment something called a variable.
这就是检查 Josh 的头部移动速度是否超过了某个值，
然后递增一个叫做变量（Variable）的东西。
We'll see those too.
我们也会看到的。
Just like in algebra you might have x and y and z, storing values like numbers, so can computer programs, have variables called x or y or z, or more descriptively called Score,
就像代数中的 x、y 和 z，可以像数字一样存储数值，
计算机程序也可以有名为 x 或 y 或 z 的变量，在这个例子里，就是 Score，
as in this case at top right, or another variable called Countdown, typically one word in code, but in this case two words, that just store some value.
或另一个名为 Countdown 的变量，在代码中变量通常是一个单词，
但在本例中是两个单词，它们都是拿来存储一些数值。
*注：多少个单词其实无所谓，但是不能用空格分开，这里的 Countdown 就是连写的。
So there's probably some math going on in there whereby the author of this program just is incrementing
因此，这里可能有一些数学运算，程序的编写者只是在递增这个变量，
that is, adding 1 and 1 every time it detected that a mole had been whacked, in this case, with movement.
也就是说，每次检测到鼹鼠被"捶打"（在这里是"移动"）时，就会一个一个地递增。
So back in the day, I, myself, actually implemented my very first program in Scratch when I was a graduate student, actually, at MIT
想当时我读研究生时，就用 Scratch 实现了我的第一个程序。
cross-registered at MIT, taking a class from MIT's Media Lab, specifically, the lifelong kindergarten group, which is the group that created Scratch, itself.
当时我在麻省理工学院注册交叉参加了一门
Media Lab lifelong kindergarten 小组的课程，这个小组其实就是 Scratch 的创造者。
And the program I wrote all those years ago and still rather cling to is a little something here called Oscartime, that I thought I'd play just a quick excerpt of myself here.
我多年前编写的，至今仍念念不忘的程序是一个叫做 "奥斯卡时间" 的小玩意儿，
我想在这里为自己播放一段简短的片段。
So in this case, consider, as the music starts playing, how this program, which is much more sophisticated, certainly, than the earliest "Say hello" examples we just did might also be implemented.
现在当音乐开始播放时，请想一想这个程序是如何实现的，
当然，这个程序要比我们刚才最早做的 "Say hello" 例子要复杂得多。
Let me go ahead now and click the Green Flag.
现在让我点击绿旗。
[MUSIC - OSCAR THE GROUCH, "I LOVE TRASH"]
OSCAR THE GROUCH: (SINGING) Oh, I love trash.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, so some trash is moving, presumably in some kind of loop from the top.
好的，一些垃圾在动，大概是从顶部开始借助循环移动的。
If I'm touching the mouse cursor, it follows me.
如果用光标碰到，它就会自动跟随。
If I hover over the trash can, it responds.
如果我把鼠标悬停在垃圾桶上，它就会有所反应。
If I let go, in some kind of loop, Oscar pops out, creates a variable with the current score.
如果我松开手，Oscar 就会跳出来，这里其实有一个当前分数的变量。
And it happens again.
再来看一次。
OSCAR THE GROUCH: (SINGING) It's awful, the holes.
And the laces are torn.
A gift from my mother the day I was born.
I love it because it's trash.
Oh, I--
DAVID J. MALAN: It's pretty easy at first but--
一开始很容易，但是——
OSCAR THE GROUCH: (SINGING) --anything dirty or dingy--
DAVID J. MALAN: So I don't need to keep playing this up on stage in front of everyone.
所以我不需要一直在讲台上当着所有人的面玩这个。
So my score is already now up to some 6 or so.
现在我差不多拿了 6 分。
But in a moment, too, you'll see that it's going to escalate.
过一会你就能看到，游戏升级了。
So I'm taking into account some time apparently.
所以我显然考虑到了时间问题。
So now--
OSCAR THE GROUCH: (SINGING) I have here some newspaper, 13 months old.
DAVID J. MALAN: So more and more sprites are suddenly appearing.
所以越来越多的精灵突然出现了。
And notice, that each time they're appearing from a different part of the screen.
注意，每次它们都是从屏幕的不同地方出现的。
That's an illusion, perhaps, too, that-- pick a random number between x and y.
这也许也是一种幻觉—— 真实情况是在 x 和 y 之间随便选一个数字。
So you can actually pick some range of values to have the game constantly changing.
我们实际上可以选择一些数值范围，让游戏产生无数的变化。
And indeed, I'm going to go ahead and click Stop, since I spent like eight hours plus, years ago, making this.
那现在演示得停一停了，好多年前我花了差不多八个多小时来制作这个。
And I can never listen to the song again, not that I should be anyway at this point in my life.
这首歌真听不了一点，反正我现在上课也不应该听。
But this song is synchronized then with a lot of the actions that's happening.
其实在这个程序里，一边在播放这首歌，一边还有其他操作在同步执行。
And ultimately, there's just a lot of building blocks.
归根结底，这都是一些拼图块。
But I didn't sit down and implement Oscartime, as I called it, all at once.
我那时候没什么头绪，不是坐下来就把 "Oscartime" 编写完成的。
I really did take baby steps, so to speak.
可以说，我真的是坐着宝宝巴士过来的。
And I figured out, well, how could I decompose this vision I had at the time to create this game ultimately?
然后我就想，好吧，我该如何分解我当时的愿景，最终创造出这款游戏呢？
And how do I bite off maybe the easiest parts first?
我该如何先蚕食最容易的一部分？
And honestly, the first thing I did was I found this image, and I just dragged and dropped it into Scratch--
老实说，我做的第一件事，就是找到了这张图片，然后把它拖进了 Scratch——
OK, done-- like, lamppost is installed.
好了，搞定—— 灯柱安装完毕。
It doesn't do anything.
它啥也做不了。
It's not interactive.
这不是可以交互的。
But I at least set the stage, so to speak, for the program.
但我至少为这个程序做了铺垫。
Then what else might I have done?
那我还能做点什么？
Well, let me do this.
来看看吧。
Let me go ahead and open up in another editor here an early incarnation of Oscartime by doing this.
我现在要在另一个编辑器中打开 Oscartime 的早期版本。
Let me go into Oscartime here.
让我打开奥斯卡时间。
Let me full screen this.
全屏显示。
And here you have-- let me hide the trash for just a moment-- is what I might call the second version of my program
这就是，让我先把垃圾藏起来，Oscartime 的第二个版本
wherein, at the top right of the stage here, I had the lamppost, which I just dragged and dropped and got going, but then I added an actual sprite.
其中，在舞台的左上方有一个灯柱，我只是拖放过来就行了，
但随后我又添加了一个实际的精灵（垃圾桶）。
And it has to be a sprite if you want it to do things interactively.
如果你想让它进行交互式操作，它就必须是一个精灵。
The lamppost-- not a sprite.
这灯柱不是精灵。
It's just an image a costume, if you will, for the whole stage itself, a backdrop.
这只是整个 Stage 本身的一个形象，一套服装，一个背景。
But this thing is indeed a sprite because it needs to respond to code and events, like dragging and dropping.
但这个垃圾桶确实是一个精灵，因为它需要对代码和事件（如拖放）做出响应。
So what might I have done early on with that code?
那么，我早期可能会用代码做些什么呢？
Well, maybe the first version would have been something like this, whereby my very first version of Oscartime might have said something like, oh, this.
好吧，也许第一个版本会是这样的。
How about, let me control the program as before-- or, rather, events.
差不多，让我像刚才一样控制程序，或者说，控制事件。
When the Green Flag is clicked, what do I want to do?
点击绿旗后，我想做什么？
Well, I want to go ahead and forever do something like this.
好吧，我首先想要一个 forever 的循环。
Forever-- so I want the lid to open up if I touch it.
我希望一碰盖子，盖子就会打开。
So if the cursor gets near the lid, I want the lid to open up.
就是说，如果光标靠近盖子，我就想让盖子打开。
And then if I move away, I want it to close.
如果把光标拿开，我希望它能马上关闭。
So how can I do that?
那我该怎么实现呢？
I want an If, but I just don't want one question, I really want two, a fork in the road that goes left or right, so to speak.
我想要一个 "if" 条件判断，但是延伸出两条路径，可以说是一个向左或向右的岔路口。
And let me grab this puzzle piece here, as I did long ago.
让我像当初上学一样，抓住这块拼图。
So notice, it grows to fill.
注意一下，它可以自动填充到合适的大小。
What's the question I want to ask?
我想问什么问题？
Well, under Sensing, I'm going to go ahead here and say If this trashcan is Touching the Mouse Pointer-- what do I want to do?
应该在 "感应 "功能下，我想问的是，如果鼠标指针碰到了这个垃圾桶，我该怎么办？
Well, I want to change what the trashcan looks like.
我想改变垃圾桶的样子。
And this part, I did in advance of class.
而这部分，我在课前就做好了。
If you go up here to Costumes, this is where all the graphical stuff happens.
如果你进入 Customes 页面，所有导入的图片都会在这里展示。
And you'll see that I imported a whole bunch of different costumes that effectively, much like a video, when you play them quickly, creates the illusion of movement, some animation.
你看到我导入了一大堆不同的服装，当你快速切换这些服装时，
它们就像视频一样，能有效地营造出运动的错觉和一些动画效果。
But it's really just dot, dot, dot, dot, dot-- different images showing on the screen.
但实际上，屏幕上显示的只是点（像素）、点、点、点、点——不同的图像而已。
Well, some of these costumes are called like Oscar1, Oscar2.
其中一些服装被称为 Oscar1、Oscar2 。
Oscar1 is closed.
Oscar1 是关着的垃圾桶。
Oscar2 is open.
Oscar 2 是开着的垃圾桶。
So let's just deal with those first.
所以我们先解决垃圾桶的开关触发吧。
So if I'm touching the mouse pointer, let me go under-- how about Looks?
所以，如果垃圾桶接触鼠标指针，让我切到下面外观栏。
And we didn't use this before, but there's this block,
我们以前没有用过，但有这么个东西——
Switch Costume to Something Else.
"改变服装到另一个"。
I'm going to drag and drop this inside of the If.
我要把这个拖放到 if 块里面来。
And notice it's a little bit indented.
注意它有一点点缩进。
I'm going to change it not to Oscar8, but Oscar2.
我要把它改成 Oscar2，而不是 Oscar8。
Otherwise, If Not Touching the Mouse Pointer-- this is the other direction in the fork in the road-- let's go ahead and switch the costume back to what I described as Oscar1.
否则，如果垃圾桶没碰到鼠标指针—— 这是岔路口的另一个方向—— 我们得把服装换回 Oscar1。
So let me run this program.
让我来运行下这个程序。
And not much of interest is happening yet.
目前还没有什么值得注意的事情发生。
But notice, if I move the cursor up, down-- but how is that working?
但注意了，如果我将光标向上、向下... 但这是怎么做到的呢？
It's just changing the costume that's being overlaid on the sprite.
这只是在改变叠加在精灵上的服装。
So it looks like interactivity, but you are really just changing the aesthetics.
因此，这看起来像是在与垃圾桶交互，但实际上你只是在改变一些贴图。
And we humans are just kind of assuming, oh, it's opening up.
我们人类就会想当然，哦，它正在打开。
Well, no, it's just changing a costume.
嗯不，只是换一套服装。
So here's the difference.
这就是区别所在。
The high-level abstraction-- trashcan opening.
高级抽象—— 打开垃圾桶。
The lower-level implementation detail-- costume changing, creating that illusion.
较低层次的实现细节—— 换装，营造幻觉。
And if I want it to look prettier, I could just have many other costumes and go boom, boom, boom, boom, boom to create more frames per second, if you will.
如果我想让它看起来更美观，可以多导入一些服装，
然后快速切换，在一秒内展示更多帧。
So I need to do one other thing.
我还需要做一件事。
Maybe if I accidentally leave the trashcan open, let me make one change here.
也许在最开始垃圾桶不小心打开了，让我在这里做一个改变。
Let me make sure that the very first thing
让我确保正确的初始化，
I do when the Green Flag is clicked, is always start with the trashcan closed because otherwise, you might accidentally leave it open.
当点击绿旗时，我总是先关闭垃圾桶，避免它呈现打开状态。
So this gets me into some default state.
这样，我就初始化了一个默认状态。
So now it's always closed until I manually hover over it instead.
因此现在它保持关闭，直到我手动将鼠标悬停在它上面。
Well, what might I have done next?
那么，接下来我要干啥？
Well, if I wanted to introduce something like the trash, I need a second sprite.
如果我想引入垃圾之类的东西，需要第二个精灵。
And here, in advance, I grabbed the image already.
在这里，我已经提前找好了图片。
Let me pretend that this never happened.
让我假装一下，从头来一遍。
Let me drag this away here.
把这个拖走。
And now I have nothing in my code area for this piece of trash.
现在，我的代码区里没有关于垃圾的任何东西。
But it is the second sprite.
垃圾是第二个精灵。
And all I did was I clicked on the little cat plus icon here, created a second sprite.
我所做的就是点击这里的小猫加号图标，创建第二个精灵。
I named it trash.
我把它命名为垃圾。
I added a costume for it.
我为它添加了一套服装。
Sort of the aesthetic stuff, I did in advance.
我提前做了一些提升美观度的工作。
But here I'll do now the code.
现在要完成代码部分。
How do I want to do this?
我们想要什么效果？
Well, how about when the Green Flag is clicked, for the trash can,
点击绿旗后，垃圾桶就会出现，
I want the trash can in parallel to do--
我想让垃圾桶和垃圾并行地做自己的事情，
I want the trash, the piece of trash, to do its own thing.
我想让垃圾自己往下掉。
So what I want it to do is maybe let's do Motion, how about?
所以，我想让它移动起来，怎么样？
And let's go to a specific coordinate.
让我们来看一个具体的坐标。
Now, there's a lot of options here.
现在，这里有很多选择。
There's Turning, Go to a Random Position, Go to x,y, Glide, more elegantly.
比如说 "转弯"、"转到随机位置"、"转到 x,y 坐标"、"滑行" 等等的优雅功能。
There's a lot of different ways to implement movement.
有很多不同的方法来实现运动。
I just want it to go to a very specific location first.
我只是想让它先到达一个确切的位置。
So I'm just going to go to x,y first.
所以我打算让它到 x,y 坐标处。
And I'm going to say x, how about, will be-- let's not hardcode this.
我看看 x 要设置为多少... 噢，我们还是不要硬编码好了。
Let's just have it be-- well, let's do it at 0, initially, and then 240.
好吧，x 从 0 开始，然后 y 是 240。
So-- whoops-- let's do 0,240 so that this piece of trash always starts at the top middle of the screen.
0,240 ，这样这块垃圾就总是出现在屏幕的中上部。
If you think back to that coordinate system, 0,0 is in the middle.
如果你回想一下那个坐标系，0,0 在正中间。
240 is straight above it.
240 在正顶上。
All right, now, after I do that, what do I want to do?
好了现在，在做完这些之后，我还想做什么？
Well, how about I control this thing by forever falling.
我想控制让它永远下落。
Now, how do I make the trash move?
现在，我该如何让垃圾移动呢？
We haven't seen this puzzle piece yet.
我们还没看到有这块拼图。
But under Motion, the very first thing is called Move Some Number of Steps.
但在 Motion 下，有个东西叫做 "移动一定步数"。
By default, it's 10.
默认值为 10。
But we'll do it more simply.
我们简单点就行了。
Let me go ahead and move-- oh, sorry.
接着看，等等...
Move is going to move it in whatever direction it's facing.
Move 会让它朝自己面向的方向运动。
I only want it to move down.
可我只想让它向下移动。
So here, even I'm getting confused as to how many different ways there are to do things.
在 Scratch，连我自己都搞不清楚到底有多少种不同的方法。
What I thing I want to do is this.
我想做的事情是这样的。
Let me only change my y-axis as follows.
我只想要对 y 轴的坐标做改动。
So here's another puzzle piece called Change y.
这里还有一块拼图，叫做 "变化 y"。
So again, y is the vertical.
再说一遍，y 是垂直方向。
So let me just change y by one pixel downward at a time, so -1 one pixel at a time.
设置每次向下改变一个像素，也就是每次让 y -1。
So it's kind of slow.
有点慢。
And I think now--
我想想啊现在，
I think that's it.
差不多就完事了。
Let me hit Stop.
让我先停止现在的。
Notice that my trashcan is still going to be interactive.
请注意，垃圾桶仍将是可以交互的。
I haven't changed or deleted that code.
我没有更改或删除这部分代码。
I've just added now code for my piece of trash.
只是为垃圾添加了新代码。
If I click the Green Flag, notice that-- after I enable it-- let me start that again.
如果我点开始，请看—— 我得先让它可见，再重新开始。
I had it hidden for before class.
刚才上课点了下隐藏。
But let me enable it now--
不过现在要开启了。
Green Flag, notice it starts dead center, at x equals 0, y equals 240, and it's dropping one pixel at a time.
开始，注意它是从上面的正中心出现的，x 等于 0，y 等于 240，每次下降一个像素。
If that seems a little boring, we can change it to -10 pixels at a time and, boom, it's done.
如果这看起来有点无聊，我们可以把它改成每次 -10 像素，然后，砰的一下它就完成了。
So that's how you might change the speed of a program.
这就是改变速度的方式。
But I'm going to leave it more simply as -1.
不过我还是把它调回 -1。
And honestly, it would be nice if it doesn't always start from the top.
老实说，如果垃圾不总是从那里出现，那就更好了。
Otherwise, this game is not going to be very interactive.
否则，这个游戏的互动性就不会很强。
I'm literally going to be grabbing the trash from the same place every time.
我每次都要从同一个地方抓垃圾，这简直了。
So why don't I, instead, Stop this.
为什么不试试呢？
Let me go under Operators, and let's pick a random number.
让我在 Operators 类别下，找到 "随机选取一个数字"。
So let me change the hardcoded-- the manually inputted-- 0, and let's make x be somewhere between 0
因此，让我丢掉刚才的硬编码，手动输入的 0，让 x 介于 0 和某个值之间
so in the middle and all the way over to-- what was it-- oh, I got my numbers wrong-- 240 and my y will be 180.
所以从中间一直到... 啥来着... 哦，我把数字弄错了，是 240，这个 y 应该是 180。
Sorry, I got my x and my y confused.
不好意思，我把 x 和 y 搞混了。
So let me play this again.
让我再启动一遍。
And now we have a game that's more like games you might have played growing up or even now, like there's some randomness to it.
而现在，我们的游戏更像你先前玩过的游戏，带有一些随机性。
So the CPU, so to speak, is doing something more interesting.
可以说，CPU 正在做一些更有趣的事情。
Let me run it again.
我再来跑一遍。
Now it's a little to the left.
现在比刚才更偏左。
Let me run it again.
再跑一遍。
Now it's a little more to the left.
往左移了一点。
Again-- now it's back to the right.
现在又回到右边一些了。
So randomness just makes games more interesting.
因此，随机性可以让游戏更有趣。
And this is why when you play any video game, if different things are happening, there's probably just some randomness.
这就是为什么你玩的几乎任何电子游戏，都带点不同性和随机性。
And it's quantized as just a simple number.
随机性被量化为一个简简单单的数字。
Now, I think I just need one final flourish here, if I may.
现在，我想需要在这里做最后的铺垫。
Let me go ahead and add this.
让我来补充一下。
How about Events-- or rather-- yes, Events.
那 "事件" 呢？ 这里的 Events。
When Green Flag is clicked, I can do multiple things within the same sprite.
当点击绿旗时，我可以在同一个精灵上同时执行几个操作。
They don't all have to be attached to the same one.
它们不一定都要连接到同一个 "when green flag clicked" 块上。
Let me go ahead and forever go ahead and do something else.
我再建一个，拖过来 forever 循环做点别的事。
How about, Whenever the Trash is-- how about-- Touching the Trash Can-- so Forever If-- let's see, I need a Sensing block.
不如来个 "每当垃圾触碰垃圾桶，就..."
So how about, Is Touching-- not the Mouse Pointer, this time, but Touching Oscar himself there.
那么，需要一个 touching 块，这次不选择鼠标指针了，而是 "触摸 Oscar"。
Now let's see what happens.
现在让我们看看会发生什么。
All right, so let's go ahead and click the Green Flag.
好了，让我们点点绿旗。
Now I go down over here and let go.
现在，我把垃圾抓下来，然后放手。
OK, I kind of want it to go into the trash can.
好吧，我其实有点想把它扔进垃圾桶。
How do I make it go into the trash can?
怎样才能把它扔进垃圾桶？
How can we take this high-level idea, put trash into the trash can, and make it seem to disappear?
我们怎样才能从底层实现这个高层次的想法——扔进垃圾桶，让它看起来消失不见？
Logically, what could we do?
从逻辑上讲，我们要怎么做？
Yeah--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, so when it touches it, let's have it disappear.
对的，当它俩碰到的时候，让垃圾消失。
So I could hide it.
我们可以把它藏起来。
Or honestly, if the game is going to be ongoing, like it was, letting me drop more and more trash, let me just have it go ahead and pick a new random location.
如果游戏要持续下去，就像演示那样，
需要扔下越来越多的垃圾，那就让它继续随机选择一个新的地点再次出现吧。
So let me do this.
我来试试
Let me go ahead and Copy this puzzle piece up here and Duplicate.
我想复制这块拼图。
And I don't want the whole thing, sorry.
我不想要这一整块，不好意思。
Let me get rid of this.
把这个扔掉。
Let me just do this.
挪过来。
Let me go back to some random location at the top.
让垃圾回到顶部的某个随机位置。
So now notice what happens.
现在请注意发生了什么。
If I click and drag on it-- here it goes-- and I let go, it looks like it's going into the trash can because it snaps back up to some random location.
如果我点击并拖动它，然后松手，
它看起来就像被扔进垃圾桶，因为它实际是随机地弹回到某个初始位置。
Now, the only thing I'm not doing really is keeping track of any kind of score.
现在，我唯一没有做的事情就是记分。
And it turns out, if I full screen this, it's not going to be draggable, by default.
事实证明，如果我全屏显示，默认情况下它是不可拖动的。
So just as a corner case, so to speak, something that you might trip over otherwise, let me go ahead and under, let's see, Sensing, it turns out I also need this for the piece of trash.
这算是一个边界条件，你可能会被卡住。
让我们看看，Sensing 里面，原来我还需要设置这个垃圾桶...
There's this way of setting, in Scratch, a sprite to be draggable or not draggable.
在 Scratch 中，可以设置精灵是否可拖动。
I need to explicitly make it draggable so that when I do full screen this thing now, it still remains draggable and someone like myself can play it again and again.
我需要明确规定它是可拖动的，这样当我现在全屏显示这个东西时，
它仍然是可拖动的，多试几次都行。
Well, how about we supplement this with one final flourish?
那么，我们最后再锦上添花一下如何？
Why don't we keep track now of the user score?
为什么我们现在不记录玩家得分？
So how about, when the user actually drags the piece of trash to the trash can, let me go under Variables here, where, in advance, I've already made myself a variable called Score.
当玩家真的把垃圾拖到垃圾桶时，让我提前在变量栏下，创建一个 score 变量。
I could have called it x or y or z or ABC, but that's not very descriptive.
我本可以把它叫做 x、y、z 或 ABC，但这样太不贴切了。
In programming, you typically give things a more descriptive English, or some other language, name.
在编程过程中，你通常会给东西起一个描述性的英文名称。
So I called this one Score.
因此，我把这个变量命名为 score。
So how do I want to do this in my Score?
那我要怎么让 score 显示出得分呢？
Well, let me go ahead and initially set this game score to 0 at the very top of one of these scripts-- one of these programs up here.
接着整，在这些代码的最顶端将 score 设置为 0，在一个地方设置就行了。
And then any time my piece of trash is touching
每当垃圾被碰到时，
Oscar, let's not just jump to the top, let's change the score by 1 up here.
对于 Oscar，我们不要直接跳到最上面，先在这里把 score 增加 1。
So now notice, If Touching Oscar, Change the Score-- that is,
"如果触碰到 Oscar，就增加 score" ，就是这个意思，
Add 1 to the Score-- and then Pick a new Random location.
让 score 加 1，然后选择一个新的随机位置。
And now Green Flag-- let's do this slowly.
点下绿旗，我们慢慢看。
Here it goes.
开始了。
The trashcan opens.
垃圾桶打开了。
I let go.
And now notice, at the top left of my program, notice the score is now 2.
注意看程序的左上角，score 现在是 2。
Notice the score, if I do this again, is about to become 3.
如果我再做一次，score 就要变成 3 了。
And so here we have building blocks, literally, of making this program better and better and better.
所以我们在不断地添砖加瓦，让这个程序越来越棒。
And so, indeed, that's how you generally approach solving any problem with code, be it in Scratch or C or Python or some other.
因此，不管是用 Scratch、C、Python 还是其他语言，
用代码解决任何问题时，一般都是这个过程。
You take this vision you might have or some vision you've been assigned in a homework assignment and try to break it down into these constituent parts and just pluck off the easy ones first.
你要把自己的想法，或家庭作业中布置给你的要求，
分解成不同的部分，先把容易的部分做出来。
Put the lamp post there first, and at least feel like you're making some progress.
像我先把灯柱放在那儿，至少会让人觉得你取得了一些进展。
Then pluck off something like the trash can, and just make it do a little thing.
然后拖来垃圾桶之类的东西，让它有简单的行为。
And it doesn't have to be in some same order here.
我们做的顺序不一定要相同。
I could have done this in a million different ways.
完成这个程序亦有无数种方式。
But figure out what the small pieces are that, ultimately, like a few of the problems we've solved today, assemble into a greater solution there too.
只要想清楚，这些小碎片最终会像我们今天解决的几个问题一样，组合成一个更完善的解决方案。
So that you have now a mental model for these types of blocks and others, let's return for a moment to this.
现在你已经初步建立关于这些类型的积木的思维模式，让我们再回顾一下。
We saw a moment ago that when I started saying, "Hello, David," and nesting those puzzle pieces, we had a whole different paradigm altogether.
我们刚刚看到，当我开始说 "Hello, David"，
并嵌套这些积木时，我们有了一个有点新奇的思维模式。
My input for that second version of, "Hello, world," was to now pass in, for instance, "What's Your Name?" into my function, called Ask.
第二个版本的 "Hello, world" 的输入，是先将 "What's Your Name?" 传递给 Ask 函数...
That gave me not a side effect, but what I called, again, a return value, called Answer, by default, in Scratch.
这没有产生副作用，而是有一个返回值，Scratch 默认称之为 answer。
And now notice and recall, when I had that same output become the input to my next block, it looked a little something like this--
现在请注意并回想一下，当我把 ask 函数的输出 answer，
变成下一个函数的输入时，它看起来有点像这样——
Say.
So how does this type of block and this nesting, this stacking of blocks, fit into the same mental model?
积木相互嵌套堆叠，但归根结底是同一种思维模式。
*注：思维模式指，接受输入、函数中进行算法运算、最终得到输出，这个过程。
Well, same idea-- my input for that part of the story is now taking in not one input but two-- two arguments-- "hello" and the answer from before.
同样的想法—— 对于这个 join 函数，它的输入不是单个，而是两个参数—— "hello" 和 询问名字，我们输入的 answer 变量。
The function, in this case, is that new block called Join.
在这种情况下，函数是那个叫做 join 的新积木。
The output thereof is, "Hello, David," which itself became-- if we sort of animate this-- the input to my final function, which indeed was still Say.
其输出是 "Hello, David"，这个输出又成为了最终函数 Say 的输入。
And this is only to say-- no pun intended-- that almost everything that you do with these puzzle pieces
这只是说，在无意间，几乎你使用这些积木做的所有事情，
be it in the context of Oscartime or the mole whacking or even just something simple like, "Hello, world," will ultimately fit into that relatively simple mental model there.
无论是在 Oscartime 、打地鼠游戏，还是仅仅是像 "Hello, world" 这样的简单程序，
最终都满足这个理解上去很简单的思维模式。
*注：思维模式指，接受 0 个或多个输入，函数中进行算法运算，最终得到输出或是副作用。程序就是这个过程的不断嵌套。
Now, I thought we'd end by taking a look at just a couple of final examples.
我们最后再看几个例子。
These ones, too, made by some of your predecessors.
这些也是上过 CS50 课程的前辈的作品。
And for this, I thought we would not write code together, but read it instead.
对这些程序，我想不用一起写一遍代码了，但是要读一读他们是怎么写的。
And so allow me to open up one other example here that will show us a few different versions of a program that a predecessor made.
我想在这里打开另一个例子，展示一下前人制作的程序的几个不同版本。
Give me just a moment here.
稍微等一等。
And we'll see how we might build up to something even more interactive.
我们来看看如何让程序更有互动性。
And in just a moment, we'll see something they called Ivy's Hardest Game, focused here on these particular mechanics.
稍后，我们将看到 "常春藤最难游戏"，重点是观察其中的特殊机制。
So here is version 0, so to speak, of this program, wherein the goal was to create a game where you have to get out of some kind of maze.
这是这个程序的第 0 版，这个游戏的目标是走出迷宫。
And you have to get out, in this case, the Harvard crest from this maze.
你要带领哈佛大学的校徽从这个迷宫中走出。
Let me go ahead and just hit Play on this Green Flag so you can see what the first building block for this program might have been.
我来按下开始键，就能看到这个程序的初版是什么样子了。
Notice that my hand here is actually on the Arrow keys on my keyboard.
请注意，我的手是放在键盘的方向键上的。
And it seems that by moving up, down, left, or right, this little crest on the screen responds in exactly that way.
似乎只要上下左右移动，屏幕上的这个小徽章就会跟着反应。
Now, let's hypothesize for just a moment.
现在，让我们猜想一下。
Even though we've not done anything quite like this before, how might this code be implemented?
尽管我们以前没有做过类似的任务，这种代码要如何实现呢？
How do you get a sprite, be it a cat or a crest, to respond to keys on a keyboard-- might you think intuitively?
如何让一个精灵（无论是猫还是徽章）对键盘上的按键做出反应，你能用直觉想一想吗？
Yeah--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, there could be something sensing what key you're pressing on.
是的，可能有什么东西，能感应到你按的是什么键。
And if you do it again in forever a loop, you'll just constantly be listening for keystrokes.
把这个操作放在一个 forever 循环里面，其实就在不间断地监听按键。
And this is how, like, every piece of software nowadays works.
如今，每款软件都是这样运行的。
It's constantly waiting for your phone to be tapped or something to be typed on the screen.
它一直在等待你轻触手机或在屏幕上输入内容。
So let me go ahead and look inside of this existing program here.
所以，我们先来看看这个程序的内部模样。
And there's more going on, but we'll take a quick glance what's actually going on.
只展示一部分，我们快速浏览一下实际情况就好。
Well, up here at top left, notice, we just have Go To x Equals 0 and y Equals 0.
注意看左上方，这里有 "移动到 x 0 和 y 0"。
That means put the Harvard crest dead center in the middle of the stage.
也就是说，把哈佛大学的校徽放在舞台的正中间。
Then we have Forever two functions that we made in advance as custom functions--
然后，这里有两个自定义函数，分别是
Listen for Keyboard, Feel for Walls.
监听键盘按键，感知墙壁。
So it's doing two things at once.
因此，它同时在做两件事。
It's forever listening for the keyboard-- up, down, left, right-- and feeling for the walls, in the sense that if I get too far to the left,
首先它一直在监听玩家按下键盘的方向键，并做出对应的行动，
还有感知墙壁以免角色穿墙而过。
I don't want it to keep moving past that black wall.
我们不想让它穿过那堵黑墙。
And if it moves too far to the right, I don't want it to blow through that wall either.
如果它一直向右，也不想让它撞穿右边那堵墙。
So it's going to do two things constantly, listening for keyboard and feeling for walls, so to speak.
因此，它要不断循环做两件事：监听键盘和感知墙壁。
And how are those implemented?
内部又是如何实现的呢？
Well, this one's a bit long.
啊，这个有点长。
But on the left here is Listen for Keyboard.
左侧是 "监听键盘"。
So this pink puzzle piece, Listen for Keyboard, first checks If the Key Up Arrow is Pressed, question mark,
这块粉色拼图 "监听键盘"，首先要检查 "是否按下上箭头键"，
Boolean expression in a conditional, Change y By 1.
如果满足，就让 y 增加 1。
That means, move it up 1.
也就是说把徽章上移 1 个像素。
Else If the Key Down Arrow is Pressed, then Change y by -1, and similar for Left Arrow, similar for Right Arrow.
否则，如果按下箭头键，则将 y-1，左右箭头的操作类似。
And even though there's not a loop in this pink function, there is where I'm using it.
尽管在这个粉红色函数中没有循环，但在使用它的地方却有循环。
So it's constantly being asked again and again.
所以这个条件语句在反复被检查。
How about feeling for walls?
什么是墙壁感知？
Well, over here to the right-- it's a little cut off-- but here you have, If Touching Left Wall,
在这个右边，有点太长了，它是说如果接触到左墙...
Change x by 1.
就让 x 加一。
So if you hit the wall, it's too late.
所以如果它碰到了墙，那就太晚了。
You're kind of blowing through it already.
你已经穿过它了。
So I want to move it back one pixel so it's no longer touching that wall.
所以我想让它后退一个像素，这样它就不再撞到那堵墙了。
Similarly, if it's touching the right wall, I want to back it up one pixel so it's no longer touching that wall.
同样地，如果它碰到了右墙，我也让它后退一个像素，就不再撞到那堵墙了。
So it's kind of like bouncing off ever so slightly so that it doesn't slip through that actual wall.
所以它就像是微微地反弹，这样就不会从真正的墙壁滑过。
And what are those walls?
那些墙是什么？
Well, notice down here, it's just a simple sprite with a black line that I've oriented vertically instead of horizontally.
注意看下面，这只是一个简单的精灵，带有一条黑线，我把它的方向改为垂直而不是水平。
And that's just so that I can ask questions of these other two sprites.
这样我就可以询问 logo 和两面墙的关系了。
Now, that gives me that form of interactivity.
这样就有了交互的可能性。
What more can I now do?
我现在还能做什么？
Well, what if we make things a little more interactive here?
那么，如果我们加强一下这里的互动性呢？
Let me go ahead and see inside version 1 our second.
让我来看看第 1 版的第二部分。
And let me propose what's going to happen here.
让我介绍一下这里会发生什么。
Well, how might we add a little something like Yale into the mix?
那么，我们怎样才能添加进耶鲁大学校徽呢？
Well, what's Yale going to do when I hit the Green Flag now based on this code?
来看看这段代码，当我点击绿旗时，耶鲁会怎么做呢？
Any hunches?
有什么猜测吗？
Here is the code for my Yale sprite.
这是我的耶鲁角色的代码。
Yeah--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, it's kind of going to be an adversarially by blocking my path, theoretically, if I keep writing more code.
是的，理论上来说，它会以对抗性的方式阻挡我的路径，如果我继续编写更多代码的话。
So why?
It too goes to the middle of the screen.
它也会移动到屏幕的中央。
It points in direction 90 degrees.
它指向 90 度的方向。
So similarly, there's a whole degree system as well.
同样地，还有一个完整的方向系统。
And it forever asks this.
它会不断地询问这个问题：
If Touching the Left Wall Or-- notice the green block--
如果碰到了左墙，注意绿色的积木，或者是
Touching the Right Wall, then just Turn around 180 Degrees.
碰到了右墙，那就转身180度。
And indeed, if you think this through logically, that just means you're bouncing this way and this way by just flipping yourself around 180 degrees for just this Yale sprite.
实际上，如果你逻辑上思考一下，这意味着你会把方向调转180度，
以这种或这种方式弹跳，耶鲁角色只会在这个范围内来回移动。
So if I go ahead and zoom in on this and click the Green Flag,
我放大点然后点开始，
I can still move up and down.
我仍然可以四处移动。
But Yale is just kind of doing this all day long, back and forth and back and forth, forever.
但耶鲁角色将会不断地这样来回移动，来回移动，永远不停。
Nothing bad happens if I try to go through it.
如果我试图穿过它，也不会发生什么坏事。
But we could add that, certainly, to the mix.
但我们当然可以把这个逻辑添加其中。
In fact, let's add one final feature before we play this particular game.
在我们开始玩这个游戏之前，让我们再添加一个最终功能。
And let me go ahead and open up the final version of these building blocks that adds MIT to the mix.
我来打开最终版本，让 MIT 也参与进来。
So here is MIT.
这是 MIT 的标志。
Someone want to explain what this code does?
有人可以解释一下这段代码的作用吗？
And this is what we're doing.
这正是我们正在做的。
This itself is a skill.
这本身就是一项技能。
Reading someone else's code and understanding it is half of the part of programming besides writing.
在编写代码以外，阅读他人的代码并理解，也是编程的重要一部分。
Yeah--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, it's chasing down the Harvard logo outline.
是的，它在追逐哈佛标志的轮廓。
So this is apparently the name of the costume that this student made, Harvard logo outline.
这个显然是学生制作的 costome 名称，哈佛标志轮廓。
And apparently, it goes to a random position first.
显然，它首先会移动到一个随机的位置。
But then it forever points to Harvard.
然后，它会永远指向哈佛。
So no matter where I'm moving it, up, down, left, or right, MIT is being a little more strategic than Yale, bouncing back and forth like this.
所以无论我将它移动到哪里，上下左右，MIT 都比耶鲁的来回反弹更有策略性，就像这样。
So let's go ahead and play this one in full screen.
那么，我们继续在全屏模式下玩这个游戏吧。
And here we have a Green Flag.
先点一下绿旗。
So if I move up, MIT, rather strategically, is following me no matter where I go.
所以如果我向上移动，无论我走到哪里，MIT 都会相当策略地跟随着我。
All right, so still, nothing bad happens.
好吧，所以仍然，没有发生任何不好的事情。
But now it's struggling, right?
但是现在它有些挣扎，对吧？
It's going up, down, up, down.
它上上下下地动，尽管我没有移动。
It's trying to follow me even though I'm not moving.
即使我一动不动，它还是试图跟着我。
So we need some final flourishes.
所以我们需要一些最后的点缀。
And so I think, for this, we need perhaps one final volunteer.
所以我想，我们可能需要最后一位志愿者。
After this, cake awaits for everyone outside, as is an end of first lecture CS50 tradition.
之后，蛋糕在外面等着大家，这是 CS50 第一讲结束时的传统。
Would you like to come up and be our volunteer?
你愿意上前来当我们的志愿者吗？
[APPLAUSE]
All right.
And so this will be the actual version but written by one of your predecessors that I'll full screen here.
所以这将是由你们的前辈之一编写的实际版本，我会在这里将其全屏显示。
It's going to stitch together all of these same primitives and more, but add the notion of scores and lives
它将组合所有这些相同的基本元素，以及更多内容，但会增加分数和生命的概念，
so that there's actually a goal, which in this case is to move the Harvard crest to constantly pursue the character on the right-hand side so that your sprite touches that one.
我们的目标是让哈佛校徽追到右边的角色，并且不能碰到其他学校的徽章。
Would you like to introduce yourself?
能自我介绍一下吗？
AUDIENCE: Hi, my name is Mohammed.
DAVID J. MALAN: All right, wonderful.
Welcome aboard.
欢迎加入。
And here we come with some instructions and final flourish if we want to keep the lights up but perhaps increase the music.
这里有一些说明和最后的点缀，保持灯光亮起，增加点音量！
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[MUSIC - MC HAMMER, "U CAN'T TOUCH THIS"]
MC HAMMER: (SINGING) You can't this.
You can't touch this.
DAVID J. MALAN: Notice he is using the up, down, left, right.
注意，他在使用上、下、左、右的按键。
But there's many more walls now.
但现在有更多的墙壁了。
First level's pretty easy.
第一关还相当容易。
But now Yale's in the mix, bouncing back and forth.
但现在耶鲁也加入了，来回弹跳。
Again, pretty easy.
同样，相当容易。
Now there's two Yale's at slightly different positions.
现在有两个略微不同位置的耶鲁。
MIT is coming soon.
MIT 很快就会加入。
But first, we have three Yales.
但首先这关，有三个耶鲁。
MC HAMMER: (SINGING) As such.
And this is a beat, uh, you can't touch.
DAVID J. MALAN: Very nice.
很好。
[APPLAUSE]
MC HAMMER: (SINGING) I told you, homeboy, you can't touch this.
Yeah, that's how it look when you know you can't touch this.
Look at my eyes, man, you can't touch this.
Yo, let me bust the funky lyrics. you can't touch this.
Yo, let me bust the funky lyrics.
Fresh new kicks and pants, you got to like that.
Now, you know you want to dance.
So move out of your seat and get a fly--
DAVID J. MALAN: You got to go quick.
MC HAMMER: (SINGING) Catch this beat while it's rolling.
Hold on.
Pump a little bit, and let them know what's going on, like that, like that.
Cold on a mission, so fall on back.
Let them know that you're too much and this a beat, uh, they can't touch.
Yo, I told you.
You can't touch this.
[APPLAUSE]
Yo, sound the bell.
School's in, sucker.
You can't touch this.
Give me a song, a rhythm.
Making them sweat, that's what I'm giving them.
Now they know, you talk about the Hammer, you talking about a show that's hyped and tight.
Singers are sweating, so pass them a wipe or a tape to learn.
What's it going to take--
DAVID J. MALAN: Second-to-last level.
倒数第二关。
MC HAMMER: (SINGING) Legit.
Either work hard or you might as well quit.
That's word because you know--
DAVID J. MALAN: Last level.
最后一关！
MC HAMMER: (SINGING) You can't touch this.
DAVID J. MALAN: Hey!
嘿！！
[LAUGHS]
[APPLAUSE]
Congrats.
All right, that's it for CS50.
好了，CS50 到此为止。
Welcome.
Cake is now served.
蛋糕已经上桌。
We'll see you next time.
我们下次再见。
[PROJECTOR CLICKING]
[MUSIC PLAYING]